what's the meaning of life they have the
that God made you halfway I don't know
how to accomplish something great for
everyone to live in peace and happiness
is that we make of it live it as much as
you can
I really don't know I only 12 to live it
know that everything happens for a
reason how you as a person react to
challenges be happy and do what you love
to be happy to be happy and to help
others with everyday to the fullest
follow your dreams
imperfection taking risks to live in
honest life love God and love people
find happiness and bring happiness to
other people's lives to be happy hearing
stories telling stories living stories
joy I'm still figuring it out love love
freedom living in your purpose life is
meant to be lived being happy to love
people being a good person and enjoying
your life Jalloh to evolve and become
magnificent to enjoy life to be happy
family the pursuit of happiness so be
grateful humble kind following your
dreams to enjoy every minute of it love
and friendship to do the best that you
can and to be grateful for every moment
that is great 42 who knows love to be
kind to love one another
connecting loving giving love giving
what's angst today in perspective is
just a bump in the road tomorrow finding
joy I'm still on the path to finding out
love have lots of fun try not to hurt
anybody in the process just life and
said learning and being humble and being
grateful to find a purpose for yourself
and others making a difference in the
world
to love one another finding what you are
here to do what you God puts you on
earth to do wonder curiosity and humor
there is no meaning it's just what you
make of it breathing one must be happy
with who they are and try to make other
people happy waking up every morning and
being here to do good deeds struggling
waking up in the morning and beginning
the day the rest of it fills in