it's very commonly said
that the root of most human unhappiness
is the sense that one's life has no
meaning
this is i suppose most frequently said
in
circles interested in psychotherapy
because the feeling of meaninglessness
is often equated
with
the existence of neurosis
and so many
activities into which one is encouraged
to enter
philosophies one is encouraged to
believe and religions one is encouraged
to join
are commended on them on the basis of
the fact that they give life a meaning
i think it's very fascinating to think
out what
this idea itself means or what it is
intended when it's said that
life has to have a purpose
[Music]
well now
it's pretty obvious i think
that when we talk about life having or
not having a meaning
we're not using quite the ordinary sense
of the word meaning
as the attribute of a sign
[Music]
we're not saying are we that we expect
this natural universe to behave as if it
were a collection of words
signifying something other than
themselves
it isn't the point of view which would
reduce
our lives in the world merely to the
status of signs
[Music]
all that is mortal or all that is
perishable
is but a symbol
and so
a symbol of what
what do we want to feel what would
satisfy us as being
the meaning
behind this world
it's so
often you know that we don't follow our
ideas and our desires through
most of the things that we want very
fervently
are things that we've only half glimpsed
our ideals are very often suggestions
hints
and we don't know really exactly what we
mean when we think about it
[Music]
but there is this obscure sense
in which
we feel that life ought to have
significance
and be a symbol in at least that sense
if not just so uh buried a symbol as a
mere sign
or it also may mean that
life is meaningful
an individual feels that his life
amounts to something when he belongs
and fits in with the execution of some
uh group enterprise
he feels he belongs in a plan
and this too seems to give people a
sense of great satisfaction
but we have to pursue that question
further too
why is it
that a plan why is it that
uh fellowship with other people
gives the sense of meaning
does it come down perhaps to another
sense of meaning
that life is felt to be meaningful when
one is fully satisfying one's biological
urges
including
the sense of hunger
the sense of love
the sense of uh
self-expression in
activity and so on
but then again we have to push that
inquiry further
what do
our biological urges really point
towards
are they just however
things
always projected towards a future his
biology and its uh
process is nothing but going on towards
going on towards going on
or there's a fourth and more theological
sense of the meaning of life
[Music]
in all theistic religions at any rate
the meaning of life is god himself
in other words all this world means a
person
it means a heart it means an
intelligence
and the relationship of love between god
and man is the meaning of the world
the sight of god is the glory of god
and so on but again here there's
something to be further pursued
what is it that we want
in
love with
a person
and even a person in the sense of the
lord god
what is the content of it what is it
that we are really yearning after
well now if we go back to the first
point
taking goethe's words that all that is
transitory is but a symbol
and that we want to feel that all things
have significance
it does seem to me that there's a sense
in which we often use the word
significance
where the word
seems to be chosen quite uh naturally
and yet at the same time it's not quite
the right word
we say for example often of music
that we feel it to be significant
when just at the same time we don't mean
that it expresses some particular kind
of
concretely
realizable emotion
and certainly it's not imitating the
noises of nature
a program music you know would simply
imitate something else and it
deliberately sets out to express sadness
or joy or whatever
uh is not the kind of thing i mean
so often when one listens to the
beautiful arabesque character
of uh the baroque composers
bach or
vivaldi
it is
felt to be significant
not because it means something other
than itself
but because it is so satisfying as it is
and we use then this word significance
so often
in those moments when
uh
our impetuous
seeking fulfillment cools down
and we give ourselves a little space to
watch things
as if they were worth watching ordinary
things
and in those moments when our inner
turmoil has really quietened
we find significance in things that we
wouldn't expect to find significant at
all
i mean this is after all the art of
those photographers
who have such genius in turning the
camera
towards
such things as peeling paint on an old
door
or
mud and sand and
stones on a dirt road
and showing us there that if we look at
it in a certain way those things are
significant
but we can't say significant of what so
much as significant of themselves
or perhaps the significance then is the
quality of a state of mind
in which we notice
that we're overlooking the significance
of the world
by our constant
quest for it later
[Music]
all this language is of course quite
naturally vague and imprecise
because i think the wrong word is used
and yet not entirely the wrong word
because as i said it comes so naturally
to us
that in those moments the significance
of the world
seems to be the world
seems to be what is going on now
and we don't look any further the scheme
of things seems to justify itself at
every moment of its unfoldment
you