“The meaning of life is to give life meaning.”
What keeps a human being going?\h
The purest answer to this question\h\h
is perhaps to be found in the worst of\h
places. Austrian psychiatrist, philosopher,\h\h
and author Viktor Frankl spent three years in\h
four different concentration camps. He was at\h\h
the mercy of sadistic SS guards and the so-called\h
“Capos:” prisoners with special privileges who\h\h
willingly collaborated with the Nazis and\h
were even more ruthless than their masters.\h
The camp inmates were constantly exposed\h
to famine, sickness, slave labor, and the\h\h
possibility of punishment or execution. There\h
was no freedom. The prisoners moved around like\h\h
a defenseless flock of sheep, kicked and beaten\h
by their shepherds, stripped of all human dignity.\h
What’s left to live for in such a horrible place\h
like a concentration camp? When they’ve taken all\h\h
your liberties and possessions, and when death\h
at short notice is almost inevitable, is there\h\h
any reason not to give up on life? Viktor Frankl\h
concluded that there’s always a reason to live\h\h
even in the worst conditions: there’s always\h
meaning in suffering. And if we can grasp\h\h
this meaning - this star in the sky - we can\h
overcome even the most painful circumstances.\h
According to Viktor Frankl, it’s not pleasure nor\h
success and power that essentially drives people;\h\h
it’s finding something - a purpose,\h
a meaning - to live and even die for.
What’s the purpose of my life? What’s the\h
meaning of all this? These questions echo the\h\h
current societal condition, predominantly\h
in the Western World, in which our lives\h\h
seem to revolve around working a meaningless job\h
to earn money so we can buy stuff as a means to\h\h
dull our sense of meaninglessness. During times of\h
globalization, secularization, and relative peace,\h\h
we’re less likely to find meaning in being\h
part of a tribe, religious community,\h\h
or defending our countries and loved ones against\h
neighboring enemies. Everything has become so\h\h
dull, so pointless, that we engage in rampant\h
consumerism and distraction just not to feel\h\h
a deep-seated sense of purposelessness that\h
plagues our existence. And before we know it,\h\h
nihilism kicks in, and we begin to ask\h
ourselves: What’s the point? Why keep going?\h
We cannot compare the circumstances of\h
the modern-day Westerner with those who\h\h
lived in the concentration camps during\h
the Second World War. But oddly enough,\h\h
we walk around with similar existential\h
questions and have similar reasons for\h\h
giving up on life altogether: the lack of\h
purpose, hopelessness, meaninglessness.\h\h
When we’re trapped in what Viktor Frankl\h
called the ‘existential vacuum,’ what awaits us\h\h
is despair. During his days in the concentration\h
camps, he noticed a division between two kinds of\h\h
people: those who had given up on life and those\h
who had not. The first group was more prone to\h\h
illness and death; the second group was more\h
likely to survive. The difference? A sense of\h\h
meaning or, more specifically, the discovery of\h
purpose in their unbearable living conditions.\h
For example, Frankl himself was a doctor\h
and found purpose in helping the inmates who\h\h
suffered from illnesses. One day, he refused an\h
opportunity to escape the camp so he could stay\h\h
with his patients. He wasn’t motivated by money,\h
status, power, or even freedom: his purpose,\h\h
in his case taking care of his fellow human beings\h
and not abandoning them, was so important to him\h\h
that he was willing to die for it. His life had\h
become a sacrifice of most profound significance.\h
On the other end, Frankl wrote about those\h
who collapsed under the harsh conditions of\h\h
the camp. They always had the same reasoning\h
for giving up, and I quote: “There’s nothing\h\h
anymore to expect from life.” End quote. Devoid\h
of meaning and faith that things could turn out\h\h
more favorable, our bodies and minds begin\h
to wither as we’ve lost our will to live.\h
Frankl wrote about a prisoner who had dreamt about\h
the end of the war and his release. His dream also\h\h
revealed the date on which the liberation would\h
happen: March 13th, 1945. He was full of hope. But\h\h
when March 13th finally passed, nothing happened.\h
As the prisoner’s prophecy was naive and he had no\h\h
purpose within the context of his imprisonment, he\h
was struck with disappointment, suddenly got ill,\h\h
and died of typhus shortly after.
But looking at the horrible and hopeless\h\h
circumstances that some people find themselves\h
in, is it fair to expect that they find meaning?\h\h
Aren’t some situations simply too\h
overpowering, so much so that they\h\h
eliminate one’s responsibility to choose?
When the war was over, Frankl reflected on the\h\h
validity of human liberty during the horrors of\h
the concentration camps. He concluded that we are\h\h
indeed able to preserve a “vestige of spiritual\h
freedom” and of “independence of mind” even in\h\h
such terrible conditions of mental and physical\h
stress. Thus, we always have a choice. I quote:
We who lived in concentration camps can remember\h
the men who walked through the huts comforting\h\h
others, giving away their last piece of bread.\h
They may have been few in number, but they offer\h\h
sufficient proof that everything can be taken\h
from a man but one thing: the last of the human\h\h
freedoms—to choose one’s attitude in any given\h
set of circumstances, to choose one’s own way.
End quote.
The ruthless Capos without morality, the sadistic\h
SS guards with no respect for human life,\h\h
the prisoners who lost their will to live, the\h
guards who tried to help the inmates, those who\h\h
found meaning in the deepest of suffering: they\h
were all responsible for their life choices.\h
Hence, regardless of how terrible life is, we\h
still can and must decide in what direction we go.\h\h
Do we choose to betray our people and commit\h
brutal acts to escape torture and death in the\h\h
concentration camps? Do we choose to succumb\h
to peer pressure and hateful ideologies?\h\h
Do we choose to embrace a nihilistic, destructive\h
mindset due to living in a consumerist society\h\h
that seems spiritually and morally bankrupt? Do we\h
choose to become a plaything of our circumstances?\h\h
According to Frankl, the spiritual freedom we have\h\h
(which cannot be taken away) makes life\h
meaningful and purposeful. I quote:
The way in which a man accepts his\h
fate and all the suffering it entails,\h\h
the way in which he takes up his\h
cross, gives him ample opportunity—even\h\h
under the most difficult circumstances—to\h
add a deeper meaning to his life.
End quote.
Imagine having to get out of bed every morning\h
without a meaningful long-term goal. The only\h\h
reason you get up is that you have to get to\h
work and engage in activities you don’t like,\h\h
just to financially support a meaningless\h
existence and the many pointless pleasures\h\h
to cope with it. You blame your past, parents,\h
circumstances, and even your genetics for not\h\h
having anything going for you. But, in reality,\h
you can still transcend your predicament\h\h
and find purpose despite any external situation.
The question is, of course: how? Before we get\h\h
into that ‘how’ of meaning, it’s helpful to look\h
at the ‘why’ of meaning. Especially in the current\h\h
age, there’s a tendency to focus on money, status,\h
power, and pleasure rather than a meaningful life.\h\h
But, according to Frankl, these pursuits\h
are ways to cope with an existential vacuum.\h\h
They are a consequence of a lack of meaning. In\h
a society highly concerned with pursuing pleasure\h\h
and achieving wealth, it’s often difficult\h
to realize that these pursuits don’t fill\h\h
our existential emptiness and are only\h
cheap substitutes for what truly matters.\h
A more direct approach for dealing with\h
the pain of meaninglessness we see today\h\h
is the pursuit of ‘happiness.’ In some\h
circles, like the good-vibes-only movement,\h\h
happiness has even become a requirement. Frankl\h
describes a characteristic of American culture:\h\h
one is “commanded” and “ordered” to be happy.\h
There’s nothing wrong with ‘happiness,’ of course,\h\h
as happiness is probably the ultimate pleasant\h
state of mind and the eventual by-product\h\h
of following, for example, Stoic and Buddhist\h
teachings. But, so argues Frankl, happiness itself\h\h
cannot be pursued, as it must ensue. I quote: One must have a reason to “be happy.” Once the\h\h
reason is found, however, one becomes happy\h
automatically. As we see, a human being is\h\h
not one in pursuit of happiness but rather\h
in search of a reason to become happy, last\h\h
but not least, through actualizing the potential\h
meaning inherent and dormant in a given situation.
End quote. The same goes for success, according\h
to Frankl. Success must also ‘ensue’ and not be\h\h
‘pursued,’ as it’s the unintended side effect\h
of one’s dedication to a more significant cause.\h\h
It must happen. The more we care about\h
it, the less we can focus on our cause,\h\h
and the less likely success will occur. But\h
if we dedicate ourselves to a purpose and\h\h
don’t care about success, the more likely it\h
will happen as a byproduct in the long run.\h
So, it seems that meaning is at\h
the root of happiness and success,\h\h
and the lack of it at the heart\h
of indulgence in and addiction to\h\h
pleasure, money, fame, and power. Having explained\h
this, let’s take a look into the ‘how’ of meaning.
First of all, according to Frankl, the meaning\h
of life depends on the person, the moment, and\h\h
circumstances. So, there’s no one-size-fits-all\h
type of meaning that suits everyone at any time.\h\h
He compares the futile quest for general\h
meaning, to a question posed to a chess champion:\h\h
“Tell me, Master, what is\h
the best move in the world?”\h\h
There’s none. The best move in chess depends\h
entirely on the situation in the game\h\h
and the characteristics of one’s opponent.
We cannot invent the meaning of our existence,\h\h
but we can detect it. As Frankl stated, meaning\h
is inherent and dormant in a given situation.\h\h
We can discover our purpose only if we interact\h
with the world or determine what the world needs.\h\h
Frankl wrote that we find out the\h
meaning of life in three different ways:
(1) by creating a work or doing a deed\h
(2) by experiencing something\h
or encountering someone\h
(3) by the attitude we take\h
toward unavoidable suffering
The first one lies in achievement and\h
accomplishment. Creative pursuits like\h\h
writing a book, painting, sharing stories\h
about our sufferings and life experiences,\h\h
or solving today’s problems with\h
science and technological inventions,\h\h
can help others. We’ll only find out when\h
we get started and engage with the world,\h\h
so other people’s needs become apparent.\h
The benefit of performing good deeds doesn’t\h\h
need an explanation. But it probably doesn’t\h
have to be grandiose; even sharing a small\h\h
piece of bread with a starving inmate can\h
be a profoundly meaningful experience.\h
The second one lies in the connection we have\h
or find with people and things. The experience\h\h
of life itself, caring about the environment and\h
its people, can be meaningful in itself. Frankl\h\h
describes this as love, as he argues that it\h
requires love to know something or someone truly.\h\h
I quote: “The second way of finding a meaning\h
in life is by experiencing something - such as\h\h
goodness, truth, and beauty - by experiencing\h
nature and culture, or, last but not least,\h\h
by experiencing another human being in his\h
very uniqueness - by loving him.” End quote.\h
The third one lies in finding meaning in\h
suffering. Frankl gives an example of an elderly\h\h
practitioner who consulted him because of his\h
severe depression after losing his wife. Instead\h\h
of telling him what to do, he asked: “What would\h
have happened, Doctor, if you had died first,\h\h
and your wife would have to survive you?” “Oh,”\h
he said, ”for her, this would have been terrible;\h\h
how would she have suffered!” Frankl pointed\h
out that the Doctor’s wife has been spared from\h\h
such suffering, and he spared her by paying the\h
price: that he has survived and now mourns her.\h
We cannot bring back the dead. In many situations,\h
like being imprisoned in a concentration camp,\h\h
there’s isn’t much we can do about the external\h
factors. “When we are no longer able to change a\h\h
situation, we are challenged to change ourselves,”\h
Frankl stated. By changing our attitude, we can\h\h
turn adversity into triumph; we can find meaning,\h
even within the worst sufferings imaginable.\h
The philosophy of Viktor Frankl could\h
perhaps be summarized like this:\h\h
‘finding something to live (and even\h
die for) transforms a meaningless,\h\h
hopeless existence into a life worth\h
living, regardless of any circumstances.’
Hence, he quoted Nietzsche, saying: “He who\hhas a why to live can bear almost any ‘how.’”
\h
Thank you for watching.