when Nietzsche said God is dead he was
referencing the end of a religious
dogmatic age and the beginning of
secular scientism now I would like to
formally apologize for this very cliche
introduction but let's be honest we all
knew I was gonna have to mention either
God Is Dead one must imagine Sisyphus
happy or there's but one truly serious
philosophical problem and that is
suicide I mean is it really a mediocre
philosophy YouTube video about meaning
in life if I don't pick one of these
overused quotes so God is dead instead
of trusting a God to tell us why we are
sick why we sometimes hurt other people
we have medicine to explain how viruses
travel and psychology to explore the
inner workings of our minds and emotions
yay free from the shackles of Dogma but
secularism left us with a major problem
science could tell us why we were sick
and why we sometimes hurt other people
but it couldn't really tell us why like
what's the point of us getting sick
what's the point of hurting other people
maybe to advantage ourselves and push
our own goals forward to endure hardship
and be stronger as a result of it but
all that would matter only if we
mattered and why should we matter we're
just a speck in the middle of an
unimaginably vast Universe we're all
gonna die one day and honestly Humanity
has done lots of awful things to our
environment do we even deserve to live
there have been some responses to these
concerns though so stick around for that
but essentially there was this crisis in
meaning because without a higher being
rubbing our egos telling us you are the
most important beings people fell into
nihilism what if there is no meaning in
life however and you can let me know if
you disagree I think there's been a
shift from meaninglessness to
insignificance to explain this we'll
need to dive deep into this paper by
Massimo Leon although it's about the the
meaning of signs and symbols rather than
human value I think it has so many
interesting ideas that can be translated
into talking about meaning in human
existence and what better way to start
our discussion than riding a bus in
Kyoto Japan but first I am going to drop
you down a flight of stairs yes this
video is sponsored by case defy and I'm
about to do the drop test okay I'm gonna
throw this case down these set of stairs
my phone better not break or else I am
going to be really mad three two one oh
my God
oh my God
is it okay
yeah oh my God okay yay I was able to
pick four cases so I got these two right
here for myself one for Vivian my
roommate how do you like your new
quesify case I love case so far and then
one for my sister they have so many
prints and custom cases I felt like I
was scrolling forever but honestly what
I love most is just how durable these
cases are I am a clumsy person so I need
that Ultra protection which is why I got
the ultra impact case that offers drop
protection up to 9.8 feet and it doesn't
feel bulky at all the new impact and
Ultra impact cases are also made of 65
percent recycled and plant-based
materials so if you're in the mood for a
new phone case you can use the link in
my description box to get 15 off your
order now according to this bus schedule
Oh we gotta run so hopefully you got a
safe and secure phone case by now let's
go
foreign
to foreigners with no Japanese buses in
Kyoto exude with mysterious prospects of
significance each of them a decoding
challenge let's say you're a
non-japanese person like me riding a bus
in Kyoto Japan and you see this sign if
you don't know Japanese you won't
understand what this says yet you do
trust that it means something that these
lines and dots are arranged in a
meaningful way maybe you know this
because it's in an area where ADS
usually reside maybe you're like oh I've
seen similar looking characters on
Ariana Grande's hand whatever it is you
trust that these are words or signs more
generally and signs always signify
something now as a person who is
clueless about the Japanese language
these signs can be meaningless to me in
three ways one I may know who it's
trying to communicate to which are the
passengers but I just can't get the
meaning two is when I know what a sign
means but not who it's meant for the
author Leon gives the example of a
Foreigner's confusion with Japanese bus
drivers who take on and off their hat
and bow every time they enter a new bus
most foreigners recognize that removing
a hat and bowing is a sign of respect
but what confuses them is why these
drivers do it who is supposed to derive
meaning from this gesture the writers
never bow back or react at all for that
matter so it's not really clear who's
supposed to be receiving meaning from
this action in this case tourists do not
ignore what the sign stands for but that
whom the sign stands to the last type of
meaninglessness is what Leon calls
uncanny meaninglessness when both what
it stands for and to who it stands to is
unknown quote riding on Japanese buses
at night one sees often bits of hemp
string nodded to the railings to most if
not all foreigners such bits look
meaningless both in the sense of
undecipherable it is not clear what the
strings stand for and in that of
incomprehensible it is not clear whom
the the string stand too however
something in such bits of hamstring will
still qualify and present them as signs
a recurrent bus passenger indeed will
soon realize that one only bits of
hamstring appear not of other materials
two they are always knotted around the
same railings three they are always
knotted in the same way thus although
foreign passengers do not know either
what these bits of hamstrings stand for
or whom they stand to they will start
realizing that their appearance in the
world is patterned assuming we can't
just Google the answer or ask a local
citizen what the hemp signifies the only
way to associate the potential meaning
of the hamstrings with an actual meaning
is to do research ourselves broaden our
experience by repeatedly riding the same
bus at different times perhaps we ride
the bus a few times in the morning a few
times in the afternoon and a few times
at night through repeated empirical
observation we will come to realize that
the bits of hemp are actually remnants
of leaflets tied to the bus railings in
the early morning which is why by night
only strings of it are left hence the
hemp strings signify that leaflets were
tied here many hours ago although hemp
strings seem to have zero connection to
whether our lives matter I actually
think this example reminds us of how we
recognize patterns in our lives in our
search for meaning Pleasure and Pain
seem to always follow certain acts we
live on an earth that somehow has all
the resources for our basic necessities
and it feels like there should be
meaning to that that it can't be all
complete Randomness but in order to
associate this potential yet unknown
meaning with actual meaning we have to
broaden our experience of the world just
as how to grasp the potential meaning of
the hemp strings we had to broaden our
experience of the Japanese bus the more
perspectives we learn about and take
time to understand and the more
opportunities we seek to learn about
ourselves the closer we can get to the
actual meaning of existence what
underlies all three types of
meaninglessness is that meaninglessness
is subjective the Japanese signs and the
hemp strings are meaningless to
foreigners either because they don't
know the language or they aren't
familiar with the cultural environment
or both but objectively there's still
meaningful signs it's not like the
Japanese characters and the hamstrings
stop signifying meaning just because I
don't get it if I just learned how to
read the Japanese characters or if I
gained more cultural knowledge then the
signs would become subjectively
meaningful to me similarly maybe our
lives can be subjectively meaningless we
feel it's meaningless but it's
objectively meaningful if this is the
case then having a meaningless existence
is not the worst thing in the world I
may be lost right now but I at least
sense that there is some potential
meaning to be uncovered but what if we
are unable to understand how to make
existence meaningful or what if there
are external barriers preventing us from
achieving meaningful existence this is
no longer meaninglessness this is
insignificance
[Music]
while meaningless signs have meaningful
potential that can be dug out
insignificant things signify nothing to
no one in no respect or capacity quote
it is a transparency that nobody looks
through a letter that nobody will ever
read not only because it is written in a
language spoken by none and not only
because it is enclosed in a bottle that
will never be opened but also and above
all because nobody ever will recognize
it as a letter because of this we can
only recognize insignificance in
contrast with significance let's return
to our bus in Kyoto many foreign
visitors will be surprised at how many
locals sleep on the public transport
some might wonder if it's because
Japanese people work very hard wake up
very early or just spend lots of time on
the bus and nap to pass time however a
few others May realize from this
experience of Japanese culture something
about their own culture quote seeing how
easily and how commonly Japanese people
fall asleep in public transport indeed
will lead some foreigners to think I
would never feel comfortable doing that
in the Metro of Paris or on a bus in
Rome or on Madrid's Suburban trains
Japanese people fall asleep in public
transport not only because they must but
also because they can they can for they
trust their public space they trust
their society they trust their fellow
Japanese notice that the Foreigner
doesn't just learn why Japanese people
fall asleep on the bus because that's a
transition from meaninglessness to
meaningfulness in this situation it goes
beyond the meaning of the sign in Japan
The Foreigner actually learns the
meaning of a specific aspect of public
space in their own non-japanese culture
and how their own cultural distrust of
public space connects to larger social
and historical systems passengers
staying awake on public transport will
stop appearing like natural behavior
instead it'll be recognized as a
significant Choice a consequence of a
whole social system that has a long
history of violence and Injustice of
centuries of hunger poverty exploitation
crime all Weighing on the shoulders of
each passenger of the Metro of Paris
Rome London Madrid all whispering to
their ears don't fall asleep it's
dangerous people staying awake on public
transport was something they once never
paid attention to it just seemed natural
but now suddenly it's meaningful it
signals to a public distrust among
citizens because of crime which signals
to the larger social systems of poverty
and oppression it's a passage from
insignificance to significance but it
would have been impossible to have this
transition happen without actually
experiencing another culture to turn
insignificance things we never even
recognize as signs of meaning into
significance we have to travel and
experience different cultures and ways
of life or at least learn about it
unfortunately this presents us with a
problem billions of people in the world
do not have the means to travel to get a
good education and learn to explore
different cultures and ways of life or
if they do learn they can be presented
with biased perspectives or face
discriminatory barriers I love this next
passage in the paper it's so beautifully
written quote to most human beings pain
hunger poverty dirtiness oppression and
violence are insignificant they hurt but
naturally thus for the child who has
starved all his life or the woman who
has been beaten since she was a teenager
or the worker oppressed and exploited
since she or he was an infant pain is
not a semiotic habit it is an
insignificant mute condition of
existence with no alternative Horizon if
hunger poverty oppression were
meaningless people would know that it
has potential meaning to uncover it
would mean that under the right
circumstances we could try to find the
cause of this suffering and eliminate it
but when it's insignificant when it's
something you experience your whole life
just as how the Foreigner experienced
people staying awake on buses their
whole life it becomes naturalized there
is no awareness of meaning it becomes
impossible to think that anything else
but this suffering is available think of
the foreign tourist on the Japanese bus
again the space and the public transport
of certain European cities is unsafe
which is why passengers can't sleep on
the bus yet Europeans do not miss
sleeping in public they do not know it
they do not think about it so long as
they're not exposed to an alternative
they have little means to conceptualize
the underlying meaning of their
situation think about many nine to five
workers who are stuck in a constant
cycle of sleep eat work and social media
it perpetuates an endless banality that
stops us from wondering what does this
mean who is it meaningful to and how is
it meaningful here's why Leon disagrees
with many academics who claim that most
of the world is meaningless he says no
no no most of us are surrounded by
insignificance and most of our lives are
insignificant we Act without being aware
of what those actions mean who's
supposed to get meaning from them and in
what capacity but that's not really our
fault because certain ways that Society
is structured prevents a lot of us from
achieving significant existence only the
privileged few can say that generally
accepted socio-semiotic habits are
automatically rational but just because
many people don't think of staying awake
in public transport as significant
doesn't mean we should automatically
accept it as the correct way to
interpret the world just because owning
slaves was once a semiotic habit a
widely accepted way of signifying social
status doesn't mean it's right not
everything that is significant is right
and so we can't ignore the insignificant
people are starving from significance
they yearn for it when they sink in the
irrationality of strong thoughts
embracing fundamentalism Superstition
and obscuritism they strive for it
through falling for the lure of
consumption they hanker after that
golden existential moment in which they
will finally believe that their efforts
mean something means something to
someone and means something to someone
in some capacity semiotics cannot and
must not teach the meaning of life
however it can and it must warn about
the death of meaning
then what the is stopping us from
just throwing ourselves off a bridge and
giving up and saying yeah the planet is
dying post-modernism is cool and all but
there are legitimate concerns about its
contributions to the death of meaning or
at least confusion about meaning I don't
want to explain what it is because I'll
probably get it wrong so I'll just let
plastic pills sum it up here Berg said
hussaro
and so as you can imagine post-modernism
is like WTF is this modernism
modernism is when science and or
rationality and or religion were seen as
the path to ultimate truth the main
point I want to stress in this video is
that modernism believed in Grand
narratives everything that goes up must
come down the history of all societies
is the history of class struggle or all
men are rude because they secretly want
to stick it in their mom but
post-modernism was like hmm how about
this perspective you're forgetting or
this bias you have how do they interact
is there really one privileged truth
position at all one characterization of
this shift from modernism to
post-modernism is a shift from sincerity
to irony from this is the way things are
to yeah this totally is the way things
are irony becomes the popular
deconstructionist tool to poke holes in
our ways of thinking but irony is an
entirely negative action it keeps poking
holes but leaves nothing new to fill
them back up it critiques but doesn't
rebuild some think we need to bring
sincerity back so that we have an
overarching structure of our thoughts
Behold metamodernism a theory that
doesn't see why we have to choose
between modernism or post-modernism
instead we can constantly move between
the two we can bring back sincerity by
being ironically sincere because frankly
pure sincerity is now considered cringe
I think I touched on this in my video on
gen Z humor already so I won't go too
much into that but essentially some of
the most effective ways of being sincere
now are to be ironic for example BoJack
Horseman explores some really dark
themes but with cartoon talking animals
living among humans in a colorful
cartoon world world the Creator Raphael
Bob waxberg explained the brighter and
the sillier and the cartoonier we went
the more the audience was willing to go
with us to these very melancholy places
that may be on a live action show would
have come off as indulgent or a sakuran
I do not know how to pronounce that
I think this comment under my gen Z
humor video also captures the sentiment
behind why ironic sincerity is now
effective but pure sincerity isn't I
don't think there is room for some
things deserve seriousness because every
single event that gen Z faces is
an existential crisis we don't get the
privilege of sincerity as the comment
suggests being truly sincere can feel at
odds with the absurdity of everything
else we live just to work and spend to
hear about Misery around the world and
for climate change to ruin the Earth
until life is unlivable we worry about
our appearance whether we'll find the
right partner all to suddenly lose
Consciousness one day and decompose away
this sounds pretty depressing but what's
a better cure than listening to some old
men try to cheer us up when I consider
the short duration of my life swallowed
up in an eternity before and after the
little space I feel engulfed in the
infinite immensity of spaces whereof I
know nothing and which know nothing of
me I am terrified the Eternal Silence of
these infinite spaces frightens me one
common reason why people feel that their
existence is insignificant is just how
enormous the universe is and how tiny we
are within it I'm already an
insignificant number in my University so
why would I be any more significant in
the universe when I am literally like
this ah yes the age-old question does
size matter spoiler alert it doesn't if
it were proven that God existed and he
said you humans are special snowflakes
science wouldn't suddenly be like this
just in the universe is actually small
the objective value of our existence
isn't affected by size if we are
intrinsically significant or
insignificant How could an external
Factor like size affect that the author
of this article quoted someone who was
like well Sir Isaac Newton was pretty
darn significant but he was smaller than
a hippo so it's true that sometimes we
use size to represent value for instance
it's hard to think of a religion that
worships a super tiny deity usually
they're infinite in size or beyond the
Realms of space and civilizations tend
to Aspire to build humongous monuments
but this is because big things are
psychologically more impressed
aggressive and they take more effort to
make this size doesn't say anything
about the intrinsic value though as the
author points out few would prefer to
have a huge pile of over a diamond
another common reason for feeling like
our existence is insignificant is
because we're all going to die heck
there's a countdown for how long the
human species has left on Earth we study
to work we work to pay for our home and
food we pay for our home and food so
that we can take care of ourselves and
perhaps a family but to what final end
it's a chain of actions that seems to
never resolve in a final end point me
working explains why I study and me
paying for my food explains why I work
but what's the Big Goal at the end of
all this if there isn't some ultimate
end we're striving for we must be
insignificant but Thomas Nagel says that
we forget there are tons of chains of
actions that end within our lifetime and
are directed towards different goals not
everything has to lead to one ultimate
purpose in order to be justified there
can be smaller endpoints within a larger
picture for example we take an Advil to
stop our headache
and that's it that's all there is to it
we don't bug our friend being like so
why did you take the Advil for
self-actualization for the good of
humankind no we probably don't think
they need to justify that action Beyond
just wanting their head to stop hurting
I think these two reasons as to why
people feel insignificant presents a
view on the Absurd that differs from
Albert Camus conception Camus says that
the absurdity of existence comes from a
gap between our search for meaning and
the world's lack of a response benagel
says the Absurd comes not from a
conflict between our expectations and
the external World rather it comes from
a collision within ourselves he says
that for starters humans can't help but
take things in life seriously we worry
about what our family and friends and
Strangers think of us how attractive our
appearance is what our career is whether
we understand the world whether that
burger was really worth 22 dollars this
is a special ability to reflect on
ourselves as humans we can step back and
evaluate our life from a more detached
perspective as if we're a spectator
making judgments about ourselves yet
simultaneously we also understand that
we can never actually escape this highly
specific position we're in namely
ourself however when we view ourselves
from this outside perspective we realize
how arbitrary our choices and
considerations are sometimes I catch
myself judging how even my eyeliner is
for the fifth time and I realize that
literally doesn't matter even eyeliner
being an attractive feature is so
arbitrary sometimes I stress a lot about
the grade that I get on a paper and that
outside spectator voice of mine tells me
Olivia this paper grade does not matter
in the grand scheme of things in fact
you're going to die one day so most
things that happen to you will lose
value once you stop existing yet
realizing how absurd our considerations
and thoughts are doesn't use usually
cause us to just sign off of life and
that's the absurdity of it all we can
recognize how odd we act and think from
this third person perspective yet still
be invested in taking those actions and
thoughts seriously first person this is
why Nagel says human existence is absurd
but not say the existence of a mouse
quote he lacks the capacities for
self-consciousness and
self-transcendence that would enable him
to see that he is only a mouse if that
did happen his life would become absurd
since self-awareness would not make him
cease to be a mouse and would not enable
him to rise above his mousely strivings
self-conscious self-transcendent Mouse
would be like damn I'm a mouse and I can
never be more than that even if I want
to so if you want to avoid a life
plagued by absurdity Nagel says just
shut your brain off act solely based on
impulse so that you tap into your head
empty animalistic side how have fun
dissociating now this would not be a
meaningful life it's just no longer
absurd but it doesn't seem quite great
but hey you avoided the Absurd this
probably unpopular way of life is
Nagel's way of suggesting that absurdity
ain't even that bad he thinks that Camus
proposition that we must Shake our fists
at the world and live in spite of the
Absurd is a romanticized and slightly
self-pitying picture of absurdity
absurdity to Nagel is one of the most
human things about us it is a product of
our most interesting and advanced
characteristics it's because we are
self-conscious and self-transcendent
that we can ever be aware of the Absurd
and that's unique yeah we're kind of
intelligent no big deal quote if a sense
of the Absurd is a way of perceiving our
true situation then what reason can we
have to resent or Escape it it need not
be a matter for Agony unless we make it
so like a lot of my videos I have no
clue what my conclusion is I just hope
something made you think and maybe you
can dig out a conclusion for me if you
enjoyed this video feel free to leave a
like a comment a subscribe so I forgot
to record the patreon shout out on the
day I was actually filming because I'm
stupid so
um you can just listen to this voiceover
and stare at pictures of me and pretend
that it's a video okay so I want to give
a big shout out to these people who
support my channel Aiden Bozeman Alan
Cisneros Alex M Benjamin Walsh Benson
lie bleach Bonzo c-dub Daniel dangond
deep toe Chatterjee Drew single Diego
embarrassed us fickle foreign man in a
foreign land GW Grammy Reeves Harry
socks Henry Adams Jacob McMillan Jeannie
Lee Jessie JL Arbor 21
John Nguyen Jonathan Von Schroeder Josh
hunt Kaden fur Kian nahad Kyle
anulishian Lee Laura Clark loraz Levy
Lorenzo Villegas Michelle Gia murky
morals name Nova ohb Robert Castro
Sabrina Fiore solidosi Tania Spaceman no
helmet Stephen Bollinger Vincent Julian
Valdez and zesty sauce thank you so much
for watching let's keep talking and I
hope to hear from you soon bye
actually no not a good joke don't put
that in the video no okay