so what is the meaning of life what is
the purpose of life depending on who you
ask they're going to give you a
different answer and depending on which
video you see they're probably going to
give you a different answer too but I
promise you that by the end of this
video you're going to be closer than you
are ever before to learning what the
meaning is in your life hi I'm Jason and
since graduating psychology I've
dedicated 10 plus years of my life
learning about self-help and personal
development and since then created many
videos that have amassed over millions
of total views and hopefully it helped a
portion of those viewers while I don't
claim to be an expert at this none of us
have our lives figured out no matter how
composed we are since I've dedicated a
chunk of my life in this topic I am
pretty confident that I will give you an
accurate picture on what the meaning of
life is for you by the end of this video
you're either going to a start to know
what the meaning in your life is or B
you're still not sure but you'll have
the concrete steps you need to take to
figure that out for yourself let's get
started so let's say you ask a homeless
person he goes spare some change you ask
him hey what do you think the meaning of
life is he might say something like
meaning of life is to survive make it
till the next day you know you ask
someone else they might tell you meaning
in life is to make as much money as
possible and pass on the generational
wealth make as much impact in the world
feel as much discomfort as you can
because you don't want to ever stop
growing you ask someone else they might
say meaning of life is to just relax
just enjoy life you know enjoy the
wonders of the world you ask someone
else oh the meaning of life is to help
as many people as I can before I die
meaning of life is to create a family
raise your kids well and travel a lot so
you don't have any regrets now are any
of them wrong or are they right in what
their meaning of life is and it's just
unique to them some people would say
okay everyone has a different meaning
while that is true to some extent it is
not the whole picture you're going to
see why in a moment let's backtrack the
homeless person is his meaning of life
to survive to the next next day the
answer is yes and no I'm going to
introduce the topic psychology topic it
is called the maso's hierarchy of needs
let me pull up Google right here so what
is Mao's hierarchy of needs maso's
hierarchy of needs basically says that
depending on where you are in your life
you have different needs that need to be
met different
priorities everyone starts off at the
lowest rung of pyramid which is the
physiological needs what this is is
breathing food shelter clothing all that
stuff you need to
survive now this is very likely where
the homeless person in our example is
his priority is to stay alive literally
biologically and for that he needs
oxygen food shelter warmth sleep all
that stuff so is his meaning of life to
survive yes it is but let's say he wins
the lottery the next day yeah or someone
gives him a million dollar assuming he
doesn't blow it all off then you could
safely say that his physiological needs
are met
he can rent a place or even buy a small
broken up home and have enough money to
survive for at least 10 years very
likely his meaning of life is no longer
to survive now he's on level two level
two is Safety and Security Family Social
ability property employment health so
Without Shelter you won't survive you'll
die in a matter of of days but Safety
and Security you you can think of it as
like a more longer term version of
physiological needs if you don't have
health if you don't have employment to
make money if you don't have a property
to live in you'll have to go from bus
shelter to bus shelter you're still in
the danger zone of not having your
physiological needs met so this second
rung is more like a more advanced
version of phys iological needs to me
it's still physiological needs it's just
a longer term version of this which
brings us to the third rung of the
pyramid which is love and belonging and
this is friendship family intimacy sense
of connection and a lot of people in
First World countries like you who's
consuming content for fun because you're
no longer in danger of your
physiological needs not being met so
you're watching videos for For Your
Entertainment you're probably in this
level or higher at this point your
priority or meaning in life maybe to
form more friendships to form deeper
friendships with your friends to form a
family have babies or adopt a baby or
not have babies just have intimacy with
your partner have a sense of connection
with your community your neighborhood
everyone else this would be where you
belong note that you don't have have to
check all of the criteria in order to
get to the next level each person is
different right like some people care
more about friendships some people care
more about family some people care about
intimacy the next level is self-esteem
confidence achievement respect of others
and the need to be a unique individual
and then the highest level would be
self-actualization which comes from
morality creativity spontaneity
acceptance experience purpose meaning
and inner potential someone like oh how
can I create the most impact in this
world that impacts the most people in a
positive way the main key takeaway from
this is that at different points in your
life your meaning your purpose will
change even when you get to the highest
point in maso's hierarchy it could
change as well because let's say you
continue to learn more about yourself
you continue to learn more skills to add
to your Arsenal and you become a
different person and then you might
think back like how can I create the
most impact and creativity and meaning
in my life and you're like oh since I
learned these new skills and have these
New World
Views I think I should do this instead
of what I'm doing now and it would be
more meaningful for me at that point
here's an exercise for you identify
where on the pyramid you are and think
about each of those words on that
pyramid for example if you're in love
and belonging ask yourself how are my
friendships do I think that they can be
improved do I care about my friendships
how's my family do I care about having
uh being close to my family because I
mean it's all individual right some
people They Don't Really Care um do I
care about being intimate with someone
else like a partner do I feel like I
don't have enough sense of connection
with other people if you feel like your
love and belonging in general is lacking
then your meaning of life is probably
something in that category and don't get
me wrong here okay the goal
isn't to get to the highest level before
you die it's not it's to identify
which category you're in right now and
do things that align with your meaning
let's say you are in love and belonging
right and someone tells you you have
five more years to live now if you feel
that your friendships are a bit lacking
and you spent the next one year getting
as many friends and hang out with as
many existing friends as you can and
finally filling that Gap in your heart
and reaching self the self-esteem tier
versus someone else who's in the same
situation but spends 5 years just
focusing on his friendships and never
really reaching the next rung of the
pyramid you can't say that you are
happier than the other person it doesn't
mean when you're higher up you you're
more fulfilled this is just a way of
identifying what your meaning of life is
right now as long as you're doing things
that make that area in your life better
you're happy oh and by the way if you're
the philosophical type or you somehow
went onto a source that tells talks
about the meaning of life in the
philosophical sense for example Socrates
and Aristotle that says the meaning of
life is to seek pleasure and uh nishe
who says it doesn't matter what the
meaning of life is no matter how much
impact you make in the world people are
going to forget you all those like ideas
from philosophers yeah it gets you to
think and I understand all of them but
it doesn't really give you a concrete
idea on what you should do like what
your meaning is in life let's say
Aristotle right the meaning of life is
to seek pleasure and to avoid pain let's
say you're in love and belonging right
when you work on your friendships
because you're lacking in that you are
gaining pleasure and you are avoiding
pain right so it's it's sort of like on
another Continuum if that makes sense it
doesn't really tell you concrete steps
you need to take so I took meaning of
life the actual philosophy course and
you see I got an A in that course I
didn't study I got an A so those
philosophers it's irrelevant I'm better
than them I hope you figured out the
meaning in your life and what did I tell
you all these other sources that you saw
it doesn't really give you a clear idea
on what the meaning of life is but this
video did and if it didn't then I'm
sorry that it didn't but I I'm pretty
sure it did maybe you need to watch it
again anyway see you on the next one