look listen to
this whenever life gets you down Mrs
Brown and things seem hard or tough and
people are stupid obnoxious or
dared and you feel that you've had quite
[Music]
enough just remember that you're
standing on a planet that's evolving and
revolving at 900 mil an
hour that's orbiting at 19 m a second so
it's reckoned a sun that is the source
of all our
power the Sun and you and me and all the
stars that we can see are moving at a
million miles a
day in an outer spiral arm at 40,000 M
an hour of the Galaxy we call the Milky
Way
[Music]
our galaxy itself contains a 100 billion
stars it's 100,000 light year side to
side it bonges in the middle 16,000
light years thick but out by us it's
just 3,000 light years wide we're 30,000
light years from Galactic central point
we go round every 200 million
years and our galaxy is only one of
millions of billions in this amazing and
expanding universe
[Music]
the universe itself keeps on expanding
and expanding in all of the directions
it can
whiz as fast as it can go at the speed
of light you know 12 million miles a
minute and that's the fastest speed
there is so remember when you're feeling
very small and insecure how amazingly
and likely is your
bir and pray that there's intelligent
life somewhere up in Sp com this bu all
down here on Earth