there are two types
world those who wake up in the morning
like this and those who wake up in the
morning feeling like this we know which
one we are but the question is what's
the difference
Carl Jung a very famous psychiatrist
said at the end of his career that over
1/3 of the patients he's seen actually
suffered from no clinical neurosis but
rather from a want of meaning or purpose
in their lives Viktor Frankl a Jewish
psychiatrist and survivor of the
Auschwitz death camp said as soon as one
of his fellow inmates lost their purpose
they'd be dead within a day or two
purpose makes us whole purpose gives us
life purposes what gets us out of bed in
the morning and without it we're
drifters drifting through life with no
Direction no destination and no end in
sight and life is dull mundane
monotonous and meaningless Sheen called
this the anxiety of life now some of us
will say just get through school get a
good job follow your dreams get married
raise a family and make a lot of money
that's your purpose and these are all
good things that are part of purpose but
can't be purpose purpose because first
of all what if these things don't work
out for me
then what and second what if all these
things work out for me
then what others will just try to avoid
the whole thing and convince ourselves
that there's no such thing as purpose
and we'll try to replace the want of
purpose with things like pleasures
experiences and excessiveness but you
know as well as I do this gets old real
fast and the older we get the louder
those questions become
so what is it what's my purpose and how
do I break out of this anxiety of life
well Sheen offers two solutions the
first is this go out and help someone
today help my neighbor who's my neighbor
anyone near me who's suffering the poor
the lonely the sick the stressed-out the
sad the broken the beaten down the
depressed that tired the hungry the
addicted the lost the hurting basically
we're all the neighbor because when
we're living in this anxiety of life
were living totally for ourselves
trapped and all the junk inside our own
heads and the quickest way out and the
second thing is this be open like our
phones receive all kinds of signals from
God knows where we have built-in
antennas able to receive infinite
signals from outside we call these but
they've long been disabled in atrophy
and we can't get a signal anyway because
we're surrounded by so much
enable it and be open to receive some
sort of encounter from God and it
doesn't matter who you are what you've
done or how far away you think you may
be these signals are coming down on all
of us even as we speak like rain just be
open
now some of us may be thinking all right
that first one makes sense but why do I
need that second one the whole god thing
makes me a little uncomfortable because
if the first one is this the second is
this if the first is this the second is
this if the first one is this the second
is this because the first is go out and
love my neighbor and the second is
opening up a permanent connection with
pure love itself that is purpose and
this purpose is like the mother of all
purposes and takes all those other
purposes into her arms and lifts them
all up
purpose is not something we rationalize
or intellectualize or figure out by just
thinking about it really really hard
it's something we do and when we do we
don't find purpose purpose finds us