um excuse me mate why are you what do you mean\h
what do you mean I mean what is the meaning of\h\h
your question the meaning of existence is the\h
meaning of my question no I'm asking you what the\h\h
meaning of your first question was the meaning of\h
you oh so you do know the meaning of Me no that's\h\h
what I'm asking you what is what is the meaning of\h
existence oh yeah that question doesn't make any\h\h
sense how come well what exactly are you asking\h
me are you asking me what my name means no I'm\h\h
asking you what you mean what existence is self\h
means I mean that I am the meaning of existence\h\h
is that it is yes but why is existence why are you\h
I could ask you the same uh well I exist because\h\h
my parents reproduced that doesn't explain why\h
your parents exist I could just keep asking why to\h\h
all of your responses all the way back to the Big\h
Bang at which point you'll essentially be saying\h\h
because existence began to which I will ask why\h
did existence begin and we will have arrived back\h\h
at square one so I'll ask again why why are you\h
um I exist to bring my future children into this\h\h
world ah but here we have the same issue again\h
just in the opposite direction I can keep asking\h\h
why until we get to the inevitable heat death of\h
the universe and you'll run out of answers that's\h\h
exactly the issue though that's why I'm asking\h
there's no meaning to any of it looking backwards\h\h
it's accidents all the way back and there's\h
no meaning to any of it looking forwards it\h\h
all comes to an end so that settles it then that's\h
your answer that it's all for nothing both ends of\h\h
the thread of time are loose and all you have to\h
do is pull and the whole damn thing unravels back\h\h
to the present moment and there's no real point\h
in getting out of bed in the morning no point in\h\h
having kids my parents gave birth to me for no\h
reason at all and it's all for nothing you're so\h\h
smart that you're Dum what you want to know what\h
it's all for but your linear mind won't accept a\h\h
circular answer and yet you ask a circular\h
question what's it all for it can't all be\h\h
for something else because then you wouldn't have\h
been talking about it all would you your question\h\h
cannot be answered without referring to something\h
within your expression at all for even if I did\h\h
give you an answer that referred to something\h
outside of it all like heaven for instance as soon\h\h
as its existence was an established fact it would\h
be contained within the expression it all and\h\h
since you're so set on rejecting circular answers\h
you would reject that answer too and ask okay but\h\h
what's heaven for the fact that you are yet to\h
discover the meaning of life is not evidence\h\h
that there isn't any just evidence that you're\h
terrible at asking the question you condemn me for\h\h
answering the question with existence means that\h
it is and yet when I ask you the same question you\h\h
go looking for answers in the past that no longer\h
exists then you go looking for answers in the\h\h
future which doesn't exist yet and then conclude\h
that it's all for nothing as if you had looked\h\h
everywhere you forgot to look in the present you\h
idiot the only place that actually exists and\h\h
since your question pertained to the nature of\h
of existence I'm almost inclined to believe you\h\h
don't even want existence to mean anything it's\h
as if you're intentionally avoiding the issue\h\h
by running off into the past or into the future\h
and acting surprised when you return empty-handed\h\h
carrying none of the meaning of existence that you\h
were supposedly looking for why on Earth would I\h\h
intentionally avoid finding answers because maybe\h
there's nothing you find scarier than the thought\h\h
that all of existence is here simply for the\h
sake of itself and perhaps if nothing means\h\h
anything then everything is permitted and why\h
would I find that first bit scary because when\h\h
you don't like the state of things for example\h
the state of having lost a loved one or burning\h\h
your toast when you're already late to work the\h
idea that things are in that state simply for the\h\h
sake of existence puts you at odds with existence\h
itself the friend of an enemy is an enemy the soup\h\h
of Life arrives unblended and you've made a habit\h
of throwing the ball from the table when you get a\h\h
of something that you don't like H and what about\h
all that the meaning is in the present [\h__\h] you\h\h
were just saying how can that be true if the\h
present is always changing remember I told you\h\h
the meaning of existence is that it is and what's\h
the one thing that never changes about the present\h\h
moment the fact that it is that it exists and how\h
am I supposed to find meaning in that I ask you\h\h
what it's all for and whether you say it's all for\h
every reason it's all for no reason at all or it's\h\h
all for its own sake hardly makes a difference\h
to me I still feel lost what I want is for it\h\h
all to be for a single unifying reason I want a\h
grand narrative I want a triumphant ending I want\h\h
fireworks and explosions and eternal Redemption\h
not for all of existence to be an accident that\h\h
simply Fizzles out and dies a whimpering death yes\h
you want the suffering of today to be justified\h\h
by the joy of tomorrow but your science told you\h
that on a long enough time frame everything dies\h\h
and so you can't justify the suffering of today\h
like you say you want a triumphant ending and\h\h
eternal Redemption you want to be aware of some\h
Grand narrative today into which your suffering\h\h
reasonably fits so that you don't feel like\h
it's for nothing you want Solid Ground not an\h\h
ocean of doubt that's why you look to the past\h
and to the Future for meaning because you're in\h\h
search of a grand narrative on which to ground\h
yourself one that's always been active and will\h\h
continue to be active forever exactly and since\h
the beginning of Life was accidental and the end\h\h
of all life is certain there can't possibly be a\h
grand narrative to which my existence is relevant\h\h
I have no purpose Beyond myself but you're wrong\h
there is a grand narrative you just can't see the\h\h
big picture and I mean that quite literally also\h
you say that in millions of years nobody will\h\h
remember you and therefore everything you do today\h
will be irrelevant a million years from now but if\h\h
what you do today will be irrelevant a million\h
years from now then why should should a million\h\h
years from now be relevant to what you do today\h
all due respect sir you're a relatively primitive\h\h
talking monkey you see things linearly in terms\h
of beginnings and endings and you don't quite\h\h
understand the significance of happenings you say\h
that you're born there's stuff in the middle and\h\h
then you die but this is a child's perspective in\h
reality you just happen and you really do happen\h\h
I'm getting the sense that I won't ever understand\h
your answers can you present the truth in a way\h\h
that humans would understand so that we can stop\h
feeling that it's all for nothing and please focus\h\h
on this Grand narrative you speak of sure consider\h
this The Elements of Life happiness sadness pain\h\h
loss food sleep love burnt toast laughter they're\h
each like individual threads and they each have a\h\h
slightly different color and as you know some\h
are much darker than others in a single human\h\h
life all these billions of threads miraculously\h
converge they flirt and dance with each other they\h\h
intertwine and form the most beautiful patterns\h
that you call Stories the ultimate story of your\h\h
life is the string woven from these billions of\h
threads and at the end of your life that string\h\h
unravels itself and the threads part ways it\h
was life that brought them together and up to\h\h
the surface in your current state you can only\h
see your string in its entirety and you may have\h\h
put lots of effort effort into making sure that\h
it's a certain color in the final analysis so\h\h
the fact that it unravels causes you distress you\h
think linearly in terms of beginnings and endings\h\h
so you want your creation to last you want your\h
string to be endless but just as your threads\h\h
interweave horizontally to form the unique color\h
of the string of your life that uniquely colored\h\h
string then interweaves vertically with the\h
strings of others the people you meet and when\h\h
it does the color of both is forever changed you\h
are all Weavers and you create your string because\h\h
you want it to last but here's what you miss\h
it does last space and time are not separate\h\h
you figure this out yourselves a moment is not\h
endless but it is eternal you cannot measure the\h\h
length of a moment it's immeasurable because it's\h
Eternal you weave the string of your life because\h\h
you want it to be endless and sure both ends\h
of it are unraveled but the string itself has\h\h
interwoven with thousands of other strings so\h
while the string has Loose Ends its Center does\h\h
not come undone because of this zoom out and an\h
entire tapestry emerges painting a portrait with\h\h
patterns more beautiful and intricate than your\h
single human mind could ever imagine or perceive\h\h
before the threads of your string converged they\h
were hidden underneath the tapestry and after\h\h
they unravel they go back under but none of that\h
matters does it what matters is the tapestry and\h\h
this sense of insignificance of yours how dece\h
deceitful is that sense granted if you were to\h\h
decide to unravel your thread right now you would\h
forever darken the tapestry but that's the thing\h\h
you'll not have died you will have lived your\h
string will still remain within the magnum opus\h\h
of the universe itself you will not have removed\h
your string from the universe's self-portrait only\h\h
cut it short and short as it may be it will\h
remain but don't for a second think you could\h\h
remove your string entirely for without your\h
string the entire tapestry would come undone it\h\h
would sabotage that to which existence itself\h
is moving and you wonder why you don't get to\h\h
choose whether or not to be born you didn't\h
stumble into existence by chance you weren't\h\h
the recipient of an open invite you were drafted\h
because you are necessary to the entire Enterprise\h\h
of existence itself this tapestry is a portrait\h
of who Gods the universe existence whatever you\h\h
want to call it it's creating a self-portrait\h
one that a single mind could never comprehend\h\h
and even if it could it definitely wouldn't\h
remind a human of any self-portrait they've\h\h
seen before but since the tapestry is the Weaver\h
it's giving birth to itself but I'll never get\h\h
to see it so how is this relevant to me ah so the\h
Ultimate Painting to which your every experience\h\h
serves as a brush stroke isn't relevant to\h
you but the heat death of the universe is\h\h
I did not know your confusion reached such\h
depths to answer your question it's relevant\h\h
to you because it is you you are one of its many\h
limbs imagine your finger was to question its\h\h
relevance to your hand or your hand to question\h
its relevance to you in medical terms you call\h\h
that cancer and you say that you'll never see the\h
whole tapestry but how can you be so sure I mean\h\h
sorry what was your name again Adam well it may\h
be true that Adam might never see the tapestry but\h\h
how do you know that Adam is all that you are\h
the belief that you are Adam is only a partial\h\h
Truth at the same time you experience Adam so\h
you are the experiencer too and the experiencer\h\h
experiences every experience the whole tapestry\h
and while it may be hard for Adam to see that\h\h
after all Adam is but one string in a tapestry\h
of trillions it's nevertheless true it's all\h\h
Inseparable there is is not two you are everyone\h
but you only experience yourself one at a time\h\h
well I certainly don't consider myself to be\h
outside of the universe and that does seem\h\h
to align with what we know about physics but\h
still as Adam I want to see this tapestry that\h\h
supposedly justifies all the dark threads in my\h
string and yet I'm fated to never be able to if\h\h
the universe is really creating a self-portrait\h
why is it necessary to go about it in such a way\h\h
that leaves its participants in the dark well\h
firstly it's not true that you do not see the\h\h
tapestry true you just see one string at a time\h
for now at least but the amalgamation of all that\h\h
you've seen is the tapestry secondly faith is one\h
of the brightest threads in existence one of the\h\h
universe's proudest achievements and if it were\h
not for unfaith or the Absurd as philosophers call\h\h
it a thread which is opposite in color then\h
Faith would never stand out in the tapestry\h\h
I see but why is Faith so necessary to avoid\h
exactly the kind of predicament you found yourself\h\h
in you lack faith in the intrinsic value of both\h
your string and existence itself and so you go\h\h
looking for it you analyze your string looking\h
backwards you analyze it looking forwards and you\h\h
return empty-handed that is your punishment for\h
growing so arrogant as to assume that the meaning\h\h
of the tapestry could or should be comprehended\h
by a single string such as yourself you weave a\h\h
linear horizontal string all you can do is look\h
backwards and forwards and since you break current\h\h
eggs to make future omelets you assume the same\h
of the tapestry it all must exist to bring about\h\h
something other than itself it's why you couldn't\h
bear my answer I mean that I am no you don't want\h\h
the meaning of life you want the meaning of life\h
that you can understand sorry all good things come\h\h
at a cost it's one of the many stylistic choices\h
of the artist and meaning is priced in faith a\h\h
currency that went out of circulation amongst\h
your kind long ago but faith in what the Weaver\h\h
of the tapestry and the intrinsic goodness of the\h
whole Enterprise you mean I need to believe that\h\h
it's all being Guided by some intelligent entity\h
the Weaver as you call it I need to believe in\h\h
God basically you don't have to call it God I know\h
God's been having some PR issues amongst you a lot\h\h
recently you could call it the laws of physics if\h
that's more high fashion both phrases aim at the\h\h
same Target and both miss the mark so take your\h
pick but the laws of physics aren't intelligent\h\h
are you intelligent I'd like to think so yes are\h
you outside of the laws of physics no then the\h\h
laws of physics are intelligent well good point I\h
guess I am kind of the laws of physics in action\h\h
but what about the second element the faith in\h
the value of the tapestry the goodness of the\h\h
whole Enterprise when you look at a beautiful\h
sunset you value it but not because it helps\h\h
you achieve some goal in the future you value it\h
immediately for itself right yes well when you\h\h
doubt the intrinsic value of existence you look\h
for it not as you would a sunset or a beautiful\h\h
painting but as a tool what's it all for you ask\h
what higher purpose does it serve like a monkey\h\h
being handed to Mona Lisa and trying to use it\h
to crack open a nut life is not a stepping stone\h\h
you use to get somewhere else or an arcade ticket\h
you use to redeem for something better so long as\h\h
you see it that way you will forever torture\h
yourself needlessly with the question what is\h\h
the meaning of life it was never science that\h
destroyed your faith and meaning it was your\h\h
own intellectual Pride for if you hadn't seen your\h
scientific discoveries through such arrogant eyes\h\h
they would certainly have emboldened your faith\h
that the Weaver was indeed creating a tapestry\h\h
that was as you say worth it and as a result\h
you would consider it a privilege to be involved\h\h
you seem kind of annoyed at us well yeah you\h
are quite rude to me your lives are tricky I\h\h
get it you rarely know what you're up to and so\h
you obsessively sting yourself with the question\h\h
what am I doing which evolves into why am I\h
here and as your beloved nature said stings\h\h
of conscience teach one to sting eventually\h
you put me in your sights asked me why I am\h\h
and began to doubt my fundamental goodness and\h
as you know it's not nice to be the recipient\h\h
of such doubts I thought it was the tapestry's\h
fundamental goodness that we were guilty of\h\h
doubting yes I am the tapestry I see and we are a\h
part of you that has renounced your relevance to\h\h
us precisely just as cells in your body sometimes\h
renounce your relevance to them so what should we\h\h
do know that you are me just as the branch\h
is the tree and the wave is the ocean thus\h\h
understand that you experience all that has been\h
is being being or will ever be experienced and act\h\h
accordingly that's kind of ludicrous though I'm\h
not the universe I'm Adam then that is just how\h\h
you will remain for a time at least until Adam\h
unravels and then you'll have to face the music