let me ask you the last question
without any serving it up without any
explanation
what is the meaning of life
i think it is either the wrong question
or that question is answered
by
paying sufficient attention to any
present moment
such that there's no there's no
basis upon which to to pose that
question it's not answered in the usual
way it's not it's not a matter of having
more information
it's having more engagement
with reality as it is in the present
moment or consciousness as it is in the
present moment
you don't ask that question when you're
most captivated by the most important
thing you ever pay attention to yeah it
is
that's a that's a question only gets
asked
when you're abstracted away from that
experience that peak experience
and you're left wondering why are
so many of my other experiences mediocre
right like why am i repeating the same
pleasures every day why did
why is my netflix queue just like
when's this going to run out like i've
seen so many shows like this am i really
going to watch another one like
you're all of that that's a moment where
you're
not actually having the beatific vision
right you're not you're you're not sunk
into the present moment
and you're not truly in love like you're
in a relationship
with somebody who you know you know
conceptually you love
right this is the person you're living
your life with but you don't actually
feel good together
right like if you you so like it's it's
in
in those moments of where attention
hasn't found a good enough reason to
truly sink
into the present so as to obviate any
any concern like that right and
that's what that's why meditation is
this kind of super power because
until you learn to meditate you think
you're like the outside world where the
circumstances of your life
always have to get arranged so that
the present moment can become good
enough to
to demand your attention in a in a
a way that makes that seem fulfilling
that makes you happy
and so if you're if it's jujitsu you
think okay i got to get back on the mat
it's been it's been months since i've
trained you know it's been
over a year since i've trained it's
coveted when am i going to be able to
to train again that's the only place i
feel
great right or you know i've got a ton
of work to do
i'm not going to be able to feel good
until i get all this work done right so
i've got some
deadline that's coming you always think
that your life has to change the world
has to change
so that you can finally have a good
enough excuse to
to truly to to just be here and hear is
enough
you know that where the present moment
becomes totally captivating
meditation is the only meditation is
another name
for the discovery that you can actually
just train yourself to do that
on demand so that like doesn't mean just
looking at a cup
can be good enough in precisely that way
and any sense that it might not be
is recognized to be a thought that
is mysteriously unravels the moment you
notice it and then and you fall in
and that the moment expands and becomes
more diaphanous
and then there's no then there's no
evidence
that this isn't the best moment of your
life right like this it doesn't and
again it doesn't have to be
it doesn't have to be pulling all the
reins and levers of pleasure it's not
like
oh my this tastes like chocolate you
know this is the most chocolaty moment
of my life no it's just
the the sense data don't have to change
but
the sense that there is some kind of
basis for doubt about the rightness of
being
in the world in this moment that can
evaporate
when you pay attention and
that is the meaning of the kind of the
meta answer to that question
the meaning of life for me is to
live in that mode more and more and to
whenever i notice i'm not in that mode
to
recognize it and return and and to not
be
to to to cease
more and more to take the reasons why
reasons why not uh at face value because
we all have reasons why we can't be
fulfilled in this moment it's like i've
got all these outstanding things that
i'm worried about right it's like it's
you know there's there's that thing
that's happening later today that i you
know
i'm anxious about whatever it is we're
constantly deferring
our sense of this is this
is it you know this is not a dress
rehearsal this is the show
we keep deferring it and we we just have
these moments on the calendar where we
think okay this is this is where it's
all gonna land it's that vacation i
planned with my five best friends you
know we do this once every three years
and now we're going
and here we are on the beach together
unless you have a mind that can really
pay attention
really cut through the chat or really
sink into the present moment
you can't even enjoy those moments the
way they should be enjoyed the way you
dreamed you would enjoy them
when they arrive so it's i mean so it's
a meditation in this sense it's the
great equalizer it's like
it's you don't have to you don't have to
live with the illusion
anymore that you need a good enough
reason
and things are going to get better when
you do have those good reasons it's like
there's just a mirage-like quality to
every future attainment
and every future breakthrough and every
future peak experience
that eventually you get the lesson that
you never quite arrive right like you
you won't you don't you don't
arrive until you cease to step over the
present moment in search of
the next thing i mean we're constantly
we're we're stepping over the thing that
we think we're
seeking in the act of seeking it and so
it is kind of a paradox
i mean there is a there's this paradox
that
which i mean it sounds trite but it's
like you you can't
actually become happy you can only
be happy and and and it's that it's the
illusion that because
it's the illusion that your future being
happy
it can be predicated on this act of
becoming
in any domain you know and becoming
includes this sort of
you know further under further
scientific understanding on the
questions that interest you
or you know um getting in better shape
or whatever the thing is
whatever the whatever the contingency of
your dissatisfaction seems to be in
any present moment real attention
solves the koan you know in in a way
that
becomes a very different place from
which to then make any
further change it's not that you just
have to dissolve into a puddle of goo
i mean you can still get in shape and
you can still do all the things that you
know the superficial things that
are obviously good to do but the sense
that
your well-being is over there is um
really does diminish and eventually
just becomes a it becomes a kind of
non-sequitur
so well there's a sense in which
in this conversation i've actually
experienced many of those things
the sense that i've arrived so i
mentioned to you offline
it's very true that i start i've been a
fan of yours for many years
and the reason i started this podcast
speaking of ai systems is to manipulate
you sam harris into doing this
conversation
so like on the calendar literally you
know i've always had the sense people
ask me
when are you going to talk to sam harris
and i always answered
eventually right because i always felt
again tying our free will thing that
somehow that's going to happen
and it's one of those manifestation
things or something i don't know if it's
maybe i am a robot i'm just not
cognizant of it and i manipulated you
into having this conversation so it was
a
i mean i don't know what the purpose of
my life past this point is
so if i've arrived so in that sense i
mean all that to say
i'm only partially joking on that uh is
it really uh it's a huge honor that you
would waste this time with me yeah
well really means a lot listen it's
mutual i'm a big fan of yours and as you
know i reached out to you for this so
so this is uh um it's great i love what
you're doing
you're doing something uh more and more
indispensable
in this world on on your podcast and
you're doing it differently than
than rogan's doing it or that i'm doing
it i mean
you have you definitely found your own
lane and it's it's wonderful
you