okay so what's what's really the purpose
of life if you can give an Insight on
that thank
you isn't it fantastic that if there's
no purpose you have nothing to fulfill
you can just
live no but you want a
purpose and not a simple purpose you
want a god-given
purpose it's very
dangerous people who think they have a
god-given purpose are doing the cruelest
things on the
planet yes or
no they are doing the most horrible
things and they've always been doing the
most horrible
things because when you have a god-given
purpose life here becomes less
important then your
purpose now life is
important life is important when I say
life I'm not talking about your family
your work what you do what you do not do
your party I'm not talking about that as
life this is life isn't
it life is within you or around
you the the ambulance of Life your
mistaking the ambulance of Life For Life
your home your family your work space
your party this is all Ambiance of life
this is not life isn't it yes or no
you're mistaking the ambulance for the
real thing
no life is
important because it's the only thing
you know you don't know anything else do
you know something
else rest is all imagined stuff isn't it
the only thing is that this is beating
and alive and that's all there
is so is this important it is a
Paramount
importance not you as a person that's
not important but you as a piece of life
it's very
important because that is the basis of
everything when I say that is the basis
of everything the universe exists for
you only because you are isn't it yes or
no the world exists for you only because
you are otherwise it won't exist in your
experience so in every way this is
important so what is the purpose for
this see if you had aose purpose and if
you fulfilled it after that what would
you
do bored isn't
it it is just that life is so intricate
and so phenomenally
intricate that if you spend a 10,000
years looking at it carefully you still
will not know it
entirely if you spend a million years
looking at it with absolute Focus still
you will not know it in its
entirety that's how it
is there is is there a meaning to it the
greatest thing about life is that there
is no meaning to
it this is the greatest aspect of life
that it has no meaning to it and there
is no need for it to have a
meaning it is the pettiness of one's
mind that it is seek a meaning because
psychologically you will feel
kind of unconnected with life if you
don't have a purpose and a
meaning people are constantly trying to
create these false
purposes now they were quite fine and
happy suddenly they got married now the
purpose
is other person then they have children
now they become miserable with each
other now the whole purpose that I go
through all this misery is because of
the
children like this it goes on
these are things that you are causing
and holding these as purposes of
life and is there a god-given
purpose what if God does not know you
exist no I'm just asking by
chance I'm saying in this
huge
Cosmos for which God is supposed to be
the Creator and the manager of this 100
billion galaxies in that this tiny
little planet and you suppose he doesn't
know that you
exist what to
do possible or no I'm sorry I'm saying
such sacrilegious things but is it
possible or no what if he doesn't know
that you
exist what if he doesn't have a plan for
you
suppose he doesn't have a plan for you
an individual plan for
you don't look for such
things the thing is the creation is made
in such a way that creation and Creator
cannot be
separated here you are a piece of
creation at the same time the source of
creation is throbbing within
you if you pay little attention to this
process of life you would not need any
purpose it'll keep you engaged for a
million years if you want there is so
much happening so much means so much
unbelievable things are happening right
here if you pay enough
attention a million years of existence
it'll keep you busy or
more right now the need for purpose has
come because you are trapped in your
psychological structure not in your life
process
psychologically your your psychological
structure functions from The Limited
data that it is gathered within that it
rolls and right now your thought and
emotion has become far more important
than your life isn't it
so isn't it so so because of this you
seeking a purpose as an escape from the
trap that you have set for
yourself it is a trap set by you you can
easily come out of it if the Trap was
set for you by somebody else
difficult to come out because they'll
set the trap in such a way that you
cannot come out isn't
it I'm I'm talking about life not
marriage that's what
I that's
what so this is a trap set by you this
is easy to come out but that is a whole
thing why it is so difficult is now
you're identified with the Trap you like
it you like it because it gives you a
certain sense
of uh Safety and Security and protection
and individual identity if you build a
cocoon around
yourself it gives you safety but it also
imprisons
you walls of self-preservation or also
walls of self-imprisonment
when it protects you you like it when it
restricts you you do not like
it that is why we have doors we like the
walls cuz it's protecting us but we have
doors so that we can open it and get out
when we want to it doesn't matter how
nice it is we still want to go out isn't
it so that is how it is with every trap
that you set it doesn't matter how nice
it is you still want to go
out so the psychological walk that you
have built which gives you a some sense
of identity which gives you some sense
of being a person an individual person
and which gives you
security beginning to experience it like
a trap somewhere you want to break
it so one
way of not breaking it is to find a
purpose those who find a purpose in
their life they become so
conceited they will live within their
own trap forever ever thinking that
they're doing the most fantastic thing
first thing you need is
balance if you have
balance then you can climb if you don't
have balance it's better you stay on the
ground isn't
it it's not safe for somebody who is not
balanced to climb high it's best you
stay close to the ground you should not
climb so first thing is to establish a
balance then you losing your
psychological structure
then it's a wonderful thing if you lose
in your psychological structure without
balance which a lot of people are doing
today see why does somebody want to
drink alcohol or take a drug because it
loosens your psychological structure and
makes you feel liberated for a
moment but without the necessary
balance you have not worked for the
balance but you got
freedom freedom without balance is
destruction Anarchy isn't
it so first thing is to work for balance
an enormous sense of balance where even
if you dismantle your psychological
structure you can simply live
here dismantling your psychological
structure is an important process
because that is your
trap that is your security that is your
stability at the same time that's your
trap because the walls are set you feel
secure but that's also your trap if you
dismantle your
trap you also dismantle your security
isn't it you also dismantle your sense
of purpose you also dismantle everything
that matters to
you so that will need balance without
balance if you dismantle you will go
crazy but don't look for a purpose
because if you look for a purpose
you're seeking Madness if you find one
you are sure
mad
yes if you think you found a purpose in
life you still you for sure gone
crazy because only the insane people
have
purpose or people who have
purpose are insane in many ways these
are things that you create in your mind
and believe it's true true isn't it
right now fighting for my country is my
purpose right now if it's necessary I
will fight knowing fully well it's an
unnecessary bloody
fight yes then you will fight only to
the extent it's necessary if you think
this is your purpose you would want to
destroy the whole world for what
nonsense you believe in isn't
it something is needed we'll do
it with with absolute involvement
there's no other purpose the purpose of
life is to live and to live
totally to live totally does not mean
party every
night to live totally means before you
fall dead every aspect of life has been
exploded nothing has been left
unexploded yes before you fall dead even
if you do not explore the cosmos at
least this piece of life you must know
it in its entirety that much you must do
to yourself isn't it that's living
totally that you experience the whole of
this all dimensions of what this is you
did not leave anything
untouched you just do that that will
take a long time that's enough good
enough purpose for you