♪♪♪
♪ ON THE WAY ♪
♪ TRYING TO GET WHERE
I'D LIKE TO SAY ♪
♪ I'M ALWAYS FEELING
STEERED AWAY ♪
♪ BY SOMEONE TRYING TO TELL ME ♪
♪ WHAT TO SAY AND DO ♪
♪ I DON'T WANT IT ♪
♪ I GOTTA GO FIND MY OWN WAY ♪
♪ I GOTTA GO MAKE
MY OWN MISTAKES ♪
♪ SORRY MAN FOR FEELING ♪
♪ FEELING THE WAY I DO ♪
♪ ON YEAH, OH YEAH ♪
♪ OPEN WIDE AND THEY'LL
SHOVE IN ♪
♪ THEIR MEANING OF LIFE ♪
♪ OH YEAH, OH YEAH ♪
♪ BUT NOT FOR ME I'LL DO IT
ON MY OWN ♪
♪ OH YEAH, OH YEAH ♪
♪ OPEN WIDE AND SWALLOW THEIR
MEANING OF LIFE ♪
♪ I CAN'T MAKE IT WORK
YOUR WAY ♪
♪ THANKS BUT NO THANKS ♪
♪ WOH OH OH OH ♪
♪ BY THE WAY ♪
♪ I KNOW YOUR PATH HAS
BEEN TRIED AND SO ♪
♪ IT MAY SEEM LIKE
THE WAY TO GO ♪
♪ ME, I'D RATHER BE FOUND ♪
♪ TRYING SOMETHING NEW ♪
♪ AND THE BOTTOM LINE ♪
♪ IN ALL OF THIS SEEMS TO SAY ♪
♪ THERE'S NO RIGHT AND
WRONG WAY ♪
♪ SORRY IF I DON'T FEEL LIKE ♪
♪ LIVING THE WAY YOU DO ♪
♪ OH YEAH, OH YEAH ♪
♪ OPEN WIDE AND THEY'LL
SHOVE IN ♪
♪ THEIR MEANING OF LIFE ♪
♪ OH YEAH, OH YEAH ♪
♪ BUT NOT FOR ME I'LL DO IT
ON MY OWN ♪
♪ OH YEAH, OH YEAH ♪
♪ OPEN WIDE AND SWALLOW THEIR
MEANING OF LIFE ♪
♪ I CAN'T MAKE IT WORK
YOUR WAY ♪
♪ THANKS BUT NO THANKS ♪
♪♪♪
♪ OH YEAH, OH YEAH ♪
♪ OPEN WIDE AND THEY'LL
SHOVE IN ♪
♪ THEIR MEANING OF LIFE ♪
♪ OH YEAH, OH YEAH ♪
♪ BUT NOT FOR ME I'LL DO IT
ON MY OWN ♪
♪ OH YEAH, OH YEAH ♪
♪ OPEN WIDE AND SWALLOW THEIR
MEANING OF LIFE ♪
♪ I CAN'T MAKE IT WORK
YOUR WAY ♪
♪ THANKS BUT NO THANKS ♪
♪♪♪
♪ WOH OH OH OH ♪