quotes since I have come to know the body\h
better zarathustra said to one of his disciples\h\h
the spirit is to me only quasi-spirit and\h
all that is permanent is also a mere parable\h\h
I have heard you say that once before\h
the disciple replied and at that time\h\h
you added but the poets lie too much why\h
did you say that the poets lie too much\h\h
why said zarathustra you ask why I'm not one\h
of those whom one may ask about their why\h\h
is my experience but of yesterday it was long ago\h
that I experienced the reasons for my opinions\h\h
would I not have to be a barrel of memory if\h
I wanted to carry my reasons around with me\h\h
it is already too much for me to remember\h
my own opinions and many a bird flies away\h\h
and now and then I also find a stray in my dovecot\h
that is strange to me and trembles when I place\h\h
my hand on it but what was it that zarathustra\h
once said to you that the poets lie too much\h\h
but zarathustra II is a poet do you now believe\h
that he spoke truth here why do you believe that\h\h
the disciple answered I believe in zarathustra\h
but zarathustra shook his head and smiled\h\h
Faith does not make me blessed he said\h
especially not faith in me end quote\h\h
that's from zarathistra part 2 chapter 12 on poets\h
and uh while it's ostensibly about poets and their\h\h
trustworthiness I think that the scene contains\h
so much uh so many gems for helping us to sum up\h\h
the central thrust of Nietzsche's affirmative\h
philosophy his spiritual philosophy as I have\h\h
called it which is anti-spirit and we'll talk\h
briefly about what that means the idea of Geist\h\h
and German which contains both the concept of Mind\h
and Spirit or means something approximate to both\h\h
um that had been invoked in both a philosophical\h
and religious context and in spirit we have\h\h
something which is a conception of the immaterial\h
spirit is not subject to the laws of physics it\h\h
doesn't arise and pass away like matter it's\h
not something destructible from the time of the\h\h
ancient Greeks philosophers and Priests alike\h
have made reference to an indestructible being\h\h
either a primordial Unity from which we steal our\h
existence as in the concept of the indefinite the\h\h
aperon written of by anaximander or else The\h
fedantist View that all the world is of the\h\h
same substance as the Brahman the godhead\h
and that this entire reality occurs behind\h\h
a Veil of Maya which means illusion and\h
that therefore there exists in fact only\h\h
the one and our separateness from it is\h
simply our own ignorance our own delusion\h\h
and we can recognize the same thought about\h
being throughout the history of both eastern\h\h
and western philosophy since nothing seems to last\h
in physical reality then why not take the Buddhist\h\h
View at the end of the day that all phenomenon we\h
perceive in physical reality are basically empty\h\h
and that to the extent that anything exists\h
it only exists at best as a representation\h\h
it's only within our perception that definite\h
boundaries or a sense of duration can exist\h\h
now in the West in contrast to that Buddhist view\h
we have not been content to rest at that position\h\h
that things are all empty and impermanent\h
we've we've instead sought for that permanent\h\h
indestructible being and since the Advent of\h
Christendom or even of monotheism generally\h\h
this has always been associated\h
with God this uh permanence of being\h\h
and within ourselves we project\h
the same concept of being\h\h
our identity is secured in Christian thought\h
because we have an immortal soul which is created\h\h
in the image of that same permanent indestructible\h
being and remember God is a spirit in Christianity\h\h
um our souls are also spiritual and not\h
material and so that we've created this\h\h
whole spiritual realm in which there is\h
permanence in which there can be permanence\h\h
the physical form the body does not have the same\h
degree of reality as Spirit within the this type\h\h
of worldview because the body is impermanent we've\h
made permanence in this view the standard of being\h\h
and therefore we now say Spirit alone is and thus\h
at the end of get as Faust and the final lines of\h\h
the play the chorus mysticus sings As Faust\h
descends to Heaven quote what is destructible\h\h
is but a parable what fails\h
ineluctably the undeclarable end quote\h\h
which means all that has happened in the past\h
no longer exists only what's happening in the\h\h
present is real all that exists within this world\h
of arising and passing away therefore is at best\h\h
only a parable because what's real is eternal\h
what has permanence is what has true substance\h\h
and so we might say you can kind of look at the\h
whole story of all these destructible things\h\h
this Narrative of uh you know whatever\h
it might be the classic hero cycle or\h\h
the story of your own life right but in the\h
end that story is the only thing that's real\h\h
um it's a very deep set of lines that has\h
contextual meaning specific to the fast play\h\h
insofar as the chorus is announcing that all the\h
things that were said and done in the course of\h\h
Faust's story form a parable um but in in that in\h
some sense that's those stories very clever way of\h\h
um of saying what can't be said that all\h
is fleeting and yet the story of all is\h\h
permanent that the archetype the ideal uh\h
exists timelessly and so the story of Our\h\h
Lives you know it isn't written until the end\h
when it becomes history that's when it attains\h\h
meaning just as Faust's story can't really be\h
understood until it is enclosed by the conclusion\h\h
and um you know the undertone of all this it's\h
clear as in the context of the story because it\h\h
takes place against the backdrop of Faust being\h
reborn into his new Immortal perfect body into\h\h
eternity Faust becomes being in the story\h
and uh so as in the chorus indicates this\h\h
is a mystery it can't fully be um encapsulated\h
into words that's why we have the story right\h\h
the meaning is Illustrated in the parable where\h
it was translated into action rather than words\h\h
um and so it's a very uh it's a very deep and\h
beautiful uh idea but the Fatal flaw as we've\h\h
discussed it uh literally the Fatal flaw as\h
we've discussed it throughout the podcast\h\h
is that by the time that definite ending\h
happens in our own lives our lives are over\h\h
it's a another way of restating Nietzsche's\h
criticism of the world of spirit that insofar\h\h
as it is a means of justifying life and making\h
a parable it promises Redemption only in death\h\h
and so zarathistra directly in these lines\h
rebukes the chorus mysticus at the beginning\h\h
at the beginning of the passage and he says on\h
the contrary that what is permanent is but a\h\h
parable that rather these assertions of something\h
which transcend the conditions of impermanence and\h\h
temporality that we see in the physical world only\h
exist in our minds uh mere abstractions spirit is\h\h
only quasi-spirit what he means by that remark\h
true enough Geist means mind and that Spirit\h\h
surely exists within this world of the mind\h
but as such an abstraction right right uh it's\h\h
uh nominally real but it's not physically real\h
and so that's the real essence of our being is\h\h
physical physiological and that it therefore our\h
being is subject to temporality and impermanence\h\h
um and then rather than believing in these\h
Parables of God or Brahman in order to imagine\h\h
that we can have something by which to Anchor\h
ourselves and our existence instead zarthustra\h\h
says he's come to understand the body better we\h
have to come to understand ourselves as bodies\h\h
that life is necessarily embodied it's physical\h
and um you know because it's necessarily embodied\h\h
it's individual and subjective it comes with this\h
certain perspective right um and by imagining on\h\h
the other side of that coin that the root of life\h
and its foundation is found in something spiritual\h\h
you know uh meaning abstract permanent\h
absolute that's what we mean by spiritual\h\h
uh by doing that we've harmed life we've Frozen it\h
um I know of a close friend who he's got sort of a\h\h
oh he describes him as a weird family member who\h
uh he says his hobby is to freeze and photograph\h\h
wasps I was like what apparently you can sort\h
of like uh freeze them I don't know what they\h\h
use but it like slows them down and then you can\h
basically take them and photograph them uh but\h\h
you know it's like that's uh that's what I think\h
that's a great mental image for what Nietzsche\h\h
might uh criticize all of our metaphysics of\h
spirit and what it does to our conception of life\h\h
um so zarthestra further down in the passage\h
uh he says quote all gods are poets Parables\h\h
poets prevarications verily it always lifts us\h
higher specifically to the realm of the clouds\h\h
upon these we place our Motley bastards\h
and call them gods and over men end quote\h\h
so he's it's funny because so he's we're talking\h
about the realm of the clouds of the obvious\h\h
philosophical referent you'd think would\h
be like Cloud Cuckoo Land um they're very\h\h
obvious implications about your head being in the\h
clouds and what zarthister employs to talk about\h\h
um or rather to invert the way we think about the\h
realm of spirit in relation to the physical as a\h\h
spirit giving rise to the physical or at least\h
the way people tended to think about it in his\h\h
own time of thinking instead implicitly in that\h
quote I just read of the physical being the thing\h\h
that gives rise to the spiritual that the abstract\h
the conceptual life has a physiological origin\h\h
and he employs not only the idea of God he also\h
uses his own idea of the over man or he's you know\h\h
we call them gods and over men it's not obviously\h
Nietzsche's own idea of the over man but um he's\h\h
established the concept of the over man throughout\h
the text as his you know new uh ideal for mankind\h\h
that is beyond Christianity that is uh in line\h
with the sort of dionysian view of humanity and\h\h
what life is and but here he recognizes\h
um all these ideals are stories and fibs\h\h
and in all ideals what actually happens is that\h
those of us here and now who are depending on\h\h
what terms you want to use and how religious\h
your own interpretations of Human Action are uh\h\h
might be you know we're all variously Unholy and\h
Wayward and lustful and murderous and vindictive\h\h
you know all these things you could say about\h
the human race and then we're the ones who come\h\h
up with the image of what Holiness looks\h
like you know us modern day people who are\h\h
um imperfect and selfish and with are cobbled\h
together Cosmopolitan moralities and religious\h\h
beliefs and then we presume to say what the over\h
man would look like when we do that we inevitably\h\h
construct such an image out of our own values\h
and our own virtues or lack thereof and so how\h\h
will those of us who are sick and have always\h
been sick produce an image of what is healthy\h\h
now going back to earlier in the dialogue um\h
the response from the disciple when he hears\h\h
zarathustra say that permanence is but a parable\h
so you remember zarathus for saying this before\h\h
but before he remembers zarathustra included\h
but the poets lie too much as a sort of caveat\h\h
but zarathustra's answer to this\h
is to clarify that he's also a poet\h\h
and that he can't therefore be trusted\h
in saying that the poets lie too much\h\h
um and the reason why he would say poets lie too\h
much um you know so it's funny because that's\h\h
sort of a it's a self-referential self-destroying\h
statement right but throughout Nietzsche's work\h\h
um what he has to say about\h
artists are the artistic process
um he says there's an essential incompleteness\h
to Art and an essential will to deception that\h\h
exists in art um and many authors throughout\h
the years have levied charges like this\h\h
but uh Nietzsche on the other hand\h
includes himself in the lot of the\h\h
accused and and he struggles over it uh\h
sometimes especially in his poetry and so\h\h
when zarath Esther says The Poets lie too much\h
he also must include himself amongst the poets\h\h
and so what is the caveat to zarathustra's\h
refutation of impermanence here and his rebuttal\h\h
to Gerta why does zarathustra take care to remind\h
us that he lies too much when he when he gives\h\h
us this rebuttal and perhaps it is because this\h
view of life that zarath Esther presents is also\h\h
a poetic gloss on reality that would be a surface\h
level reading that life is becoming is another lie\h\h
in other places which we'll look at today\h
describes life in terms of Will To Power\h\h
which is apparently a consistent enduring\h
principle wouldn't that be a kind of permanence\h\h
or perhaps we could consider the eternalization\h
of Our Lives within the con text of the\h\h
Eternal recurrence which would mean if we\h
take it seriously that everything physical\h\h
is actually permanent right it's permanent in its\h
sort of fluid ever Dynamic state right but the\h\h
parable of your life the story of your life always\h
plays out the same way in like the superposition\h\h
is the same we might say and so the whole idea\h
of permanence as but a parable would itself be\h\h
incorrect it would be zerothistra\h
would be the lying poet in saying that\h\h
uh from that perspective if we take the eternal\h
return very literally and so there are endless\h\h
ways to interpret this and rather than give us\h
a canonical interpretation sarathastra instead\h\h
seemingly goes off in a non-sequitur from the\h
main point which ends up being the topic of\h\h
the chapter I mean when asked to explain himself\h
he explains why he can't really explain himself\h\h
and so we started out talking about life as\h
an embodied existence not the permanence of\h\h
spirit but now the passage is about\h
sarath ester's own untrustworthiness\h\h
and I think it's digressions like these and\h
thus books are a Thruster that can throw off\h\h
some readers but is it a non-sequitur I mean is\h
there some connecting tissue for this passage\h\h
on closer examinations earthhsters explain\h
explanation that he gives of why he can't\h\h
be trusted is because his thoughts the abstract\h
Productions of his intellect are merely memories\h\h
the experiences of yesterday to zarathustra who he\h
is is the body and its impulses which is it's not\h\h
dependent on memory in any sense most of the self\h
is subconscious it strings the conscious intellect\h\h
along our thoughts are like a superficial surface\h
and skin a conscious gloss on reality the reality\h\h
that's first and foremost physical and driven by\h
physical need physical desire physical instincts\h\h
and this even applies to our philosophizing as\h
Nietzsche argues and Beyond Good and Evil that the\h\h
philosopher is merely giving a voice to whoever\h
whatever um has he put it moral or immoral aims\h\h
are deep within him uh he says the philosopher\h
is giving a confession he's telling us who he\h\h
is revealing his deepest instincts of thought and\h
so zarathustra Compares his own thoughts to birds\h\h
his conscious mind is just like a little Roost\h
for a bunch of thoughtbirds to come and make\h\h
their nests and some of which are not even his\h
you know he says that sometimes he finds foreign\h\h
thoughts in his mind that have flown in from\h
somewhere else and they don't really belong to him\h\h
they tremble as he places his hand on them\h
so carrying around his reasons for things he\h\h
said and did is something zarathustra dismisses\h
because our conscious reasons for doing things\h\h
are not themselves the truth he doesn't\h
want to become a barrel full of reasons\h\h
because reasons bring us no closer to that\h
that raw physical truth and thus we might\h\h
recall Nietzsche's statement in Daybreak that the\h
Consciousness is a commentary on an unknown text\h\h
and what Nietzsche has done here in this new\h
conception of the body is that he's given us\h\h
a holy mystery throughout his work he attempts\h
to Humble the conscious mind before the body\h\h
humble reason before the importance of passion\h
and thus the ultimate spiritualization of the body\h\h
is to make the physical body akin to\h
the way that we have conceived of spirit\h\h
in such a way as to give power to Spirit and\h
our conception of it and so in Nietzsche's\h\h
philosophy the body is the Lord issuing\h
Commandments to the conscious mind\h\h
you know that's your the conscious mind uh\h
in its relationship to the body uh you know\h\h
the people who have difficulties in Life or\h
fail failings of the will we might compare\h\h
them to a uh a defiant Center who's you know\h
ego Consciousness is compelling him to defy\h\h
the uh dictates the natural order of the issue\h
from his Lord which is should be his body right\h\h
and the body is a mystery to us just as no\h
one knows the mind of God none of us may know\h\h
the true nature of our own inner life where the\h
deepest drives and impulses within us come from\h\h
Nietzsche insists on unconscious origins of all\h
our motives and even our philosophical ideas\h\h
and so our attempt to have control over the world\h
through our own self-conscious rationality has to\h\h
yield to a love of fate and in this formulation\h
uh I think it's important I did not say faith\h\h
uh even though I could see one reaching for such a\h
term but the reason I didn't is because Nietzsche\h\h
has this perhaps unusual way of presenting\h
his ideas which may be relatively rare within\h\h
philosophy he tells us that we shouldn't really\h
believe him and that sarathustra is not a reliable\h\h
source and that therefore it's not appropriate for\h
you to follow Nietzsche who is only human All Too\h\h
Human and that having faith in his religion is not\h
a Sacrament but a kind of sin assuming that I mean\h\h
we even permit the idea of sin but I mean have\h
you ever heard of religion like that you know a\h\h
lot of religions will claim the specific point\h
of their uniqueness right hear it all the time\h\h
um you know I've heard uh Christians say the\h
uniqueness of their religion is that their God\h\h
lives in lived and died in human form right became\h
he he lived the through the suffering and the uh\h\h
the mortality that we all live with right um so\h
what's the uniqueness in Nietzsche's religion\h\h
I I would say faith which is so fundamental to\h
every religious tradition that the word faith\h\h
is itself a synonym for a religious tradition in\h
the sense we talk about people of many different\h\h
faiths right but Nietzsche uh or zarathustra\h
rejects faith and it would even be hard to\h\h
call that a sin the way I did earlier um I mean\h
every religion tends to have a concept of sin to\h\h
whatever they might call it but sarthustra's\h
reaction to someone's misplaced faith in him\h\h
is not chastisement or even forgiveness\h
but uh just he laughs and shakes his head\h\h
you know the way a parent might laugh at\h
their child you know it's like a making a\h\h
simple innocent mistake or something like that\h
it's not it's a good-hearted laugh it's not\h\h
um at least that's the read I get off the passage\h
so just to put what we're talking about in context\h\h
here we're coming to the end of the season of\h
the podcast and I want to to give a summary of\h\h
Nietzsche's revaluation and particularly his\h
affirmative philosophy as we have explored it\h\h
which means describing this new form of\h
spirituality or anti-spirituality and\h\h
saying what it means in Practical terms\h
to begin following the value of life\h\h
and furthermore to hopefully give a sort\h
of synthesis to all the major ideas we've\h\h
covered this season the over man the\h
eternal return Will To Power Amor Fati\h\h
what does life look like to us when all these\h
philosophical pieces are fitted into place and\h\h
when life is understood from this New Foundation\h
of um you know the body as the root of it all\h\h
and nevertheless in that affirmative philosophy\h
we have to do this with an awareness of this\h\h
particular tendency in Nietzsche that to tell us\h
not to follow him and to find our own way and to\h\h
remember that he could be lying to us and that in\h
fact The Poets always lie so we must include this\h\h
element within the summary of what the meaning\h
of life is for Nietzsche because this affects\h\h
how we might integrate Nietzsche into our life\h
because the answer cannot be well now we have this\h\h
blueprint these do-it-yourself instructions step\h
one step two step three for how to become what\h\h
one is right none of these Concepts or figures\h
such as the Overman or the spirit of gravity\h\h
have any more actual reality to them than God or\h
the devil did right and ultimately there can never\h\h
be an orthodox presentation of the nietzschean\h
message now I believe that one can in spite of\h\h
that create a coherent and accurate presentation\h
of nietzschean affirmative philosophy and that\h\h
we can say definitively what it is Nietzsche\h
asserted what he criticized what he admired\h\h
what he rejected as evidenced by what he writes\h
in his own books the postmodern position is\h\h
really not my own like I think there are more\h
accurate interpretations of nature than others\h\h
um even though all interpretations are physic are\h
are uh fictional excuse me uh quite the opposite\h\h
of physical you know I and I think I can hold both\h
of those propositions and I would say to Nietzsche\h\h
himself who sometimes wrote Things implying that\h
the interpretation of a work is all there is\h\h
that nature is indeed correct that the poets\h
like Nietzsche lie too much and I don't believe\h\h
him on that particular point um but when we\h
go beyond the philosophical or theoretical\h\h
and into the Practical into the specifics um\h
zarthostress preachments not to follow him\h\h
and to discover your own path become very very\h
relevant and there's some sense in which any\h\h
useful life advice will always be contextual\h
and relative any code of virtue or behavior\h\h
when extended to be completely General will simply\h
become another form of universal morality of an\h\h
ought imposed on existence and\h
therefore a judgment passed on existence\h\h
and so Niche and life philosophy always\h
must avoid this and so these limitations\h\h
they don't make the challenge of describing\h
Nietzsche's affirmative philosophy impossible I\h\h
mean quite the contrary they set the boundaries\h
of what such a thing might look like and so we\h\h
have to we have to refine the question and ask is\h
there any way to do this without falling victim\h\h
to dogmatism or to violating the\h
spirit of Nietzsche's philosophy\h\h
and it's a pressing question to me because\h
it's demanded uh that we derive some\h\h
practical application in order to say that\h
Nietzsche's philosophy has mattered at all\h\h
and in order to integrate his philosophy into\h
our lives um and so what is his answer to the\h\h
life problem if we can't make that answer real\h
in our own lives then is it really an answer\h\h
and so it's a bit of a different question\h
than we normally ask on the podcast\h\h
and I I should say um what we normally do on this\h
podcast is philology really I mean there's some\h\h
philosophizing and involved but mostly what\h
I'm doing here is less akin to what Nietzsche\h\h
did when he was writing his books up in sales\h
Maria and more like what Nietzsche was doing\h\h
when he was studying the Greek philosophers of\h
Basel although probably nowhere near the skill\h\h
level of either Nietzsche but uh you know it's\h
philology we're studying the history of ideas
um and so but I I don't want to just try and\h
catalog Nietzsche's ideas and the ideas of his\h\h
influences I want to sincerely engage with figures\h
from the past I want to learn what it is that they\h\h
thought and felt and I want to know the context\h
of their lives as a background for their thought\h\h
and I don't want to do this in order to judge them\h
or affix a label either moral or a qualitative\h\h
judgment I mean sometimes that still happens\h
because we're human we judge all the time\h\h
uh and so you know that's man is the measure of\h
all things right that's what it means to be a\h\h
mensch in German the etymological root suggests\h
man is a measurer so naturally we make judgments\h\h
and oftentimes we feel it's our prerogative to\h
judge philosophers and other figures from history\h\h
as to whether their ideas are worthy of\h
us or sometimes what we want to do is take\h\h
our own ideas from today and simply project\h
them onto past figures in order to to claim\h\h
someone you know Jesus was a socialist or\h
Jesus was a Libertarian that sort of thing
um but here I think we can learn a great\h
deal from Nietzsche's own example of how\h\h
he treated the Greek philosophers\h
when he himself was a philologist\h\h
and a sincere practice of philologians involves\h
a sort of oath not to project yourself under past\h\h
figures and not to judge past figures relative\h
to your time or interpret them anachronistically\h\h
um or you know judge them in accord with events\h
that haven't happened yet or standards they didn't\h\h
hold or facts they didn't know about to really get\h
to know someone and get into their head it's not\h\h
when you try to figure out what you yourself think\h
of of a figure from history like be it Nietzsche\h\h
or heraclitus or Emerson schopenhauer or geta\h
or Plato but instead when we try to figure out\h\h
what would all of those people think of me and I\h
think that's how you really enter into a dialogue\h\h
with artists and thinkers from history um because\h
we're always going to put our own judgment on them\h\h
so what you really need is two-way communication\h
right so figure out what they would be telling you\h\h
about your life and then you can pass your\h
judgments and have your assessment anyway\h\h
I feel we we've done that with\h
Nietzsche throughout this podcast\h\h
uh but as we've already considered Nietzsche\h
is so aware of this danger of dogmatism\h\h
being attached to his own ideas that he can't\h
present it as specific Universal moral advice\h\h
as I've said we're going to try and infer\h
some general principles from his statements\h\h
but in the final analysis Nietzsche presents\h
his ideas in such a way that there is no\h\h
Universal Doctrine or way of life and it's not\h
just because Nietzsche doesn't want disciples\h\h
but because he would argue there is no Universal\h
way of life for human beings and that all of us\h\h
in the end must find our own way whether you\h
want to believe that that's something you have\h\h
to do or not it's simply the reality and what's\h
good for one person it's not necessarily good\h\h
for another and we all have our lies and fables\h
within our conscious gloss of thought which may be\h\h
appropriate for us but not for others so everyone\h
has to become what he or she is on their own terms\h\h
um and people are always looking to abdicate\h
our own authority and our own responsibility\h\h
for our will and defer to some Authority which\h
is beyond ourselves and Nietzsche quite simply\h\h
will not let us do that with him and his ideas and\h
that's the last thing he wants rather he wants to\h\h
put you in a position such that your will and the\h
nature of your own character and instincts can\h\h
be made clearer to yourself such that you're in a\h
better position to realize your greatest potential\h\h
um and there doesn't need to be free will in\h
this process it's simply a fact that with more\h\h
awareness of yourself you gain more knowledge\h
uh you gain relevant knowledge over your own\h\h
life and never has the acquisition of\h
new knowledge limited one's options\h\h
it may reveal to you that an option you\h
thought you had didn't really exist but\h\h
that doesn't really take anything away since it\h
was never really there to begin with so that it's\h\h
an increase in one's power right uh we might\h
say since limiting out the options that would\h\h
bring harm to yourself is not a decrease in your\h
power and we fully think that proposition through\h\h
and so an honest awareness of ourselves and our\h
own nature because of the mystery of our own\h\h
subconscious and instinctual life it can very\h
well be a lifelong quest for self-knowledge\h\h
this isn't something you know you might think okay\h
I'm gonna make the nature of myself and my drives\h\h
clearer to myself how do I do that what's the\h
three-step process right it's a lifelong process\h\h
and since we've all started it we have\h
to carry it through to the end now\h\h
Nietzsche writes in the preface to genealogy of\h
morality quote we are strangers to ourselves we\h\h
men of knowledge end quote the the knowledge\h
of ourselves the thing we find farthest away\h\h
especially those of us who like to think\h
in these explicit abstract conceptual ways\h\h
this world of thought this world of the mind\h
of Geist it's the farthest thing away from the\h\h
physical reality of the body though and the\h
Deep impulses that really drive us because\h\h
the intellect the imagination has become so\h
free as to become increasingly untethered in\h\h
its Productions from any physical limitations\h
and the more objective and Abstract we\h\h
become in our thought the less we're able to\h
intuitively understand ourselves as subjects
um and so that is the great quandary\h
set before us men of knowledge\h\h
um in any case it's not possible as I've said\h
to give a canonical view of the nietzschean\h\h
life right or a canonical set of nietzschean\h
Virtues or a definitive vision of what the\h\h
Overman would be like um I think it is\h
on the other hand quite possible to say\h\h
in general terms what Nietzsche thinks\h
life is and what he thinks the good life is\h\h
we could address ourselves to that way of\h
looking at the question of the meaning of life\h\h
um and so actually I mean we really could break\h
down this most frequently Asked of existential\h\h
questions into its constituent parts and answer\h
the question as Nietzsche or zerathustra might\h\h
answer it answer each question and keeping in mind\h
that this is more of an art than a science here\h\h
as we kind of go over how I think each of these\h
questions might be answered but here are four\h\h
aspects actually that I think will cover most of\h
what people are asking about when they inquire\h\h
about the so-called meaning of life so first one\h
may ask what is life second what is the good life\h\h
Third how to facilitate the good life\h
and finally how to confront death
so let us address ourselves to the first question\h\h
I'll give the nietzschian foundation\h
for answering it what is life\h\h
we approach that question with resistance to\h
metaphysics that is to say a repudiation of the\h\h
traditional belief that we must begin with a set\h
of first principles or employ our reason in order\h\h
to transcend the limitations of our senses instead\h
we start from the immediate sense perception\h\h
that doesn't mean we're dogmatic about what it is\h
these senses indicate or what the quote unquote\h\h
true nature of the world really is it's simply\h
that those questions must be tabled because\h\h
this true world so long as it's conceived of\h
is this mind independent reality a reality\h\h
which exists in some objective form outside of\h
and independent of any human perception of it\h\h
has been recognized to be a useless concept it's a\h
misleading bypass instead we simply take the world\h\h
as revealed to us by the senses as the real world\h
good enough secondly when we apply our reason we\h\h
see that the world behaves according to patterns\h
and laws which can be apprehended by the senses\h\h
and this doesn't mean that these patterns\h
are Universal or mind independent\h\h
because we've done away with those Notions already\h
as a sort of first principle see I just said it so\h\h
I'm like laying out first principles and the first\h
principle is to do away with first principles\h\h
all right moving on the second principle you\h
see how it's like uh it almost impossible to\h\h
um I talk about this in a coherent way but I\h
think what he's saying still makes sense actually\h\h
um so really the what we're getting at\h
here is that it seems the behavior of\h\h
matter can be explained via the properties\h
of matter that we don't we don't find an\h\h
indication of some power beyond the world\h
without which the world can't be explained\h\h
rather we perceive that the power which is\h
driving the world is within the world itself\h\h
in past ages figures such as Spinoza believe\h
that there was an imminent quality of the\h\h
Divine in all things which animated the\h
world and this notion was carried on to\h\h
like some of the most important scientific figures\h
such as Newton who believed that motion had to\h\h
be explained by an appeal to God and we find\h
when we look back in western civilization all\h\h
the way to the time of the pre-platonics we have\h
empedocles who posits a first cause which started\h\h
all the processes we perceive in reality with\h
the atheistic schopenhauer Nietzsche found the\h\h
ingredient he needed to overcome this equality\h
within the world within life within the things\h\h
of existence which is not itself created by\h
something outside the world schopenhauer's\h\h
system was atheistic and yet he believed that\h
the world and the most fundamental level was Will\h\h
and when we look inward in schopenhauer's writing\h
he says you look inward you get in touch with the\h\h
deepest reality of our being we perceive that what\h
we are as will then that's the inner intelligible\h\h
character of Life the will for schopenhauer is in\h
all things all phenomena are a manifestation of it\h\h
it's completely undivided and only appears to be\h
that way to to be divided in all these different\h\h
forms due to our representations of it but it's\h
uh what does he say it's not increased when new\h\h
things are born or decreased when something dies\h
it exists equally in all things and it always has\h\h
been and always will be because it's not subject\h
to time time is simply another representation\h\h
uh when individuals arise the will doesn't\h
increase they pass away it doesn't diminish\h\h
that's show up an hour's View and so Nietzsche\h
was materialistic insofar as he believes that\h\h
the world's Behavior the motion of it you know\h
the world the patterns the laws we discussed\h\h
are not explained by anything outside of the\h
world and yet like schopenhauer Nietzsche\h\h
believes there is an inner content to phenomena\h
an intelligible character to them he also calls\h\h
it will but while schopenhauer believed that\h
the fundamental form of the will was ontological\h\h
meaning it's a true character of being which\h
exists independently of the world of phenomena\h\h
um and furthermore schopenhauer believes it\h
manifests as self-preservation because it's a will\h\h
towards continued existence and towards duration\h
Nietzsche believes instead in a boscovitchian\h\h
world which is a world of Multiplicity and the\h
basis of all those Wills is the will to power\h\h
what this means is not a will to duration\h
but a will to expand to conquer to dominate\h\h
to make itself felt to make its impact felt\h
to overcome and to create Beyond oneself\h\h
we might say to attempt to give rise to\h
something better for whatever that might mean\h\h
in perhaps not the same ontological sense of\h
schopenhauer Nietzsche nevertheless thinks that\h\h
these various drives are all really the same thing\h
that they we might say a better way to put it as\h\h
they can all be explained by the same principle of\h
Will To Power and he does at certain times even go\h\h
as far to ask us to sort of dare to undertake the\h
thought experiment of considering that in terms of\h\h
our subjective experience the only intelligible\h
character of the world is Will To Power\h\h
now if this is the world's inner character it's\h
intelligible in her character Will To Power\h\h
some of us might immediately recognize that\h
there's at least an apparent contradiction\h\h
how can Nietzsche reject metaphysics but\h
posit a true character of the world which\h\h
is beyond the senses in some sense right\h
when we look around do we see Will To Power\h\h
with the senses and if not wouldn't it be an\h
abstract thing but Nietzsche believes there\h\h
is an observable basis to Will To Power\h
which we can perceive with our senses\h\h
and like heraclitus he would say that wilted\h
power is not an ontological reality behind\h\h
things but something which is revealed in the\h
behavior of all the things that we perceive\h\h
um and so you know for example on the level\h
of physics Will To Power as boscovich's\h\h
unified field Theory a single equation which\h
describes how every Force every pattern every\h\h
law in reality as we perceive them manifests\h
according to the distance at which it acts\h\h
all things are Force points that push and strive\h
for and against one another and he explains both\h\h
attraction and repulsion with the same equation\h
on the level of biology Will To Power is not\h\h
so much a drive for preservation as we've said\h
but the drives for nourishment and procreation\h\h
Nietzsche argues that nature is a great squanderer\h
that it can be wasteful arbitrary and so on the\h\h
individual of the species is never preserved I\h
mean quite the opposite really none of them are\h\h
preserved but the species survives if nourishment\h
and reproduction continue and so that is the uh\h\h
that is the pattern that we perceive right that's\h
the the parable right and so this is a drive to\h\h
exist yes but part of Nietzsche's point is that\h
it's not really descriptive to say that something\h\h
merely strives to exist because um that that\h
doesn't explain adamant matter at all of life why\h\h
we engage in action or motion uh it's a criticism\h
he levels at schopenhauer that we already exist\h\h
now and if the will driving life is simply a will\h
for us to continue existing then we're driven to\h\h
do a thing we're already doing we're striving to\h
attain something we already have um it doesn't\h\h
tell us anything about the actual character of\h
existence creates this strange Circle that things\h\h
exist for the sake of continuing to exist so why\h
then would life generate itself generate new forms\h\h
why would forms arise that move themselves\h
about and consume things and make offspring\h\h
Nietzsche's counter description is that life\h
is engaged in this process of striving to\h\h
find nourishment which means consume and extract\h
energy from other forms within the ecosystem and\h\h
to reproduce the process by which the organism\h
creates Beyond itself he says that organisms\h\h
don't seek to preserve themselves but to discharge\h
their strength that life is a positive phenomenon\h\h
not positive in the sense of good necessarily but\h
essentially generating self-generating doing so by\h\h
giving rise to things in a long active process\h
of differentiation as all things strive to be\h\h
different to be distinctive to express power in\h
their own particular way and thus Nietzsche would\h\h
say in our understanding of genetic mutation for\h
example and its role in evolution on the macro\h\h
scale you know the process of speciation we have\h
a phenomenon that's described by Will To Power\h\h
on the level of human\h
psychology or human sociality\h\h
Will To Power is an explanatory\h
principle for Human Action also\h\h
I mean in one sense power or potency is a\h
prerequisite for acting at all and in terms\h\h
of examining human motivations we find the desire\h
to become powerful and to feel powerful and to\h\h
manifest power at the root of all of them\h
Nietzsche argues for example that there's\h\h
no truly selfless act because all selfless\h
acts emerge from a foundation of selfishness\h\h
in fact selfishness and selflessness are not\h
opposites at all but gradations of the same thing\h\h
that our motivations can be coarse or refined\h
such that both the philanthropist and the car\h\h
thief are both expressing their Will To Power\h
or to put it another way our identity can be\h\h
complex and individual or rigid and inherited\h
like the difference between us Children of the\h\h
age you know of uh of authenticity of discovering\h
our true selves um and someone placed in into a\h\h
role in Chinese Society by which he gains his\h
identity by family and class um and so we can\h\h
see how in various circumstances or different\h
cultural contexts different types of motivations\h\h
or different types of identities or means of\h
gaining one could be your means of advancing\h\h
um but they all we see a Will To Power as\h
a fundamental principle in all of these\h\h
and finally uh I mean just on the\h
moral level or The Meta moral level\h\h
Nietzsche argues all moralities that have\h
ever been created involve an element of self\h\h
overcoming shy of the basist Hedonism in which\h
one abandons discipline and restraint altogether\h\h
and lives purely according to one's impulses\h
any system of right and wrong requires that\h\h
one overcomes impulses instincts feelings either\h
abstaining altogether withholding from indulging\h\h
or doing so only in like a proper context\h
all morality is the attempt for the self to\h\h
challenge itself to challenge its own weaknesses\h
and shortcomings and become something greater\h\h
and so all of these are aspects of human life\h
and what life is is Will To Power from every\h\h
single one of those perspectives for Nietzsche\h
as something that he sees revealed empirically\h\h
in the world and it's it will to power is the\h
intelligible content which is generalizable\h\h
across all of these perspectives and Nietzsche\h
believes this again not because it's something we\h\h
find when we look deep within ourselves which is\h
what Mike schopenhauer's means trying to get over\h\h
the uh phenomena numina chasm uh you know although\h
I would argue that Nietzsche probably does believe\h\h
that if we did that honestly we would discover\h
will to power but that's not his reasoning for\h\h
for seeing it everywhere in the world right but\h
it's because it's manifest in all these observable\h\h
um phenomena and thus whatever the world might be\h
independent of the human mind we can say without\h\h
a doubt that the world for us the world as we\h
experience it is Will To Power Will To Power\h\h
is the simplest most fundamental statement\h
of what the world is like without an appeal\h\h
to anything outside of it being necessary\h
and without invoking a Divine personality\h\h
or an intelligence or purpose to life this\h
view life has no Transcendent value that is\h\h
to say a value imposed upon it from a world\h
that is above it and it has no purpose nature\h\h
says unless the circuit of Eternal recurrence\h
itself is a purpose and it has no intelligence\h\h
except insofar as we're a part of it and we're\h
intelligent but it seems that our intelligence\h\h
comes out of a blind unintelligent World in which\h
intelligence is not the rule but the exception\h\h
so now we'll look at a couple of Nietzsche\h
passages on life uh the first is his rebuke\h\h
to the stoics stoicism represents an attempt to\h
master one's passions so that one's not carried\h\h
away by their emotions and one doesn't\h
attach to one's current circumstances\h\h
um you know a common practice might be to\h
visualize what tragedies can and will befall you\h\h
um and so the stoic lives in the knowledge of\h
nature of what nature is really like all its\h\h
forms are fleeting and impermanent including\h
us and this is all uh just to give context I'm\h\h
not really reading this because of Nietzsche's\h
attack on the stoics but rather because of what\h\h
he says about life and nature in this section and\h
so this is section 9 of Beyond Good and Evil quote\h\h
according to Nature you want to live oh you Noble\h
stoics what deceptive words these are imagine\h\h
a being like nature wasteful beyond measure\h
indifferent beyond measure without purposes and\h\h
consideration without mercy and Justice fertile\h
and desolate and uncertain at the same time\h\h
imagine indifference itself as a power how\h
could you live according to this indifference\h\h
is that not precisely wanting to be other\h
than this nature is not living estimating\h\h
preferring being unjust being limited\h
wanting to be different and supposing\h\h
you're imperative live according to Nature meant\h
at bottom as much as live according to life\h\h
how could you not do that why make a principle\h
of what you yourselves are and must be end quote
so very wonderful passage um what's funny about\h
it is uh and and what's funny about Nietzsche's\h\h
criticism of the stoics is that I think these\h
charges could be levied at him to some extent\h\h
um I mean if Nietzsche is to have a life-affirming\h
philosophy right is he not guilty of also\h\h
extolling us to live according to life but I\h
would argue um being wife of affirming does not\h\h
mean that Nietzsche is affirming a certain path of\h
life as more natural or closer to life than others\h\h
rather with Nietzsche's insight one could\h
choose to accept the fundamental nature\h\h
of what life is or not one could\h
be grateful for being alive or not\h\h
um but whether you are of one temperament or\h
the other has nothing to do with Nietzsche right\h\h
um and I think Nietzsche has a real\h
point that many philosophers and many\h\h
ideologies and religions throughout\h
time have ultimately been anti-life\h\h
um and so I would because I think that is a\h
meaningful thing to talk about what is anti-life\h\h
I would reject the argument that it's like a\h
meaningless distinction there are real examples of\h\h
people who have said no to life right schopenhauer\h
Christianity Buddhism and so on um Nietzsche's I\h\h
mean and you know if of course if you phrase it\h
to a Christian like are you anti-life virtually no\h\h
Christian's gonna say yes to that but if you ask\h
them in more specific terms like is your you know\h\h
is your like what is your life here worth compared\h
to what your uh whether your soul is saved you\h\h
go to heaven worth I mean they'll all tell you\h
that that the latter is way more important right
um and so I I think Nietzsche's definition\h
of these ideologies as anti-life uh and\h\h
distinguishing them from what a life-affirming\h
philosophy would be is actually descriptive\h\h
um whether we would agree that it he successfully\h
applied creates a philosophy of life or not right\h\h
but on the other hand um so Nietzsche here he's\h
making a principle of Will To Power and if Will\h\h
To Power is life why make a principle of what we\h
ourselves are and must be and perhaps the only\h\h
answer here is that Nietzsche is simply raising\h
this truth into our Consciousness and I don't\h\h
think he imagines that he can in any fundamental\h
way change the driving force of reality and\h\h
all human life and then again by expanding our\h
knowledge and our understanding we gain a greater\h\h
more complete perspective and if it happens to\h
follow from this that you make changes to your\h\h
life your way of life then so much the better but\h
just as zarathustra doesn't want us to follow him\h\h
um and wants to remind us that the poets lie too\h
much I think we can be safe in saying Nietzsche\h\h
um well he doesn't ever lay out a a list of\h
like these are the proper ways to manifest\h\h
your Will To Power right that's sort of\h
what I'm getting at now he does show ways\h\h
that are he points out a examples where manif\h
where will to power is turned against itself\h\h
and so that's sort of you know it's like if you\h
if you care about life you should probably avoid\h\h
the ways in which your life is going to be\h
um self-defeating or self-undermining right\h\h
um but uh we'll discuss this more you know as\h
we go on um but so from this this description\h\h
of what life is indifferent desolate and abundant\h
at the same time arbitrary and cruel in a sense\h\h
um so suppose we agree with that definition and\h
supposing this perception of what life is has been\h\h
raised into our consciousness the world would now\h
appear differently and our own way of life could\h\h
be brought under a more critical eye we might\h
have grounds to make new judgments and assessments\h\h
um and that's very important because what\h
comes out in this passage is living as\h\h
judging evaluating something I made reference\h
to earlier but as Nietzsche says in this quote\h\h
life is quote estimating preferring being unjust\h
being limited wanting to be different end quote\h\h
life is not a primarily self-preservative Force\h
it's a generating Force what life is is not the\h\h
passing on of the same genes that isn't really the\h
essence of life it would be the essence of life\h\h
would be again mutation endlessly individuating\h
forms becoming more complex more rarified more\h\h
specialized more speciated and notice this\h
process is fundamentally just as innocent as\h\h
it is arbitrary and unjust these preferences\h
these judgments aren't founded in reason\h\h
um you know they're just expressions of the\h
drives within the organisms reaching out\h\h
into the world reacting physiologically\h
when something gives pain or pleasure\h\h
or when something appears ugly or beautiful
um and so for example whether you find someone\h
else attractive or not beautiful or not it's\h\h
not in any way the product of a rational\h
syllogism or a well-considered argument or\h\h
a moral imperative and when I you know to\h
speak for myself when I look at the most\h\h
important things in my life I find almost none\h
of them derived from these things right life's\h\h
judgments are spontaneous non-rational preferences\h
it's Direct valuation on an intuitive level\h\h
uh let's look at another passage describing\h
what life is I probably the most important one\h\h
from the spokes orthostra this is an excerpt from\h
on self-overcoming which is a chapter from the\h\h
second part of the novel again zarathistra speaks\h
to us on the essence of living and he recounts\h\h
things that he has heard in an encounter with\h
the character of life itself life personified\h\h
and as the context for the passage\h
zerthustra prefaces all this by saying\h\h
that he's telling us this story so we\h
understand his words on Good and Evil\h\h
so we cannot understand zerothistra's morality and\h
his condemnation of good versus evil type moral\h\h
systems until we understand what he believes\h
about life and living and so the passage quote
wherever I found the living there I heard also\h
the speech on obedience whatever lives obeys\h\h
and this is the second point he who\h
cannot obey himself is commanded\h\h
that is the nature of the living this however is\h
the third point that I heard that commanding is\h\h
harder than obeying and not only because he who\h
commands must carry the burden of all who obey\h\h
and because this burden May easily crush\h
him an experiment in Hazard appeared to\h\h
me to be in all commanding and whenever\h
the living commands it hazards itself\h\h
indeed even when it commands itself it must\h
still pay for its commanding it must become the\h\h
judge Avenger and the victim of its own law end\h
quote and so remember morality is self-overcoming\h\h
the inner character of morality is\h
Will To Power like everything else\h\h
uh what is morality it is and the language of this\h
passage issuing commands to oneself completely\h\h
absent from this vision is anything like freedom\h
of the will or the libertarian application of uh\h\h
you know some quality of reason to govern Human\h
Action rather it's simply a question of whether\h\h
one has the strength to command oneself and if\h
not then one shall be commanded his drives rather\h\h
than the other way around there's no detaunt\h
no equilibrium the choice is to command or be\h\h
commanded and in a way in a way they both sort\h
of imply uh one another um but uh yeah the idea\h\h
is that it's always better to be Commander too is\h
short-sighted all life is an experiment in most\h\h
experiments fail right so to dare to allow your\h
judgments your non-rational arbitrary preferences\h\h
that your will is aimed at to reshape your\h
world and to even bind others Wills to your own
um or just on the more basic level\h
to take command of your own life\h\h
and reshape it into an artistic pattern\h
right giving style as nietzsa says these\h\h
are dangerous experiments and most people\h
throughout history do not do this experiment\h\h
most people throughout time live their life in\h
accord with the inherited conventional pattern\h\h
and yet there's this driving will beneath us\h
all and always this tendency for some number\h\h
of us to burst forward attempting to be different\h
and to Define ourselves individually and you know\h\h
like but how many Aquatic Life forms suffocated\h
above the water until some muted some of them\h\h
mutated into forms that could endure like more\h
and more exposure to the oxygen atmosphere right\h\h
so advancement requires vast sacrifices and as\h
this passage indicates we always have to we always\h\h
have to pay for it in some way it's a reality\h
of life um but the passage gets tougher still\h\h
quotes where I found the living\h
there I found Will To Power\h\h
and even in the will of those who\h
serve I found the will to be master\h\h
that the weaker should serve the stronger to\h
that it is persuaded by its own will which\h\h
would be Master over what is weak or still this\h
is the one pleasure it does not want to renounce\h\h
and as the smaller yields to the greater that it\h
may have pleasure and power over the smallest thus\h\h
even the greatest still yields and for the sake\h
of power risks life that is the yielding of the\h\h
greater it is Hazard and danger and casting\h
dice for death and where men make sacrifices\h\h
and serve and cast Amorous glances there too is\h
the will to be master along stealthy paths the\h\h
weaker Steels into the castle and into the very\h
heart of the more powerful and there steals power\h\h
and life confided the secret to me behold it\h
said I am that which must always overcome itself\h\h
indeed you call it a will to procreate\h
or a drive to an end to something higher\h\h
farther more manifold but all this is one and one\h
Secret rather would I perish then forswear this\h\h
and verily where there is perishing and a falling\h
of leaves behold their life sacrifices itself\h\h
for power that I must be a struggle and to\h
be coming and an end and an opposition to\h\h
ends alas whoever guesses what is my will should\h
also guess on what crooked paths it must proceed\h\h
whatever I create and however much I\h
love it soon I must oppose it and my love\h\h
thus my will wills it and you too lover of\h
knowledge are only a path and a footprint\h\h
of my will my Will To Power walks also on the\h
heels of your will to truth indeed the truth\h\h
was not hit by him who shot at it with the word\h
of will to existence that will does not exist\h\h
for what does not exist cannot will but what is\h
in existence how could that still want existence\h\h
only where there is life is there also will not\h
will to life but thus I teach you will to power\h\h
there is much that life esteems\h
more highly than life itself\h\h
but out of the esteeming itself\h
speaks Will To Power end quote
so we have the repudiation at the end\h
there of schopenhauer's idea of the\h\h
will to exist or the will to live we have the\h
idea that life is that which overcomes itself\h\h
and that life sacrifices itself for power and that\h
this is the fundamental nature of Will's power\h\h
meaning life itself is Will To Power is\h
self-overcoming self life is judging praising\h\h
being different as we if we were to draw in\h
from the other path passage and the basis\h\h
of all of this is physiological preference\h
and as such the nature of life is valuing\h\h
another way of saying that is how he brings it\h
out at the end here saying that to lives to esteem\h\h
if we are to be the measure of things which all\h
life must be for itself and for its own kind then\h\h
we must self-legislate that good just as the\h
hawk must determine its own good and the lamb\h\h
must determine its own good right but we humans\h
it's a little different because we perhaps value\h\h
more powerfully and more subtly than any other\h
being ever has and that's why our Will To Power\h\h
precedes un crooked paths even those in a position\h
of servitude have their ways of gaining power over\h\h
the Masters we can find the expressions of Will To\h
Power in the most subtle ways whether in charity\h\h
and patronage or in subterfusion infidelity all\h
manner of human behaviors and tendencies present\h\h
themselves in our cognition as wholly separate\h
from this fundamental character of life we hide it\h\h
behind ideas like the search for the truth but the\h
high estimation of Truth just like the estimations\h\h
we make of any phenomena speak to the fact that\h
steaming itself is our nature judging valuing\h\h
measuring is nature it is a prerequisite for\h
any such evaluation and within this fundamental\h\h
activity we see the essence of Worlds of power the\h
willingness to impose our standards upon reality\h\h
and then manifest those standards with force\h
and when we zoom out so to speak and consider\h\h
the total picture of life Life as a whole is\h
always doing this meaning that life is constantly\h\h
judging which forms or biological patterns\h
are worthy of esteem and which ones are not\h\h
insofar as this war of all against all takes\h
place continually across generations of life\h\h
forms all eating each other and competing for\h
the feeding ground and the right to reproduce\h\h
so with this perhaps uh somewhat\h
troubling picture of what life is\h\h
and who we are as living beings is there such a\h
thing as the good life Nietzsche would obviously\h\h
say yes and although his conception of it\h
changes a little bit throughout his career\h\h
in his early days he believes that\h
life can be aesthetically Justified\h\h
this is as he writes in uh birth of tragedy\h
and this has a sense to it if life is basically\h\h
arbitrary estimations on the direct perceptual\h
level why can't the good life Simply Be The\h\h
Beautiful Life if we're living according to\h
brute preference why not aesthetic preference\h\h
um this particular form of aesthetic\h
preference Nietzsche advocates is what\h\h
we might call the tragic perspective on life\h
this is the perspective cultivated artistically\h\h
through a dramatic tragedy in ancient Greece of a\h
cheerful fatalism in the face of one's destruction\h\h
we can better understand this view\h
by what Nietzsche opposes it to\h\h
he opposes this view to what he calls the\h
theoretic approach which begins with Socrates\h\h
and birth of tragedy he writes of the\h
cultural divide between theoretic and\h\h
the tragic the theoretical life is a life lived\h
according to reason according to the view that\h\h
human problems can be solved by reason in a\h
lasting way and human life and Society can be\h\h
improved by reason it is fundamentally a form\h
of optimism and the best representative for it\h\h
is Socrates because he offers the strongest\h
and most noteworthy case for this worldview\h\h
an important point in all this is\h
that socrates's view is for Nietzsche\h\h
ultimately an aesthetic view Socrates is at bottom\h
driven by an irrational estimation of the truth\h\h
that's uh Nietzsche's fundamental criticism of him\h
and I think the various Paths of ideas or thoughts\h\h
that one could follow just from the explosive\h
quality of that initial statement you know that\h\h
initial accusation in niche's career it contains\h
all the seeds of Nietzsche's later philosophy\h\h
but in any case so he presents Socrates and birth\h
of tragedy as totally unartistic but he clarifies\h\h
in his later preface to the work that socrates's\h
irony is that very thing that he irrationally\h\h
valued the truth about all things and that this is\h
in itself an expression of socrates's underlying\h\h
nature his arbitrary demand for life his demand\h
that all reality be bound under one universal\h\h
principle of reason and that all illusions of\h
superstition and Prejudice be banned because\h\h
under this Socratic aesthetic those things are\h
ugly and so it's all socrates's aesthetic judgment\h\h
any questions was that oh great ironist was\h
that perhaps your irony now Nietzsche's opposing\h\h
aesthetic Outlook is one which is pessimistic and\h
again Nietzsche believes he's a rather positive\h\h
representative of the Outlook Because he believes\h
himself to be a pessimist of strength and thus the\h\h
tragic worldview is the affirmation of all of the\h
character of life that we just discussed with the\h\h
full realization that this entails the Embrace of\h
one's own downfall we do not accept any optimistic\h\h
or morally redeeming narratives about life and\h
embrace wholeheartedly that entropy always wins\h\h
life is short the Good Die Young bad things happen\h
to good people pride comes before the fall history\h\h
is a series of cycles of a rise followed by a fall\h
just like all organisms are born and then they die\h\h
but one does not count any of these\h
honestly ascertained aspects of\h\h
human life as charges against it the\h
tragic aesthetic instead is defined by\h\h
emphasizing the beauty inherent to the\h
fundamentally entropic nature of life story seen\h\h
in total of a tragic figure is somehow beautiful\h
to us and Nietzsche believes that this experience\h\h
occurs when we engage with the tragic because we\h
are confronting the terrifying reality of life\h\h
in such a manner that it does not immediately\h
destroy us right and so we feel that we are\h\h
through the experience of tragic art\h
overcoming the terrifying nature of\h\h
the World by encountering it and surviving it by\h
that token to use a heretical word in this context\h\h
transcending it and turning it into art\h
the experience of uh beauty or the sublime
now Nietzsche didn't stick with this answer as\h
to what the good life is because this answer\h\h
I mean like any other answer to the question\h
of what the good life is his perspectable to\h\h
really answer the question in general terms\h
we have to make it into a meta question\h\h
what later Nietzsche eventually concludes in\h
a mindset more of that type in the metal world\h\h
uh what he later concludes it's related to\h
his understanding of what every attempt at\h\h
creating the good life has been\h
and that is the will to power\h\h
that the will to power is expressed in\h
the socratic quest to know the truth in\h\h
order to practice virtue as much as Will To\h
Power is expressed in the Christian ethos to\h\h
love thy enemy and resist not evil or the\h
Buddhist ethos to renounce selfish craving\h\h
all are forms of self overcoming and all our\h
attempts to impose a judgment on the world\h\h
Nietzsche then inquires about the direction in\h
which this transformation proceeds or how these\h\h
judgments on the world eventually manifest in\h
human life and the reason why he does this is\h\h
because in seeing that element of Will To Power\h
and all of these answers and how each one is\h\h
sort of from a different perspective right but\h
it's always manifesting this world's power thing\h\h
um I think he's able to see that his\h
own attempt to impose an aesthetic\h\h
judgment on the world was actually\h
not a newer Innovative thing at all\h\h
or Innovative notion um that it's simply\h
what every religion has been trying to do\h\h
and that the real question that we should\h
be asking is why is it that all of these\h\h
Aesthetics that already exist do not work for\h
us anymore that might be one way to put it\h\h
so what is it that these various moralities and\h
religions have given rise to and in a strong sense\h\h
Nietzsche is very empirical here all the various\h
manifestations of the world's power have these\h\h
fundamental characteristics that we've described\h
but not all its manifestations are created equal\h\h
accordingly some ways of life are stronger\h
and some are weaker or we might say healthier\h\h
or sicker or to put it in the language we used\h
earlier some are ascending Paths of life meaning\h\h
that these are expressions of strength which give\h
rise to more strength but some are descending\h\h
which represents a degeneration into weaker and\h
weaker forms so it's still a manifestation of your\h\h
strength but it's a manifestation of your strength\h
that get doesn't give rise to more strength but to\h\h
um but to weakness and so um it's the difference\h
between a positive feedback loop and a negative\h\h
feedback loop and so the good life is the\h
positive feedback loop that is the healthy\h\h
life in the sense of this the life-affirming\h
life right and we should remind ourselves at\h\h
this point that while this statement does have a\h
very figurative Dimension to it it also has a very\h\h
um literal dimension because the root of this\h
all is still what physiological our judgments and\h\h
preferences occur at that physiological level and\h
so one strength to order their drives according\h\h
to such a life ascending manifestation of will\h
that's determined at the physiological level\h\h
if we're going to take seriously the idea that\h
human beings are bodies that what we are is what\h\h
we appear to be by all observation in the world of\h
direct perception than where physical beings and\h\h
our psychic life in the sense of the psychological\h
right as well as our social life and their our\h\h
moral life all of this sort of flows out of the\h
headwaters of our own nature of the conditions\h\h
that produced us aspects of our temperament um\h
but another way to look at it would be like maybe\h\h
how much physical Vitality we have or we\h
might say how much Vitality do we have left\h\h
and so Nietzsche believes that weak or\h
self-undermining moral values for example\h\h
are at bottom the product of\h
a weary degenerating person\h\h
and that this is true in some sense of them\h
physiologically as well as psychologically\h\h
and so that's the root of everything we\h
are so we look at it in the physical sense\h\h
um I mean on the other hand though it's\h
entirely possible for someone who's young\h\h
and otherwise physiologically healthy to have\h
a weary or degenerative view of life and life\h\h
is not a frozen thing again it's not being\h
so we can't inquire as to whether someone's\h\h
way of life is apparently healthy uh in the\h
here and now and then have done with it right\h\h
we are viewing people as human becomings\h
rather than human beings as a dynamic process\h\h
which is ever unfolding and never really\h
standing still and so like with everything\h\h
we can't really say whether life is\h
healthy until we know what it led to\h\h
what did it give rise to right and so we always\h
have to remember in pursuing the good life\h\h
um the important thing is what we spend our\h
lives uh what are we what direction are we\h\h
moving in what are we bringing forth if we try\h
to hold on to our life or hold on to it the way\h\h
it is now from a Devotion to the self-preservative\h
Instinct will will always fail in that task right\h\h
when it's all over you'll be gone anyway and and\h
uh all that's going to be left is whatever it is\h\h
you've given rise to it's not really an option\h
but so what is the good life to Nature we're\h\h
still sort of answering this question and with all\h
of that all this piece isn't a place we could say\h\h
this is where the concept of the younger man comes\h
into play It's the good life is in so many words\h\h
to live in such a way that you bring forth the\h
over man and this simply means to live in such\h\h
a way that your life is aimed at bringing forth\h
something greater than you are it means to live\h\h
your life and longing for something beyond your\h
current Horizons and it means being willing to\h\h
make sacrifices which emphasizes a lot to spend\h
yourself and your life and spend Your vitality\h\h
and in this the over man is the promise of\h
the Redemption of mankind from all its faults\h\h
it's a dare I say it faith and the\h
ascendance of Life winning out over\h\h
the degeneration of life it's faith\h
in the positive feedback loop of life
um and so can we say in general terms what that\h
good life looks like I mean well we see it in\h\h
zarathus just prologue and the tightrope Walker\h
the jester I mean the literal word translation\h\h
means rope dancer um there it's roughly equivalent\h
to what we would mean by a tight rope Walker but\h\h
you have the word dancer there in in German and\h
so uh you know that's very important because in\h\h
Nietzsche dancing has such a metaphor for you\h
know the expression of the deepest happiness\h\h
of the you know anyway uh so the Rope dancer\h
the sort of clownish character this gesture\h\h
lives his life in practice of a dangerous\h
craft and he dies while performing his craft\h\h
and um zarathustra you know uh Praises him in in\h
some sense it's Nietzsche's exaltation to us to\h\h
live dangerously build your temples on the slopes\h
of Mount Vesuvius so fully commit to your great\h\h
passions in life and be honest about what it is\h
that drives you which is something that may take\h\h
you years to explore and come to any understanding\h
of and many great and dangerous experiments\h\h
to see of what happens when you let\h
certain drives Take the Wheel so to speak\h\h
um so let's look at some examples of good\h
lives which I think might be instructive um\h\h
Nietzsche would suggest we look to if we want an\h
example of the good life and the nietzsian sense\h\h
should look to figures such as Getta a true\h
Renaissance Man I mean he wrote beautifully\h\h
in every style of literature expanded\h
the possibilities for the German language\h\h
um had this vast catalog of poems and guerta\h
stands as a soul torn between classical Aesthetics\h\h
and the fiery passion of Romanticism or we could\h
consider a non-artist a completely non-theoretical\h\h
man a man praised by the aforementioned in fact as\h
much as by Hegel and many of the intellectuals of\h\h
his time Napoleon Bonaparte Napoleon emerges from\h
the chaos and the excess of the French Revolution\h\h
in order to produce a new French Empire and in\h
the process he constructs the modern French state\h\h
and he is by the Numbers the most effective\h
military commander of all time but to this very\h\h
day and by a mile and so just as good to reshaped\h
the German artistic landscape in his own image\h\h
Napoleon reshaped the French political landscape\h
in his own image these were men who dared to\h\h
command to follow the dictates of their will\h
and impose their judgments and that was a risk a\h\h
hazard as Napoleon says when Fortune is done with\h
him quote she will break me like a glass end quote\h\h
but you know most won't measure up to these\h
examples many will fail some like Caesar will\h\h
succeed but in their moment of Triumph when\h
their Victory is barely drawn a breath they\h\h
meet their downfall but in the image of such\h
people whether we find it attainable or not\h\h
we may find the inspiration to\h
attempt to emulate The Good Life
in Twilight of idols the section\h
skirmishes of an untimely man\h\h
number 48 we find this passage\h
which references Napoleon\h\h
and speaks of him in the language of being\h
this ideal for what ascending life looks like\h\h
Nietzsche makes reference to the idea of a\h
return to Nature and I think there he's primarily\h\h
rebutting the rason ideals concerning what such a\h
thing would entail uh quote progress in my sense\h\h
I too speak of Return To Nature although it\h
is really not a going back but a going up\h\h
an Ascent to the high free even\h
terrible nature and naturalness\h\h
where great tasks are something\h
one plays with one may play with\h\h
to put it metaphorically Napoleon was a piece\h
of Return To Nature as I understand the phrase\h\h
for example and Rebus tacticus even more as\h
military men know in matters of strategy end quote\h\h
so he references their Napoleon's extraordinary\h
record as a tactician and the fact that he was\h\h
a very he was a man who acted it seemed on an\h
instinct right uh so Nietzsche often speaks of\h\h
great and terrible individuals right and there are\h
many ways in which we could take that description\h\h
but at bottom I think the important thing he's\h
getting at the essentially innocent nature of all\h\h
of our drives innocent because they're natural\h
innocent in the way that it's innocent when\h\h
a hawk eats a little field mouse right the\h
high free terrible naturalness he speaks of\h\h
as a human being who's recaptured this sense\h
of innocence and thus is free to follow the\h\h
commands of his own will because he's freed from\h
imposing guilt or imposing moral condemnation upon\h\h
those drives and so yes such a person might\h
end up doing what we would call evil things\h\h
but that's by no means the focus of\h
what Nietzsche is talking about here\h\h
um you know Napoleon's not great because of like\h
a body count right that would be a rather morbid\h\h
um the point of living the good life is not to\h
do evil things I mean it's the moralists will\h\h
try and scare us by making us uh you know\h
think that that's what any sort of belief\h\h
in life in the world outside of a Transcendent or\h
Divine Telos that's what that means but Nietzsche\h\h
Nietzsche is just simply demanding of\h
himself that he'd be honest with us here\h\h
and admit that a return to innocent human nature\h
in fact means getting in touch with a part of\h\h
ourselves which is passionate domineering\h
and at times violent and unreasonable\h\h
in the very next section of Twilight of Idols\h
Nietzsche gives us his assessment of Gita this\h\h
is section 49 quote get her not a German event but\h
a European one a magnificent attempt to overcome\h\h
the 18th century by a return to Nature by an\h
Ascent to the naturalness of the Renaissance\h\h
kind of self-overcoming on the part of that\h
century he bore its strongest instincts within\h\h
himself the sensibility the idolatry of nature\h
the anti-historic the idealistic the unreal and\h\h
revolutionary the latter merely being a form\h
of the unreal he sought help from history\h\h
Natural Science Antiquity and also Spinoza but\h
above all from practical activity he surrounded\h\h
himself with limited Horizons he did not retire\h
from life but put himself into the midst of it\h\h
he was not faint-hearted but took as much as\h
possible upon himself over himself into himself\h\h
what he wanted was totality he fought the mutual\h
extraneousness of Reason senses feeling and will\h\h
preached with the most abhorrent\h
scholasticism by Kant the antipode of ghetta\h\h
he disciplined himself to\h
wholeness he created himself\h\h
in the middle of an age with an unreal\h
Outlook ghetto was a convinced realist\h\h
he said yes to everything that was related to him\h
in this respect and he had no greater experience\h\h
than that inzrealism most real being called\h
Napoleon Goethe conceived a human being who would\h\h
be strong Highly Educated skillful in all bodily\h
matters self-controlled reverent toward himself\h\h
and who might dare to afford the whole range\h
and wealth of being natural being strong enough\h\h
for such freedom the man of Tolerance not from\h
weakness but from strength because he knows how to\h\h
use his to his Advantage even that from which the\h
average nature would perish the Man For Whom there\h\h
is no longer anything that is forbidden unless\h
it be weakness whether called Vice or virtue\h\h
such a spirit who has become free stands amid\h
the cosmos with a joyous and trusting fatalism\h\h
in the Fate that only the particular is loathsome\h
and that all is redeemed and affirmed in the whole\h\h
he does not negate anymore such a faith\h
however is the highest of all possible faiths\h\h
I have baptized it with the\h
name of Dionysus end quote
and so very clear terms\h
Nietzsche calls Gerta dianesian\h\h
but in a very specific meaning of the\h
dionysian which we've talked about\h\h
so in comparing and contrasting you know\h
the profiles of Napoleon and Gerta surely\h\h
both are candidates for what Nietzsche would\h
call The Good Life and we have a more or less\h\h
adequate picture of what it entails naturalness\h
straightforwardness and a trusting fatalism
um and of course you know the fact that both\h
create something great beyond themselves which is\h\h
an imposition of their creative will and reality\h
but the fatalism aspect you know in other places\h\h
Nietzsche critical criticized um excuse me uh\h
criticized a fatalistic attitude in the sense\h\h
of being oppressed or like abound fatalism what he\h
disparagingly calls Muhammad in fatalism but this\h\h
trusting fatalism that he describes is different\h
it's trusting in life trusting in necessity\h\h
um feeling that everything is redeemed in\h
the whole right um that in the whole picture\h\h
um life is more beautiful than it is ugly\h
we might say and um you know in the full\h\h
awareness of the danger Napoleon brought upon\h
himself but you know without a care for it\h\h
he pursues this ambitious course in life\h
that's a perfect example of trusting fatalism
um and the fruits of such a natural healthy life\h
are Freedom gratitude a sense of cheerfulness\h\h
but notice it's not uh when we're talking\h
about a life that's free and natural\h\h
remember when Nietzsche describes Gerta as a\h
return to Nature he's already said what that\h\h
means and that there's this inherently it's like\h
his conception of what that means is a nature that\h\h
is inherently sort of uh violent and dangerous but\h
those who most profoundly mantle that role in life\h\h
become something that's almost more\h
than human more like a cataclysmic event\h\h
shock wave that rocks an entire continent a force\h
that reshapes an entire culture launches an entire\h\h
artistic movement and so in this context perhaps\h
we might look at the third question what what\h\h
facilitates the good life this is in effect\h
a question of Nietzsche and virtues and again\h\h
while we may consider these examples uh we must\h
understand that the passages that I'm going to\h\h
read in this respect don't refer to any absolute\h
claim of morality or Universal application for\h\h
all the reasons we've already talked about um you\h
know everyone has their own way their own virtues\h\h
to cultivate and so on Nietzsche says that your\h
most precious virtues will be known to you alone\h\h
and you will not even have a name for them right\h
because the most personal things are the things\h\h
which can't be shared by the universal word\h
Concepts that we communicate with via language\h\h
um but Nietzsche nevertheless offers us a few\h
uh suggestions about the cultivation of a good\h\h
life and so there are a few reliable pieces of\h
wisdom he has for those of us who wish to live a\h\h
healthy life uh this isn't Beyond Good and Evil\h
284. I'll quote here in an Abridged form quote\h\h
to live with tremendous and proud composure\h
always Beyond to have and not to have one's\h\h
effects one's pro and con at will to condescend\h
to them for a few hours to seat oneself on them\h\h
as a horse often as on an ass for one must know\h
how to make use of their stupidity as much as\h\h
of their fire and to choose for company\h
that impish and cheerful Vice courtesy\h\h
and to remain master of one's four Virtues\h
Of Courage Insight sympathy and solitude\h\h
for Solitude is a virtue for us as a Sublime\h
bent and urge for cleanliness which guesses\h\h
how all contact between man and man in\h
society involves inevitable uncleanliness\h\h
all Community makes men somehow somewhere sometime\h
common end quote so for virtues here first courage\h\h
this is required for the good life because courage\h
is required for any Command Decision right an act\h\h
of will we might say um because as we said during\h
the act in one's own will on one's own judgments\h\h
is dangerous and we have insight which means\h
not acting based on superficial qualities or\h\h
Surface level observations that would just see\h
you misled and would be counterproductive these\h\h
virtues are very uh virtuous stick in the old\h
sense of the word right in terms of efficiency\h\h
sympathy is an odd one for Nietzsche one might\h
think especially because He follows it up with\h\h
Solitude which he justifies by saying that all\h
participation in society makes us unclean and\h\h
he means I think intellectually morally\h
emotionally unclean right we're getting\h\h
uh communicated all these uh sort of sick\h
herd values into our heads more in society\h\h
um but this reveals I think that we have two\h
sort of couplets within the four which are\h\h
sort of counterbalancing you know you need to\h
be courageous which means suspending judgment\h\h
and acting uh or like suspending deliberation\h
and acting it's a better way to put it and yet\h\h
one also needs Insight which means not acting\h
blindly or based on short-term interests that\h\h
are in the long term sense unhealthy right so\h
sort of a counterbalance to the capacity for\h\h
Action that you need in Courage uh Insight is the\h
capacity for reflection in some sense and then uh\h\h
you know we also need a sense of sympathy a\h
sincere heartfelt emotional connection to other\h\h
human beings that's natural uh for human beings\h
as much as anything else we've been talking about\h\h
um it's natural between members of a family or\h
with people we love and it it's required that we\h\h
that it exists to some extent in order to function\h
in society it's the basis of all things like you\h\h
know courtesy and respect and charity many of\h
these socially beneficial behaviors and attitudes\h\h
that are required for civilization as a\h
project to continue and yet if we truly\h\h
want greatness in our lives Solitude is\h
required one has to be able to leave the\h\h
endless all-pervasive influence of\h
the thoughts of others this chorus\h\h
of Judge judging voices all around us that\h
render our own individual judgments moot\h\h
or our experimental judgments forbidden right\h
declare them immoral harmful dangerous and so\h\h
the judgmental voice of the majority exists\h
with us at all times in the form of conscience\h\h
and it's more strongly felt the more often we're\h
exposed to the judgments of others and that makes\h\h
us all common as he says somehow some way it\h
imparts some of the same thoughts or the same\h\h
types of thoughts and so for someone to live the\h
good life and to bring forth something greater\h\h
something stronger something healthier they\h
have to be able to move outside of the current\h\h
cultural moral software one has to\h
cultivate the ability to think their\h\h
own thoughts because that's the only way to\h
go beyond the current values which that's the\h\h
possibility of the great individual who\h
reshapes said values creates new things\h\h
Anita has another set of four virtues in a\h
different place in the book Daybreak or the dawn\h\h
this is section 556 it's similar but it's\h
not exactly the same uh list of Virtues\h\h
but we can see a similar reasoning here so\h
this is a different list as it appears quote\h\h
the good four honest with ourselves and whoever\h
else is our friend courageous with the Enemy\h\h
magnanimous with the vanquished courteous always\h
thus the four cardinal virtues want us end quote\h\h
so courage is included in both out of these two\h
lists of four the total seven cardinal nietzsian\h\h
virtues would be courage Insight sympathy\h
Solitude courtesy magnanimity and honesty\h\h
and I hope everyone can hear when I say the\h
phrase card Cardinal niche in virtues that my\h\h
tongue is in my cheek here nevertheless that's\h
as good a list of Virtues as any religions ever\h\h
produced and maybe better than any religion has\h
produced in far insofar as uh we have solitude\h\h
as a virtue it's a masterful idea and\h
a unique contribution of Nietzsche\h\h
uh Kaufman points out in a footnote to\h
the good four passage that Plato also\h\h
has for cardinal virtues which are wisdom\h
courage Temperance and justice um so that's\h\h
interesting courage appears in both Nietzsche's\h
lists and in Plato's there's some additional\h\h
overlap and that you know wisdom and insight\h
probably could be roughly considered analogous\h\h
um temperance kind of similar to magnanimity to\h
some degree but it's interesting the way in which\h\h
they contradict one another because Justice is\h
absent from Nietzsche's list and in fact something\h\h
like justice would generally be considered a vice\h
for Nietzsche zarathistra says in the passage on\h\h
the tarantulas that if you know for the culture\h
Warrior who's totally concerned with Justice the\h\h
thing that actually stands behind that word is the\h
desire for Revenge says the Bridge To His Highest\h\h
Hope For Humanity and a rainbow after long storms\h
is that mankind shall be delivered from Revenge\h\h
as if he's redeeming man from a sin we\h
might say to belabor the point right\h\h
so look to the cheerful trusting fatalism that\h
Nietzsche mentioned earlier in describing guerta\h\h
and which could also be applied to Napoleon\h
why such a fatalistic Embrace of necessity\h\h
because in this world as Will To Power we\h
find nothing of guilt or moral responsibility\h\h
and so if we're dutiful to the virtue of\h
insight we consider our in our feelings\h\h
and actions involving others that everyone we\h
encounter is entirely innocent of any wrongdoing\h\h
all we encounter is simply manifestations of\h
the will to power pushing and pulling against\h\h
us or attracting and repulsing us and the person\h
who does you harm is no more immoral than when\h\h
a hurricane does you harm or when a mad dog bites\h
you or when you you know when you open the cabinet\h\h
and a jar of something falls and hits you on the\h
head you don't Factor morality into those things\h\h
you might still get angry you might be physically\h
harmed or even emotionally uh you know aggrieved\h\h
by it but when all is said and done The Virtuous\h
person maintains the degree of equanimity with the\h\h
knowledge that all that's happened is absolutely\h
necessary it would happen the same way every time
that's I mean to put it in another way it's a\h
means of maintaining a sort of mental or emotional\h\h
cleanliness because the most dangerous thing for\h
the spirit the most corrupting influence possible\h\h
is the influence of resentment that's the feeling\h
one gets when one wishes to take revenge to pay\h\h
back harm that one that one has experienced right\h
but you cannot do so right that's when resentment\h\h
arises is when you want to respond or pay\h
someone kind but you don't have the power\h\h
this is driven by Will To Power as much as\h
anything else but this is a negative feedback\h\h
loop type of pattern because this feeling it\h
turns one's will in a counterproductive Direction\h\h
it's corrosive to the soul the individual suffers\h
greatly from it and resentment's not aimed at\h\h
creating anything or at bringing anything forth\h
It's solely aimed at destroying it's externally\h\h
directed and it's negative in its orientation and\h
so a life lived in service to resentment is very\h\h
useful in providing one of many counter examples\h
for us to what the good life might be and or a\h\h
counter example of how to facilitate the good life\h
the good life is the opposite of a resentful life\h\h
now just to clear or a caveat when we're\h
talking about Justice there's another kind\h\h
of Justice which Nietzsche argues in human\h
all to human originated amongst the noble\h\h
classes of society the warrior aristocracies\h
of old would strike agreements with one another\h\h
based on the perception of relatively equal\h
strength between two parties that's how they\h\h
establish the concept of Rights of certain\h
respect or certain things do to all parties\h\h
the basis of justice and such a perspective it's\h
the real it's based on the reality that if there\h\h
were a conflict between the party's Mutual injury\h
or death might occur and so all parties must be\h\h
treated fairly their rights must be respected\h
but it's out of that fundamental Power Balance\h\h
furthermore if one amongst these parties is\h
slighted one does actually possess the ability\h\h
to repay the slight and if one is given a gift one\h
incurs an obligation to repay that gift because\h\h
um you know would be expected that you also would\h
have that ability it's the whole gift-giving\h\h
culture among the nobility that we see uh across\h
the world particularly in China for example\h\h
the same happens if for example somebody of this\h
type of noble mindset is shown Mercy out of Good\h\h
Will Mutual Goodwill they ought to return the\h
favor with leniency in the future right this\h\h
is the Justice of the warrior Aristocrats of\h
antiquity balancing the scales between multiple\h\h
parties who respect one another's rights out of a\h
mutual respect for each other's power and so when\h\h
that when we contrast Justice and the way Plato's\h
talking about it uh against Nietzsche's virtues
Justice is not a niche in virtue because\h
what justice has come to mean has become\h\h
so foreign from that original concept\h
of justice that what it now signifies\h\h
is almost entirely synonymous with the\h
Revenge seeking of a grieved people
um in fact Justice as a virtue to Nietzsche\h
if he were to include that it would resemble\h\h
something more like the willingness to back\h
up your words with your deeds and the power\h\h
to rebalance the scales when they're unbalanced\h
um fairness in a mutual agreement among equals\h\h
and thus we see a healthy Justice portrayed as the\h
product of an aristocracy and an unhealthy Justice\h\h
portrayed as the product of the weak and that\h
this is a key to decoding many of the puzzles of\h\h
nietzscheon virtue ethics we might call it that\h
that it's not power that corrupts but weakness\h\h
that it's the weak person lacking in\h
power who will use any means to get it\h\h
who will become resentful and destructive one\h
therefore should distrust the weak and should\h\h
also avoid allowing oneself to become weak at all\h
costs if for no other reason that a weak person's\h\h
fate is to be corrupted by resentment as they\h
constantly find themselves imposed upon but the\h\h
power of others but unable to assert themselves\h
or to retaliate or to make their power felt
accepting the essential inequality of Life\h
the Injustice of life which is all implied\h\h
by what we've been talking about accepting all\h
of these uncomfortable realities is perhaps what\h\h
we might call another virtue of Nietzsche is\h
that he didn't explicitly list perhaps what we\h\h
could call hardness it's in one of zarathustra's\h
Parables that we get the simple Maxim become hard
um and this means become tough and it does mean\h
physically but also psychologically intellectually\h\h
um I mean that this would include the ability\h
to entertain painful dangerous or uncomfortable\h\h
ideas and perhaps the most uncomfortable for\h
us now uh looking at all this would be the\h\h
inevitable difference between human beings and\h
the implications of ascending and descending\h\h
life for society the implications of the nature\h
of life as contained in commanding and obeying\h\h
um that all human life has involved what\h
we would call according to our moral system\h\h
today immorality and exploitation and that\h
if you're prospering and flourishing today\h\h
your success is built on the\h
same kind of exploitation\h\h
the kind of toughness we're talking about involves\h
cutting off those false Paths of mentation\h\h
which allow you to deal with that brute reality\h
in a dishonest way such as by imposing moral guilt\h\h
upon yourself or upon all Society or by becoming\h
resentful or by entertaining utopian ideals that\h\h
violate Human Nature these are no longer open to\h
us and this conception of Nietzsche and virtue\h\h
for obvious reasons affirming life in this way\h
is not possible for everyone as we've said and so\h\h
Nietzsche's ultimate challenge is accepting life\h
to the point of asking for the same life to recur\h\h
eternally that said in Nietzsche's unpublished\h
notes to be a challenge that will enliven the\h\h
strong but break and paralyze the world weary it's\h
not a universal life philosophy and the good life\h\h
can't be reached by everyone although All Things\h
Considered it's not a particularly shocking Claim\h\h
about the good life now is it I mean going all the\h
way back to the Greek philosophers who gave us the\h\h
concept there's always been the fair warning\h
that virtue is not the province of all people\h\h
quite the opposite in fact I mean in some deep\h
way if virtue was possessed by all people it\h\h
would cease to become virtue a virtue is\h
at bottom equality it's a power and aspect\h\h
an ability that someone or something has and\h
like all things it's physiological in the most\h\h
fundamental sense and therefore not everyone can\h
possess the same ones and human beings differ so\h\h
much and their inclinations and even within the\h
range of possibilities that you might possess\h\h
there's no guarantee for Nietzsche that any course\h
of action or set of intentions will bring you to\h\h
the good life it's just not the property of the\h
common person but in his affirmative philosophy\h\h
we see how he even affirms the the act of\h
aspiring to it right of of playing the dice\h\h
game for death and taking the risk for it even in\h
full knowledge that you probably won't attain it\h\h
that and in this way he brings his meta answer\h
to the question in line with his own aesthetic\h\h
um attempt to justify life that he's always sort\h
of that perspective he's always been coming from\h\h
of see the Beauty and the tragedy right and\h
so it's a self-overcoming starts with that\h\h
feeling he talks about his orthostra of a great\h
contempt great dissatisfaction with oneself\h\h
and the willingness to endure\h
real dangers and real suffering\h\h
um because that's what's needed to get out of\h
wretched self-complacency and just like the dancer\h\h
on the tightrope this in itself is laudable\h
for Nietzsche even if you fall off the Rope
and so let's talk about falling off the Rope the\h
final question I raised uh the final aspect we\h\h
broke the question of the meaning of life into\h
was the question of how we confront death and\h\h
Nietzsche gives us a pretty straightforward answer\h
and Beyond Good and Evil 96 quote one should\h\h
part from life as Odysseus parted from nausicaa\h
blessing it rather than in love with it end quote
now some have suggested that Odysseus may actually\h
have been in love with nausicaa even if this was\h\h
unrequited love I mean nasik is a beautiful\h
young woman Odysseus meets on his travels while\h\h
Shipwrecked and she's so beautiful that Odysseus\h
compares her to a goddess and uh you know the the\h\h
two of them seem to have feelings for one another\h
but when the time comes from Odysseus did apart\h\h
he leaves her out of necessity right and so that's\h
what Nietzsche is talking about I mean he presents\h\h
his ideal attitude is of celebrating and\h
being grateful being grateful for having been\h\h
graced without encounter by Beauty right but\h
not becoming despondent and melancholic by\h\h
having depart from this experience but doing so\h
uh voluntarily um and with uh you know ease and\h\h
so this expresses an attitude that is totally\h
commensurate with people who in some ways their\h\h
attitude is an antipode of Nietzsche but we\h
might consider the taoism of laoza or zhuanza\h\h
the image of the figure who loves\h
life but does not cling to life\h\h
because true love of Life involves a knowledge of\h
life's transformative and impermanent nature and\h\h
so the sage in his wisdom in taoism doesn't cling\h
to any particular forms or manifestations of life\h\h
Nietzsche puts this in perhaps a stronger way\h
in which he brings out a dichotomy between two\h\h
ways that we could think about death one way or\h
really ways we could think about mortality right\h\h
so one way in which death is viewed in an\h
unhealthy Manner and then he talks about\h\h
another way in which we regard death in a healthy\h
or life ascending manner quotes the certain\h\h
Prospect of death could sweeten every life with a\h
precious and fragrant drop of levity and now you\h\h
strange Apothecary Souls have turned it into an\h
ill-tasting Drop of Poison that makes the whole\h\h
of Life repulsive quote so the inevitability\h
of death that we perceive in our mortality\h\h
could either hang over our heads at all hours\h
like the Sword of Damocles letting this thought\h\h
intrude on us at all times and therefore look\h
ruin all the happiness and joy and fulfillment\h\h
we might be able to have or we may why can't we\h
see it in more light-hearted terms as a natural\h\h
um something which we take in good humor which\h
allows us to keep our life in perspective and\h\h
all the events of life and perspective um to see\h
The Comedy of the misplaced importance we have\h\h
like the trivia Trivium of our lives right um\h
you could see death as the into the play that\h\h
reveals our life's meaning to us that might\h
be like another way we could look at it right\h\h
um the Insight that a Perpetual existence would\h
actually be rather torturous that could be another\h\h
um like way we could look at it but some limit\h
to life some framing some finitude creates the\h\h
horizons within which we can actually have\h
a distinct different individual existence\h\h
and that it's like through\h
these limitations that we have\h\h
a narrative making our subjective experience\h
possible this is all found with infinitude\h\h
and um I mean however we want to look at it\h
once we accept that life really needs to have\h\h
some finitude at that point is life long is life\h
short I mean who can say and I stay in some time\h\h
life can't last forever in order for it to be\h
life so let's let the inevitable end serve as that\h\h
motivation to sweeten every moment let\h
it be a drop of Honey on everything right\h\h
there was a sorry to go Eastern again but I just\h
thought of this there's a zen master who wrote a\h\h
poem I'll give sort of the uh the paraphrasing\h
translation from Zen flesh's and Bones it's\h\h
like uh quote this day will never come again\h
each moment is like a precious gem end quote\h\h
the attitude given in this poem it the kind\h
of attitude that colors our whole life and the\h\h
whole of our experience when we reflect on the\h
finitude of life with this nietzschean Outlook\h\h
and he's simply saying um you know maybe this\h
is one way in which we should call to mind the\h\h
contingency of all interpretations and just\h
consider that the dreary and pessimistic view\h\h
of uh life and its finitude is not by any means\h
the obvious default perspective and that we have\h\h
examples of people like Odysseus or the Taoist\h
sages as I just brought up who people who are\h\h
able to bless life without um without clinging\h
to it right and that perhaps the and for someone\h\h
like myself the knowledge of death and the\h
finitude of life is a very motivating thing
we're going to look at a final Nietzsche quote\h
today and it provides the best that I think most\h\h
Innovative response to the troubling awareness of\h
our own mortality and that is don't think about it\h\h
that's funny because you know the philosophical\h
types we always think we have to have some sort\h\h
of answer to everything right a philosophical\h
position on every issue and mortality\h\h
you know our own death it's one of those things\h
that the intellect can't answer you can't think\h\h
your way out of death comes to everyone and no\h
one knows what happens and even if we accept\h\h
the materialist account that Consciousness\h
simply ends we can't conceive of not being\h\h
beyond our experience no matter what it is\h
and it must remain beyond our experience\h\h
and we so we just cannot comprehend it and\h
it's coming to everyone and so naturally\h\h
become very fixated on this and disturbed by it\h\h
and like come to believe that before you face\h
that moment the moment of death the dissolution\h\h
of Consciousness or passing on to the other world\h
or whatever you might think happens that they have\h\h
to you know quote unquote figure it all out first\h
right we have to do something before we meet death\h\h
to be ready for it that will make a difference\h
whether we've made our peace with it or not\h\h
but in reality I think we all know deep down\h
that it doesn't really matter what level of\h\h
an intellectual progress we've made in\h
grappling with or understanding death\h\h
um because you you're not going to get there\h
um you're not going to understand it because\h\h
it's beyond you and it's going to come\h
when it comes and there's no guarantee\h\h
you'll get your time to work it all out\h
before it does I mean we don't have the\h\h
the privilege of Jorge Luis Borges his character\h
in the story the uh the the secret Miracle he's a\h\h
uh playwright who's about to be shot and\h
he begs God for the time to finish his\h\h
play and time freezes and the playwright's\h
able to mentally think out everything and\h\h
um you know like he finishes his whole play\h
he finishes all his great his magnum opus in\h\h
the moment before the bullet hits his brain a\h
moment that lasts he allows it to last for like\h\h
like hundreds of years if I recall correctly\h
so um you know unless you find yourself in the\h\h
Twilight Zone or in a magical realist short\h
story that isn't usually how it all works\h\h
so this is one of my favorite um Nietzsche\h
passages he argues against our philosophical\h\h
inclinations and as elitists as Nietzsche can be\h
and we've discussed a lot of that in this episode\h\h
he has his moments where he can take a step\h
back to admire or pay his respect to the\h\h
average person and in this aphorism Nietzsche\h
for my read of it seems to be people watching\h\h
I get that impression that that's what he's\h
doing when he had the idea for the aphorism\h\h
and this is from the gay science\h
book for Section 278 quote
the thought of death living in the midst\h
of this jumble of little Lanes needs and\h\h
voices gives me a Melancholy happiness\h
how much enjoyment impatience and desire\h\h
how much thirsty life and drunkenness\h
of Life comes to light every moment\h\h
and yet silence will soon descend on all\h
these noisy living life-thirsty people\h\h
how his shadow stands even now behind\h
everyone as his dark fellow Traveler\h\h
it is always like the last moment before\h
the departure of an immigrant ship\h\h
people have more to say to each other than ever\h
the hour is late and the ocean and its desolate\h\h
silence are waiting impatiently behind all of\h
this noise so Covetous and certain of their prey\h\h
and all and every one of them suppose that\h
heretofore was little or nothing while the\h\h
near future is everything and that is the\h
reason for all of this haste this clamor\h\h
this outshouting and overreaching each other\h
everyone wants to be the first in this future\h\h
and yet death and deathly silence alone are\h
certain and common to all in this future\h\h
how strange it is that this sole certainty\h
and common element makes almost no impression\h\h
on people and that nothing is further from\h
their minds than the feeling that they form\h\h
a Brotherhood of death it makes me happy that men\h
do not want at all to think the thought of death\h\h
I should like very much to do something\h
that would make the thought of life\h\h
even a hundred times more appealing to them\h
quote so as a final word my personal advice\h\h
to agree with Nietzsche is don't spoil\h
your high moments thinking about the end\h\h
this ties in into Nietzsche's critique of\h
pity which we've only briefly touched on\h\h
here but about how fixating on cruelty happening\h
elsewhere suffering happening to other people\h\h
it only serves to infect us with that suffering\h
we've been enculturated to think that what goes\h\h
up must come down to always keep in mind\h
that we'll be laid low and into dust one day\h\h
and because of this it that feeds right\h
into the feeling that we feel we still have\h\h
to worry about having the correct thing\h
in our hearts by the time we Face death\h\h
and the extent to which we have that feeling still\h
is the extent to which we are still Christian\h\h
the thought of death is a heavy weighty thought\h
it might be important to pick up that weight\h\h
and lift it from time to time especially for the\h
hyperboreans out there but we can't let it become\h\h
a heavyweight a burden right and so to the extent\h
that the common man is relatively speaking freed\h\h
from the heavy existential concerns that plague\h
philosophers Nietzsche says he's better off for it\h\h
and we should never forget that our concern with\h
such things as a handicap something deleterious to\h\h
life the meaning of life is not found by saddling\h
ourselves with burdens or by making things Grave\h\h
and serious the thought of death is useful so\h
long as it can enrich our lives sweeten Our Lives\h\h
make us appreciate that our moments are precious\h
gems but while we are living those moments the\h\h
point is to become absorbed and engaged in\h
the here and now to live in such a way that\h\h
you fall in love with life and ideally a\h
kind of mature love like that of laozza or\h\h
Odysseus or better yet that you live with such\h
Vigor and Zeal that you leave behind a stamp\h\h
upon the world like Gerta or Napoleon to live with\h
the kind of creative innocent sincerity described\h\h
by Nietzsche and the most cheerful and most\h
elevated moments in his work to live in such a\h\h
way that when you come to the end of your life you\h
know that you would gladly do it all over again\h\h
the attitude that we should have when facing death\h
is as Nietzsche describes quoting from the Greeks\h\h
someone who says was that life well then once more
if you enjoyed the Nietzsche podcast or found it\h
helpful you can visit us and support the show at\h\h
patreon.com untimely Reflections the link is in\h
the description or just share the show with any\h\h
of your friends that you think might enjoy it\h
or on social media thank you for your support
foreign