What are we doing here and where are we going
to go
It's like we just woke up one morning and
then it's welcome to the show
Don't ask any questions just go with the flow
Make as much money as you can and try your
best not to get broke
Copy everything you see on the tv
From the hairstyles to the clothes
And don't think too often just do exactly
as your told
You ever get confused then turn towards the
alcohol
You still hear your thoughts?
then just turn up the radio
As you learn to live a lifestyle of drugs,
sex and rock n roll
But in all honesty I just need to know
Is there more to the cycle than growing and
getting old
Living and dying just to leave behind a happy
home
And a whole lot of property that somebody
else is going to own
I just really need to know before the caskets
closed
Cause I'm not willing to gamble with my soul
nor am I ready to take any chances
These are just simple life questions and I'm
just searching for some answers
Like what are we doing here and what is our
purpose
How did we get here and who made us so perfect
And what happens once we go or is this world
all really worth it
Questions we don't answer because apparently
we don't really have to
There's no purpose to this life and our existence
merely natural?
In that case please let me ask you.
Did you create yourself or was it somebody
else that had fashioned you?
Because you're a being that's impeccable faultless
and unparalleled.
You are a product of supreme intelligence
and I'm merely being rational
For there isn't a camera on this earth that
can come close to the human eye
Nor a computer that can compete alongside
the human mind
And If the whole world was to come together
we wouldn't be able to create a single fly
So many signs yet we still deny
As science tries to justify that all this
could come from none
When It's a simple sum
Zero plus zero plus zero cannot possibly ever
give you one.
So from where did all this order come?
For everything has it's origins, a maker,
a creator of it's own
I mean the only reason your watching this
video is because somebody had to press upload
So you can believe in the Big Bang but I'd
rather Believe in He who caused it to explode.
Allah, The creator of the universe along with
every single soul
The Everliving, the Master the only one who
is in control
Unlike his creation, beyond our imagination
And NO -
He's not a man nor has he any partners in
association, He's on his own.
And neither did He ever leave us alone
Just like every manufacturer he left us with
an instruction manual
The Quran and Islam and I'm sorry to jump
to conclusions but it's the only one possible.
The only definition of God as the One and
Only, supreme being its logical,
A book with zero contradictions and miracles
that are both scientific and historical.
All revealed over 1400 years ago
Like the detailed description of the human
embryo
The expansion of the Universe and the creation
of everything from H20
To the mountains as pegs holding firm the
earth below
and the two seas that don't mix in a complete
separate flow
to the planets in orbit alternating night
and day as they stay in float
to the stories of the past and the preservation
of Pharaoh.
To identifying the lowest point in the land
where Persia defeated Rome
The gushing fluid that created man in the
glands between the ribs and the backbone.
And not a word has changed it's still the
same
So please explain how all this was known over
1400 years ago?
To a man who couldn't read or write, as he
would recite what the angel spoke.
And if you still don't believe please come
up with something that's even close.
But you can't.
So we took God as a mockery and his Messengers
as a joke
Dismissed his scriptures as legends and tales
of the ancient folk.
As we live life according to our whims, desires
and hopes
Saying this life is the only home we will
ever know
We will live then die and simply turn to bones
YOLO.
Correction: After the grass dies the rain
arrives it re-grows
And Allah promises to do the same thing to
your very soul
And bring you back from your very fingertips
to your toes.
As the All Seeing Supreme Being watches us
so close as we are surely being tested.
In Our wealth, our health, our self and everything
that we've been blessed with
So believe for we will surely be resurrected.
And be brought to Lord in account for every
single deed
As he hands us our books and orders us to
"READ!"
From the bad to the good and everything in
between
You, yourself are sufficient for your own
accountability
So Don't be mad at me, Your Lord says...
YOU WERE THE ONE WHO THOUGHT HE WOULDN'T COME
BACK TO ME
I gave you a whole life long to search after
me
But you were busy chasing all that which was
temporary
So read, and glad tidings to all those who
believed,
but if you disbelieve
READ
And don't let that day be the first day you
find out what life really means.
READ