every day over 150,000 people die that's
over 6,000 people every hour over a 100
people every minute and about two people
every single second that means since you
started watching this video about 20
people have already died and some of
these people got hit by cars others fell
off a cliff others may have had a heart
attack and others may have simply passed
away from natural causes death is one of
those things that every single living
thing on Earth has in common and death
does not discriminate against your skin
color or your political beliefs or where
you were born or how much money you have
no one can escape the incurable disease
that we all are blessed with from birth
called life and it's interesting because
even though we all logically know this
very few of us have really internalized
this how many of you have really sat
down with your eyes closed in an empty
room and truly imagined what your
funeral would look like like who would
even be at your funeral who would be
there out of pure obligation and
politeness and who would be there
because they actually wanted to be there
what would people say about you what
would they remember and it's weird
because you think because we all have
this terminal disease called life that
we all would be more sympathetic and
loving with one another I mean this life
disease really is the one thing that all
human beings have in common because in
120 years from now every single human
being on Earth will be dead and a brand
new set of humans will be alive and then
in another 120 years after that another
brand new set of people will be alive
and this is the cycle of life it just
goes on and on and on and when you start
thinking about life like this you really
start to realize how short our time here
on Earth really is and you also start to
realize that we all are on this journey
together as one and it also makes you
question the way most people interact
with one another like why do so many
people get so angry with each other or
why do people argue with each other why
do people physically harm one another
why are there so many parents who yell
at their kids or even beat their kids
why do so many spouses who supposedly
love each other fight all the time why
are there siblings who don't speak to
each other to this day over some
disagreement that took place years ago
why do best friends talk badly about
each other behind each other's back why
do human beings behave like this I think
a part of it is because we really have
not sat down to really think about what
the true meaning of life is and I also
think that most people really have not
come to terms with the fact that they
are not going to be here forever and to
be honest I don't really claim to know
what the true meaning of life is okay I
think it's something that our human
brain can't fully logically understand
it would kind of be like trying to
explain Consciousness to a dog or a cat
or something they they just can't
understand it however what I will say is
there are some things that I think
everyone should know and I think the
first step to actually understanding a
topic like the meaning of life is to
First align ourselves with the four
truths of the universe and the first
truth is the truth of cause and effect
which means that every single thing you
do or say has some kind of effect on the
world around you and yourself for
example let's say a number of years ago
you lost your temper and you got really
mad at a loved one in your life this
could be a family member or a friend or
even that random person on the street
that one single incident where you lost
it will have a lingering effect on that
person to this day now with that being
said it doesn't have to be some huge
effect it could be a very mild and small
effect and it could be buried deep
within their subconscious that isn't
necessarily visible on the exterior but
make no mistake the effect is there and
it will always be there and there is
nothing that you can do to undo that and
the reason why most people hate hearing
this is because it instantly makes them
accountable for every single thing that
they have ever done and being held
accountable is something that most human
beings hate now to be clear I'm not
saying that we should all dwell in the
past and feel sory for ourselves but
what it does mean is that going forward
you should be very conscious of the
things that you say and the things that
you do within this world and if you feel
like you behaved in a way or you really
lost it on someone you can always
apologize to that person because it is
never ever too late to say I'm sorry and
the second truth Tru of the universe is
the law of impermanence which means that
every single thing here on Earth is
temporary like our bodies Our Minds our
relationships even our brains even the
video that you are watching right now
this video will probably be gone one day
because the sun could explode and every
single thing could be gone within a
second and funny enough this is actually
a good thing and it shouldn't really
make you feel bad or sad because it's
none of those things what it should make
you do is really cherish each and every
single moment that you have here on
Earth and to be clear they don't have to
be these big special moments they can be
any moment like that one time where you
laugh so hard that tears fell from your
eyes or maybe it was that time where you
simply were sitting alone and you were
just gazing at the sunset because all we
really have in this lifetime is the
present moment and the third truth is
the law of suffering and attachment
anytime that we become attached to
something or someone you are basically
making a contract with yourself to be
unhappy because like we just discussed
nothing here on Earth is permanent which
means that you will eventually lose that
loved one or you will eventually lose
that watch or that car or that family
member even your own body you are going
to lose and the fourth truth is that we
all are going to die one day and the
death truth is typically the toughest
one for most people to accept because it
often makes people really sad but death
does not have to be this horribly bad
thing or even a sad thing because
without death the moments with our
friends or our family would not really
be that special or deep without death
everything would eventually become dull
and meek and gray and there would be no
incentive to really love and cherish the
moment moments that we have with one
another there would be no incentive to
really laugh deeply or love deeply or
even to be present and these are the
things that truly make life rich and
worth living and on top of that death is
one of those things that truly does
connect all of us because it makes you
realize that you and the Seven other
billion people here on Earth really are
all on the same team because this is our
time this is our time to collectively
live live life to the fullest as one so
the next time that you feel the need to
yell at that loved one or to yell at
that person who cut you off in traffic
or to get revenge on that person who
wronged you in the past just remember
that you are choosing to actively hurt
your very own teammate make every moment
count love deeply laugh deeply and be
present to the moment because at the end
of the day all we really have in life is
the Pres present moment so don't let it
go to waste if you want to learn more
about life and motivation then go ahead
and click the video on the screen right
now I promise that you will love it
thanks for watching and I'll see you all
very soon