so one of the biggest questions people
seem to have these days is what is the
meaning of life I feel like we are going
through a time period where there is a
crisis of meaning so many people seem
like they're alive they're existing
they're living for all intents and
purposes but their life really has no
meaning and I think one of the reasons
so many of us are devoid of meaning in
life
is because we're chasing after things
that don't mean anything to us one of my
favorite saying when it comes to life is
one of my favorite timism is that if it
doesn't mean anything it doesn't mean
anything and by that I mean so many of
us are spending our lives chasing after
things material possessions uh titles
careers whatever it is mates whatever it
is so many of us are spinning Our Lives
chasing after things things that Society
told us we need to chase after Society
the world around us said if you get this
if you achieve this level of wealth if
you achieve this lifestyle if you
achieve this title if you get with this
type of person then you'll be happy then
your life will have meaning the problem
with that is each one of us are
different each one of us are unique you
know we all have different DNA we all
have different backgrounds we all were
raised in different environments we all
have different things we like in Joy
love desire we're all different and what
the world around us what Society has
tried to do the Matrix if you will is to
make us all one person to narrow us down
to like worker robots you know and it's
like if you do this you'll be happy
anything else is crazy and if you're
brought up just like subconsciously
getting this message your whole life
what are you going to do you're going to
go after the path that everything around
you has told told you would make you
happy but then when you don't get there
when you excuse me when you do get there
if you get there cuz the the world also
makes it very hard to get there but if
you get there you look around and you're
like okay now what if if you get there
and it's not something you genuinely
want then you look around and you're
like now what and that's when you start
thinking like what's the meaning of life
I did everything they told me to do I
achieved the stuff that like they told
me to to to strive for to achieve I got
it I'm here and it doesn't mean anything
and that's because you can't make
something that has no meaning for you
have meaning for you people try oh
people try you know what people
typically do if they do achieve the
things that they think they should
achieve what they do when it doesn't
bring them happiness is they double down
on it well let me make more money let me
climb higher up the ladder let me
indulge even more in whatever this
lifestyle I'm indulging in they Double
Down On It if maybe I didn't do it good
enough maybe I need more but then when
they get more if they get more a lot of
times you know they burn out trying to
get more it's the same game it's the
same game that's why you see people who
outwardly we think should be very happy
people who have all these
accomplishments and achievements and
titles and they seem like they have all
the toys and all the bells and the
whistles and the nicest house and the
nicest car and the Beautiful You know
the handsome husband and the Beautiful
Wife the people who seem like they're
doing everything have it all and a lot
of them were kind of like me a lot of
them are depressed um a lot of them you
know are just kind of meh with life a
lot of them if you ask them some of
these people who seem like they have at
all like what's some of the most
memorable times in your life a lot of
them will think back or recall a Time 20
years ago where they were like oh yeah I
was backpacking in Europe with my
friends it was amazing I think about
that summer all the time you know what I
mean because that's something that means
something to them so what we have to do
is take the time to figure out what
makes us happy what means something to
us and the problem is like most people
don't do that we just follow the
programming this is what everybody else
is doing they look happy on
Instagram so so I'mma do it too but if
you do that like hey I'll I'll even say
this go for it try it try it you might
be one of the people that it works for
there is a small percentage of the
population that the status quo is what
they would have done anyway it brings
them happiness for a lot of us though it
doesn't so if you go after it and it
doesn't bring you
meaning my advice to you my plea to you
is think about what might think about
hey when was the last time I I wasn't
asking what the meaning of life is I
always say a genuinely happy people
don't ask about the meaning of life they
don't ask ask about the purpose of life
they're just living think about when
you're spending time with your friends
or your family or doing one of your
favorite hobbies or even if you have
work that you love you know at work when
you get in that flow State and you're
just really doing it you know think
about the last time you was really doing
something you enjoyed you weren't
sitting around asking what the meaning
was that is the meaning that's it right
there the meaning of life is to like do
things that make you feel
alive the meaning of life is doing
things that make you feel alive make you
appreciate this thing called life so if
that's not happening I think we have to
look back like when was the last time I
felt
alive when was the last time I really
just was in the zone in the flow was
enjoying myself and what were some of
the things I was doing who were some of
the people I was around it's very
important you know a lot of this stuff
that our you know our our grandparents
or great grandparents really appreciate
it family friends everybody sitting down
eating dinner together together taking
vacations taking train you know all this
stuff that we think is like old school
now you know for us it's all about
getting to the bag getting to the money
times have changed yeah but we as humans
haven't changed times have changed we as
humans haven't changed the things that
bring us joy are the things that have
always brought us joy throughout
Humanity it don't matter how much new
technology we come up with the things
that bring us joy are the things that
bring us joy and the good news is the
good news is because a lot of this new
technology is expensive you know they
keep coming up with new technologies
which is basically new ways to get your
money but the good news is the things
that bring us joy and happiness a lot of
it is pretty cheap a lot of it isn't
that expensive so that's the good news
that's the good news a lot of times
we're like man I you know this life I'm
living now and cutting it but I don't
know if I could do what I really want to
do um you know it might be expensive it
might not be it might not be but I think
we have to take the time to sit sit down
and really ask ourselves when was the
last time I felt
alive who was around me what was I doing
and how can I find a way to do that as
much as
possible a lot of the stuff that we're
told we got to achieve success which
success is different for everybody but
like success and and and all this money
you know like if you're the type of
person that likes stacking your money
you like making Investments you like
making your money move around cool but
there are a lot of people who honestly
could care less about
money there are a lot of people like I
just need enough money to pay my bills
if they were honest with themselves they
would realize I just need enough money
pay my bills be comfortable I'm trying
to do some other stuff and what we I
think what we need to do is figure out
what that other stuff is and do that as
much as
possible life's pretty simple life's
pretty simple figure out what you like
to do in life do that as much as
possible if you got to do some other
stuff to finance that or to make sure
you have time to do that cool but once
you identify the things you like to do
the things that bring you Joy bring you
happiness do
that it might be helping others
ironically one of the things that brings
us the most joy in life is helping other
people find joy in Life or helping other
people have the basics and the Comforts
they need in
life once again free for the most part
you know sometimes you can give money
things like that but just like helping
people being there for people is free
and it brings us some of the the most
joy in life while we're out here trying
to acquire all these possessions for
ourselves we could be 10 times 100 times
happier if we were out there trying to
help other people giving away some of
that stuff to other people it's crazy
how it works you know like the answers
are right there in front of us I think
we all know deep down inside the things
we like to do sometimes we think we're
an adult so we can't do some of that
stuff anymore or we could never turn
that into maybe a a side hustle or or
business if we need to find a way to
like pay the bills doing it so a lot of
times we shy away from some of this
stuff we think it's too crazy um we
don't have the self-confidence to think
we could ever do it but we know deep
down inside most of us I think we know
and if we don't there's no rule that
says we can't take the time to figure it
out you got your whole life ahead of you
if you don't know tell I got no clue
what I want to do okay well that's what
you're doing from now on is figuring out
what you want to do you know why instead
of sitting around questioning
questioning the meaning of life take
some time to Fig take that time to
figure out what you want to do try some
stuff hang out with some people try some
stuff do some anything pops in your head
I might want to do that try it you got
the rest of your life to figure out what
you want to do with the rest of your
life I'm dropping a lot of timism in
this one you got the rest of your life
to figure out what you want to do with
the rest of your life because that's all
you really have to do there's nothing
you have to
do you know you may we may have
responsibility these things we feel we
need to take care of but there's nothing
we have to
do right be there for your fellow man
and figure out what makes you happy find
a way to do it it might take a year it
might take five years but wouldn't you
rather the last 30 years of your life
you figured it out your life has meaning
because you're doing meaningful stuff
stuff that's meaningful to you or would
you rather just keep following the
status quo and for the rest of your life
just be going through the motions you
know
like what's the point what is the point
if you're just going through the motions
you're not happy there's no joy like why
are you doing it the reason we're alive
is to do things that make us feel
alive but the game is we have to figure
those things out and we have to take
action to bring those things into our
life it's already here for us I promise
you on this vast planet called Earth
there are the people and the things and
the experiences and the activities
whatever it is that will bring meaning
to your life that will bring you
happiness that will bring joy I promise
you was here and if it's not we starting
to go off in space too so you know if
it's on the moon hanging there about 10
more years you might be able to go get
it but it's probably here we just have
to figure out what it is and figure out
how to bring it into our life and keep
it in our life and focus on that because
if we don't we're going to spend the
rest of our life wondering why all this
stuff
doesn't mean anything I'll talk to you
later