life is hard I bought a new pair of
shoes the other day walked outside into
the rain and ended up stepping into some
mud now they're ruined and I'm bitter
but then I took a step back not
literally of course but I really thought
about it and I came to the conclusion
that nothing in life really matters
here's why the earth has been around for
four-and-a-half billion years
one day humans became a thing and we
became conscious this world seemed
perfect for us it wasn't scorching hot
it wasn't deathly cold we fit right in
the middle the gravity on earth was
perfect it allowed us to move and run
and catch animals that conveniently
existed for us humans to eat there was
water to drink there was oxygen to
breathe it's as if we were put here for
a reason we began creating things we
begin working together as a species
building empires covering the planet and
fighting each other for whatever reason
fast-forward a couple million years and
here we are today computers rockets Elon
Musk they are all here somewhere along
the line we also in a way created
something out of nothing it's called
time we've laid out definitions of time
seconds minutes hours years but it
doesn't really matter we've made those
for our own use time is nothing more
than a way to measure the passing of
events but we've only really set up
these units of time based off of
ourselves a day is how long it takes the
earth to spin around once a month is
about how long it takes the moon to
orbit the Earth and also spin around
once a year is how long it takes the
earth to orbit the Sun once you get
about 78 earth revolutions around the
Sun in this journey called life as
poetic as that sounds there's not much
scale to these things once we pass a
human lifetime sure we can judge how
long a thousand or maybe even ten
thousand years are but after that the
timescales of things are just too much
for our brains to handle as much as you
think you understand the 13.8 billion
year life span of the universe you
really can't put that into an imaginable
scale on the scale of a human life the
universe is unbelievably old
but in terms of the universe's lifespan
pretty much nothing has happened yet
it's barely even started we can make
predictions about the next hundreds of
trillions of years of the universe's
life we can figure out how when when our
Sun is going to blow up we can figure
out when our galaxy is going to collide
with another we can come up with
theories that describe why the universe
we've been put into is expanding faster
than anything else physically possible
but yet we have zero idea what happened
in the fraction of a second between when
there was nothing and when there was
something for some reason as far as we
can tell
we're the only conscious beings to have
ever existed but we don't even know what
being conscious is we developed
consciousness only to be aware of the
fact that nothing else is their growth
so aware of our surroundings that the
smarter we get the smaller we become as
this thing we call time goes on we begin
to realize things things that prove that
the universe probably wasn't made just
for us you are most likely born in a
hospital if not props to you for making
it this far
back then you were your parents entire
world for a small time which is cute but
you aren't everything 360 thousand
people are born each day of all of those
people with the same birthday some are
going to do big things and change the
world others are just gonna die that
just happens but earth is just one
planet in our solar system there's eight
or nine of those for now for life as we
know it to exist it's kind of hard to
believe that there might be other life
out there it takes so much to happen for
us to be able to exist we've discovered
over 4000 exoplanets to date planets
that don't revolve around our Sun and we
found multiple examples of earth-like
planets roughly the same shape size
temperature but yet there's nothing
there from what we can tell so if there
are so many planets that could have life
why haven't we seen it yet why are there
no signs
well we're just one solar system in an
entire galaxy there's over 200 billion
stars in our galaxy alone but that's
just one galaxy we're a part of the
local group which is a collection of 30
galaxies near our own Andromeda is one
of them that's the one that's gonna
collide with our galaxy in about
four-and-a-half billion years
by then you'll be long gone and soon
after that so will the earth the Sun at
this point will be reaching the end of
its life it's going to expand in size
and by the end it will completely
consume the earth shining over 3,000
times brighter than it does today but
even though our home planet will be gone
the rest of the galaxy wouldn't even
notice billions of years on a multi
trillion year time scale is truly
nothing but even so there are some
things that we're observing in the
universe's infancy today that will
drastically influence the far future to
keep it short the universe is expanding
this is nothing new
a lot of people know this but what many
people don't know is that this expansion
is speeding up now we don't know why but
we have an idea of what's causing it
dark energy I made an entire video about
this so go watch that after this dark
energy is stretching the fabric of
space-time we don't know what it's made
from we know it's there we observe its
results but we don't know exactly what
it is or what it's going to do dark
energy at least according to our current
calculations will eventually stretch the
space-time between galaxies faster than
the speed of light the light emitting
from our neighboring galaxies will
travel towards us at the fastest speed
possible but even this won't be enough
the light will never reach us because
the space between it is stretching
faster than the light that is traveling
through it it will spread the universe
so thin with galaxies that when we look
out to observe what's around us we won't
see anything we're going to end up all
alone could find whatever galaxy we end
up in
but in the end even our galaxy will
start to go dark the fate of the Sun is
the same as it is for all stars in the
universe eventually trillions of years
down the road these lights in the sky
are going to begin turning off one by
one by one without any new stars to keep
things running the universe is going to
get a bit colder depending on their size
these dying stars begin to turn into
white dwarfs or neutron stars providing
the last glimmers of light in a cold and
dark universe this is the very last hope
for any surviving life forms in the
universe but eventually trillions of
more years after the last stars like our
Sun die even these white dwarfs will
begin to dim out some of these neutron
stars roaming throughout the universe
may collide by chance resulting in the
brightest known events in the entire
universe supernova
[Music]
but once these supernovae conclude the
universes again plunged into darkness
all matter that used to make up the
galaxies that we see today will begin to
fall into the black holes that kept
things held together for so long
the Big Bang that created the highest
temperatures ever known to physics
ultimately results in the most dormant
dark and cold configuration possible
from a universe teeming with light and
beauty to a cold barren wasteland a
universe dominated by black holes but
even now the universe has just begun
these black holes are going to be around
for a while and the things we used to
call galaxies with stars and planets and
life are now just going to be full of
black holes black holes and more black
holes this is how the universe is going
to spend most of its time cold dark and
alone we're no longer talking about
millions of years here the timescales
are now on quadrillions of years but
even these black holes won't last
forever through Hawking radiation these
black holes will slowly very slowly
begin to evaporate away one subatomic
particle at a time until eventually
after all the black holes fade out of
existence there is nothing left in the
universe a universe where nothing
changes where time becomes pointless
there's nothing
the nothingness of space though will
continue to expand because of dark
energy a force that accounts for 70% of
our universe that we don't even
completely understand yet matter as we
know it today the things that make up
everything you see only accounts for
barely 4% of the stuff in the universe
so maybe just maybe we're a fluke we
were never supposed to make it to the
end but we still have a role to play out
today we are one species on one planet
in one galaxy in an almost
indistinguishable part of the universe
whether or not we came to exist not much
would be different every day we matter a
little less and a little less until
eventually we realize that in the grand
scheme of things we don't matter at all
our galaxy could just disappear it
wouldn't really change much we came to
exist in such a weird time but it's also
pretty unique we know we're just the
beginning a blip in the universe's
potential but the only way to fulfill
that potential is to start making
progress today it's not a stretch to say
that there won't be others like us
random spurts of intelligent life spread
throughout trillions of trillions of
years but now we're at one of those
stages where life is possible and
probably the easiest is ever going to be
you get one life to do whatever you want
there are some things you can avoid like
school lower taxes but other than that
you're free to do mostly whatever you'd
like if we can't figure out our purpose
for coming to exist on this planet if we
can't figure out why or how the universe
came into being then our purpose is
whatever we want it to be if you want to
sit around and play games all day there
are people doing that if you want to
build a multi-billion dollar company
that's going to help propel humanity to
other worlds there are people doing that
as well anything you want to be or do
can be done and should be done like I
said our own purpose is whatever we want
right now if good things are happening
to you if bad things are happening to
you it's actually not gonna last forever
you have zero idea what the future holds
for you and the most random of
experiences can reroute your future in
an instant everyone was still to hand in
life that we honestly just didn't ask
for some people's hands are better than
others but we all have to play with the
cars we've been given in the best way we
can there's a chance that we humans may
never figure out why everything in the
universe acts the way it does is there
life anywhere else or are we the
exception for every answer a hundred new
questions pop up there's infinite
possibilities as to how we came to exist
but there's infinitely just as many
things to do while we're figuring that
out there's dogs to feed there's people
to meet there's science to be done so
whatever you do while we figure out our
spot in the universe this universe at
least just try to enjoy it because no
matter what happens to you no matter how
many times you mess up no matter how far
humanity ventures out into the unknown
in the end it doesn't even matter
[Music]