why am I here what's my life purpose why
should I care about anything if
everything is just going to
end these are the kinds of questions
that haunted one of the greatest writers
of all time Leo
Tolstoy despite having achieved almost
everything Fame wealth a loving family
and success Tolstoy found himself
struggling with these very
thoughts he was often considered Cormac
McCarthy of his time
as his two most famous novels War and
Peace and Anna Karenina continue to be
some of the most celebrated Works in
literature on top of that he owned a
large farm had a beautiful family and
was married to a loving wife but despite
all of this something shifted for
Tolstoy when he reached the age of
50 suddenly nihilistic thoughts hit him
hard and all of his previously found
happiness seemed to vanish a man who had
once lived life to its fullest doing
whatever made him feel good now found
himself questioning
everything why did this happen how did
he get through it in this video we'll
discuss tolstoy's personal struggle and
how he faced these deep existential
questions to an
answer from a young age Leo Tolstoy was
deeply skeptical of Christianity he lost
both of his parents early in life which
left him feeling abandoned and
disillusioned the church in particular
gave him a negative impression told
Tolstoy once said so that now as
formerly religious Doctrine accepted on
trust and supported by external pressure
gradually throws away under the
influence of knowledge and experience of
Life which conflicts with
it his early life filled with tragedy
and doubt set the stage for his later
struggles with faith for almost 50 years
Tolstoy lived a life seemingly free of
major worries he was successful rich and
surrounded by family but then something
changed he hid an intellectual crisis a
deep and overwhelming existential crisis
where sleep became his only escape the
weight of his thoughts was so intense
that he found Solus in sleep because it
provided temporary relief from the
constant barrage of questions about his
purpose and
existence in his essay a confession
Tolstoy expressed how during this time
he had to trick himself into not taking
his own life life as nihilism consumed
him as his thoughts spiraled he became
like an emotional toddler constantly
asking himself why why life why
existence why death he believed there
was something fundamentally wrong with
his
soul in anarina the character Levan
mirrors this struggle Levan much like
Tolstoy was caught in an endless loop of
why questions fixated on the meaning of
life and death Tolstoy wrote if not now
then tomorrow if not tomorrow then in 30
years does it make any
difference capturing the hopelessness
that defined his thinking at that time
these thoughts LED Tolstoy to
contemplate
suicide but instead of ending his life
he decided to embark on a different
Journey a journey in search of meaning a
search for ultimate peace he turned to
philosophy science and various
ideologies to find answers one of the
turning points in his journey was a
parable he reflected on deeply a tale he
included in a confession the parable was
about a man fleeing from a wild beast
who eventually stumbled upon an
abandoned well desperate to escape the
Beast the man jumped into the well only
to find a dragon waiting at the bottom
with its jaws wide open in his Panic he
grabbed onto a branch growing out of the
wells wall hoping to avoid falling into
the dragon's grasp amid this situation
the man noticed drops of Honey on the
leaves of the branch he was holding
despite the danger he reached out and
tasted the honey momentarily distracted
from the life-threatening predicament he
was in Tolstoy saw this Parable as a
mirror of his own life he recognized
that like the man in the well he was
caught between two extremes the wild
beast of existential dread above him and
the dragon of death waiting
below yet in the midst of this turmoil
he found moments of
sweetness moments that kept him alive
and
searching rather than give in to the
Dragon's Jaws Tolstoy chose to seek
meaning exploring almost every ideology
first he turned to philosophy and
science tolto read The Works of multiple
philosophers including Solomon Socrates
and Buddha but he did not find complete
answers in any of them he felt that
these teachings ultimately led to one
simple conclusion
happy is he who has not been born death
is better than life and one must free
oneself from
life on the other hand Tolstoy also
explored science which he believed
offered knowledge but found little
Solace there he viewed Darwinism as
embodying nihilism suggesting that
humans are nothing but an accidental
Creation in the
universe according to biology we are
merely lumps of energy valuable only
when we are healthy and destined for
death once our cells grow
old to Tolstoy science offered no
Comfort regarding life's purpose or how
one could live a happy life free from
the existential thoughts that haunted
him disillusioned with both philosophy
and science Tolstoy turned to studying
and observing the people around him
after much reflection he concluded that
for people in his Circle there were four
ways out of the terrible position in
which we are all
placed the first first way is accepting
the absurdity of life I find a lot of
commonality between Albert Kimo's
philosophy and tolstoy's perspective on
existence especially in their shared
view of
absurdism Tolstoy observed that one way
people cope with the absurdity of life
is simply By ignoring it they do nothing
about it they don't overthink it life is
absurd so what they just live
it kamu also argued that instead of
succumbing to despair or nihilism in the
face of absurdity we should ad an
attitude of defiance and resilience the
key is to keep a mindset of so what so
what if you can't find the answer just
go have a coffee with your wife and
forget about it however Tolstoy didn't
think this could be a lasting solution
how can you stay ignorant when you have
a fully functioning mind constantly
pushing you to think about your
existence the deaths of loved ones or
personal struggles can make these
thoughts even harder to ignore
eventually the weight of n ISM overtakes
and absurdism no longer works so while
he observed that some people cope this
way Tolstoy didn't believe it was a path
to Lasting
peace this led Tolstoy to observe a
second group of people who sought peace
in another way epicurian ISM Tolstoy
noticed that some people turned to a
life of indulgence filling it with
Pleasures to distract themselves from
the suffering and uncertainty of
existence they pursued material wealth
relationships and entertainment to
escape the fear of death and the
meaninglessness of
life however Tolstoy criticized this
approach for being ultimately
unsatisfying while Indulgence in
pleasure may offer temporary relief it's
fleeting and fails to address the deeper
questions of
meaning for Tolstoy living solely for
pleasure results in an endless cycle of
dissatisfaction no amount of indulgence
can resolve the ultimate existential
questions
in tolstoy's view epicurian ISM was like
the drops of honey in the parable of the
man in the well sweet for a moment but
ultimately just a distraction from the
harsh reality of
Life the third group Tolstoy observed
were those who in the face of life's
struggles lacked the strength to carry
on but have strength to end the silly
joke they were overwhelmed by the
absurdity of existence and saw no way
out this is a path that Tolstoy himself
could not Embrace he saw some people go
so far as to consider ending their lives
but he believed that this too was not
the
solution and yes please never ever do
that if you're in an existential crisis
keep moving forward don't let it consume
you instead search with an open mind as
the answers may not be immediate but
will come in time anyways this however
was also not a path that Tolstoy could
accept instead he observed a fourth way
which he described as a state of
existential limbo this is where
individuals after recognizing the
inherent meaninglessness and suffering
of Life feel trapped between two
extremes they acknowledge the futility
of existence its suffering the
inevitability of death and the absence
of inherent purpose but they lack the
strength hope or energy to act on it
Tolstoy noticed that unlike those who
actively seek pleasure find solace in
faith or even those who consider suicide
as a way to escape their suffering these
individuals do nothing at all they don't
reject life but neither do they embrace
it they are caught in a state of passive
resignation they recognize the problem
but feel too drained or defeated to
confront it this is not an active choice
to continue living rather it's a form of
numb endurance a kind of spiritual
exhaustion these individuals simply
exist unable to move forward it's not so
much about embracing life or rejecting
it but rather about existing in a
suspended State unable to act or find
any form of meaning or peace Tolstoy saw
this as the weakest form of living
because it offers no resolution no
progress the individual is fully aware
of life's absurdity and the existential
challenges but remains stuck in a
standstill unable to seek purpose or
hope this state of limbo leaves them
emotionally and spiritually paralyzed
they remained suspended in their
suffering with no movement in any
direction and no real possibility of
finding peace or meaning in their
lives after studying various theologies
and observing people Tolstoy experienced
a profound
[Music]
Revelation on a journey to find the
meaning of life he started observing
everyone his observations of the poor
however marked a significant turning
point in his understanding of life
purpose he was struck by how The
Peasants despite facing immense
hardships maintained an unwavering faith
in God this belief seemed to give them
purpose and resilience even in the face
of suffering in contrast Tolstoy caught
up in his own existential struggles
found himself disconnected from such
Faith the peasant's simple yet steadfast
belief stood as a stark contrast to his
intellectual uncertainties and inner
turmoil having achieved wealth and
intellectual success Tolstoy found
himself at a
Crossroads material possessions and
social status no longer brought him
peace or
satisfaction the pursuit of reason and
logic which once seemed to promise
answers instead led him deeper into
despair this mirrored the dark moments
of Doubt Levan experienced in anak
Karenina where the search for meaning
appeared feudal and
unresolved however tolstoy's encounter
with the faith of the poor challenged
his perspective
he began to see that life could not be
fully understood through reason alone it
required belief in something greater
than the material world this realization
marked a profound turning point for
Tolstoy although he had not initially
believed in God he began to recognize
that Faith particularly in the infinite
was the key to transcending the
limitations of the finite World The
Suffering and struggles of human life
were temporary but the Eternal presence
of God offered a sense of purpose that
could provide meaning beyond the
fleeting nature of
existence in this newfound understanding
faith became not just an intellectual
concept but a way of enduring life's
challenges and finding meaning in the
face of
suffering even if his rational mind saw
Faith as a leap without tangible
evidence Tolstoy came to understand it
as the only path to true peace and
purpose embracing this belief Tolstoy
was able to overcome his Despair and
find genuine contentment his life
underwent a transformation as he adopted
a simpler way of living focusing on the
well-being of others and committing
himself to a life of humility and
service he became convinced that without
faith true happiness was
impossible faith in his view provided
life's meaning a higher purpose that
went beyond human suffering and the
limits of human
reason as Tolstoy embraced this simple
faith he found a renewed sense of
purpose dedicating himself to helping
the poor and living in a way that
reflected his Newfound humility and
Devotion to
God in the end tolstoy's life once
dominated by intellectual struggles
found its meaning in the very Faith he
had once rejected though his version of
Faith was not entirely Orthodox
Christianity it was deeply rooted in his
belief in the infinite and his
understanding of
God this gave him the satisfaction he
had long been
seeking it was not wealth or
intellectual achievement that provided
meaning to his life but a trust in
something greater than
himself what had seemed at first like a
concession to his rational mind
ultimately proved to be the only path
that allowed him to find peace a peace
that had eluded him in his earlier
attempts to seek meaning through reason
alone he began living a more modest life
giving away much of his Health which his
family did not
appreciate after this period of struggle
and adjustment Tolstoy spent his
remaining years living honestly and
devotedly finding the peace he had been
seeking and at last he passed away on
November 20th 1910 at the age of 82
[Music]