what if the beliefs you've held close
the very things that gave you purpose
suddenly seemed like
strangers how do you hold on to meaning
when it feels like slipping through your
fingers this question tormented the
great Russian writer Leo Tolstoy leading
him to a crisis so deep that even his
wealth Fame and family couldn't pull him
out of it Tolstoy wasn't just a
Storyteller but a Seeker digging into
the most complex uncomfortable questions
about human existence
his writing's travel time inviting us to
confront our deepest fears and
doubts and perhaps his most profound
question was the one that many of us are
afraid to face what is my life's
purpose born in
1828 Tolstoy was raised in a Russian
aristocratic family steeped in privilege
and Traditional
Values he inherited vast Estates and
wealth and by his 30s he was acclaimed
as one of Russia's literary
Giants with masterpieces like War and
Peace and anakaren Tolstoy achieved what
most of us dream of success respect and
even a sense of
Legacy yet for all his accomplishments
he was consumed by an inner emptiness
that no amount of fame or Fortune could
fill in his 50s at the peak of his
career Tolstoy grappled with an intense
existential
crisis he realized everything he'd
believed in and worked for felt Hollow
like chasing
Shadows despite having the love of his
family the admiration of his readers and
a life of comfort Tolstoy couldn't
escape the haunting thought what is all
of this for it was a question that
brought him face to face with his
mortality and the fear that his life
might lack true meaning Tolstoy later
described his struggle as standing at
the edge of a precipice with nothing to
hold on to he saw Life as a fleeting
Journey where even the most most
significant achievements would be washed
away by time why am I here he
wondered what's my life's purpose and
why should I continue living if
everything I love and cherish will
ultimately fade
away this crisis wasn't merely
philosophical it tore at the foundations
of his life Tolstoy began questioning
everything his art relationships and
identity in his own words he felt
trapped in a cycle of Illusions deceived
by the world into believing that success
and Status had meaning but underneath he
sensed a more profound truth none
mattered this realization terrified him
yet it also awakened him to a profound
desire to find something that would last
and give him a reason to keep going
tolstoy's Quest To Find meaning was not
a simple
journey in his autobiography a
confession he describes the moment he
hit rock bottom writing my question that
which at the age of 50 brought me to the
verge of suicide was the simplest of
questions what will come of what I am
doing today or shall do
tomorrow he was searching for an answer
that wouldn't just make life tolerable
but would justify it Tolstoy found it
most unsettling that many around him
seemed at ease with life's uncertainty
never wondering about its
meaning in contrast Tolstoy was consumed
by the question he began observing The
Peasants around him noting that they
found comfort in their faith and the
simple routines of life this crisis
wasn't just internal it resonated
through his novels where his characters
grapple with similar
disillusionment in Anna Karenina Anna is
drawn into a passionate yet ultimately
destructive Affair believing it will
bring her happiness and freedom but in
the end her Pursuit leads only to
isolation Despair and
tragedy Anna's Journey mirrors tolstoy's
realization that untethered from any
higher purpose personal satisfaction
becomes a hollow pursuit in the end he
discovered a truth that was as simple as
it was
profound he realized that meaning could
be found not in Grand Pursuits or
intellectual answers but in Acts of
humility connecting with others and
accepting life as it is he wrote only by
merging myself with the whole life of
humanity could I find my life for
Tolstoy this Embrace of life's
interconnections the feeling that he was
part of something larger than himself
finally brought him peace tolstoy's
transformation didn't alter his beliefs
it reshaped his writing and
activism his later work Resurrection
reflects his intense criticism of social
institutions especially the judicial and
penal systems in this novel the main
character nek ludovi a moral Awakening
that mirrors tolstoy's own as he
recognizes his complicity in a system
that exploits and dehumanizes others
neov Journey illustrates tolstoy's
belief that true meaning lies not in the
Comforts of society but in an ethical
commitment to live justly no matter the
personal cost tolstoy's philosophy grew
more radical as he developed his ideas
on nonviolent resistance and simple
living which would later Inspire figures
like Gandhi and Martin Luther King Jr in
the kingdom of God is within you Tolstoy
argues government is violence
Christianity is meekness non-resistance
love he believed everyone was
responsible for rejecting the structures
of power and violence they saw around
them for Tolstoy the honest answer to
Life's purpose was not found in
intellectualism or materialism but in a
profound ethical commitment that
demanded we look inward to understand
our complicity in societal evils and
work tirelessly to live
morally so here's tolstoy's challenge to
each of us what is the purpose of your
life are you willing to confront that
question look beyond the achievements
possessions and distractions and see
what lies at the core of your
existence Tolstoy believed that meaning
comes when we live not for ourselves but
for others when we find purpose in love
humility and
connection if you've never taken a
moment to ask yourself this question
maybe now is the time tolstoy's wisdom
shows us that while the search for
meaning may be painful it's also the
path to True
fulfillment are you ready to take that
Journey
[Music]