what is 1pl
two I hate these stuff man uh 1pl
two oh
man I'm going to
say three mhm you sure not anymore and
how many hours are in two days 48 48 how
many hours are in three
days this maths
now 72 no that's
four was less than 72 71 uh
64 in 3 days yeah no it's not at all no
seven seven takeway six sorry seven
takeway six is minus one and how did you
get to that if you could explain to the
public oh man uh gcsc maths shout out
miss little miss little T you that yeah
man
okay Miss little man cuz he done a good
job miss little he SP the word scissors
scissors
x
e I'm confused bro why you confused I'm
confused cus cus cus cus X
is yeah it spells Financial
Financial okay f i n a n c c e
Finance what you spelling Financial
Financial okay s u r o
e s u r o e yeah no F no f i a f sorry f
i f i n a n c e s u s u r o r e
Financial no no no I'm I'm wrong you're
wrong K SP the word scissors scissors
scissors s e a s e a no
scissor scissors scissors
scissors s
e I
have is Asia a country or a continent
Asia yeah yeah it's a continent it's a
continent okay can you explain the
meaning of Life Meaning of Life yeah uh
that's difficult bro we just want to
live the life so I'm not that much
experienced so I just want to live the
life I will say after just 10 years
something like that I will say the
meaning for the life maybe I'm just
started to live the life right now yeah
I just want to experience all the things
so if I go gone through all these things
I will I will be capable to say the
meaning for the life but I'm not the
person right now to experience like to
say the meaning for the life maybe
that's the thing that's the point of
view from me what age you you think you
can explain the meaning for the life
maybe 40 40s 50s Maybe yeah what's 8 * 8
oh can can you sp the word I beef for
no so are you sure you what I Bea
no have a good day cheers in what planet
can you find natural water natural water
uh which planet yeah
um I would have said well what you know
yeah well natural natural or yeah yeah
yeah which planet which plan
um
UK is that a
planet yeah oh yeah yeah UK is a planet
well I would assume so yeah yeah right
now we are getting some smart people and
some not so smart people but you know
what at the end of it doesn't matter if
you're smart or not it's about what's in
here at the end of the day and uh yeah
um make sure you to like make sure you
continue to subscribe and um yeah let me
ask this gentleman over here as well
excuse me sir can I ask you a quick
question please thanks yeah no thanks no
no worries no worries no worries no
worries
yeah yeah you you what does what does
DIY stand for what is that what is 3 * 2
three times two
five I've seen you oh
thank you 3 time 2 is five what the f
excuse me sir we're going around asking
people what is three times
two nine you add 10 years to the year
1999 what year are we in now so you add
10 years on top of 1999 yeah probably
like
2009 you sure probably yeah that's
correct that's correct that's correct
what do you think the UK is missing out
on probably a lot of things yeah cost a
pet not to come back down you drive no I
am going for my
license first of all how small are you
from 1 to 10
Steve I'll say a five I'll sit on the
fence come on be more believe in
yourself man believe in yourself man you
know what I so so so you're five then
sitting on the fence five okay hopefully
that fence don't break okay so the first
question
is what's 11 + 1 11 + 1 is 12 12 correct
correct who was the first black
president of
America
uh uh that [\h__\h] Martin Luther King
Martin Luther King the first black
president I don't know is Asia a country
or
continent I will say it's a cont
continent I'm already guessing on that
part so it's
like could be a contra
but depends how you look at it how do
you look at it see as a
country but I could be wrong it could be
a continent where got midle
Asia all that thank you for your time
sir you got a lot to say as well cheers
have a good day yeah
cheers depends how you look at at the
end of the day could be a cont could be
a continent who knows at the end of the
day you know same way that the planet
like we're we're in a planet UK is the
same way that Asia could be a country or
continent you
know what's 44 divided by
two 21 21 21 it took me far too long to
figure that out it means can drink in
America though
yay so 44 divid by 2 is what oh that's
22 you got it wrong did you it's been a
long weekend oh what's been happening
man talk to
me my wife who doesn't normally drink
did drink went to a pant house slagged
off the flat slagged off his children
and somehow came out okay spilled beans
on the floor and it's Monday how are you
is Asia a country or continent it's a
continent I'm not
American you're not American no which
means I know what a continent is oh so
Americans yeah I get it you yeah they
have passports I know yeah yeah yeah and
that that's the reason I'd like to
travel to Mars or the moon soon because
yeah yeah this decade's been a piece of
let's call it dog tofe sh we yeah dog
tofe I like that lingo thank you thank
you cheers that was the most random
interview I've ever had in my life what
brother said dog tofe that's a new lingo
dog tofe dog tropy is a new lingo so
Danny um how small are you from 1 to 10
1 to 10 probably 10 my bro I hope
hopefully 10 yeah how many hours are in
2 days in 2 days 48 yeah that's correct
that's correct and you add you add 10
years to the year 1999
what year are we in now what year are we
in now
2024 no where's closer to the Earth the
moon or the Sun the moon or the Sun
closer to the
Earth I don't actually know this one but
I'm going to say the sun mhm could be
wrong yeah and why is why why do you
think it's the sun if you could explain
it to the public I don't know the sun
just seems more positive to me how many
ears do dogs normally
have like
what does the DIY stand
for uh do it yourself yes correct
correct what 14 -
eight
joia
yeah yeah okay that's great was uh
what's nine take away nine zero what's 1
plus one
two that's M it yeah yeah did you learn
all this it's general knowledge is it
supposed to know this supposed to know
this what's 12 * 2 24 yeah that's
correct that's correct and what's 12
ided by two and 12 divid by 2 six six
yes that's correct that's correct what
is the square root of 81 square root of
81 yeah nine nine yeah yeah and what um
name me uh five countries in uh Europe
and Switzerland Spain England and and
then
Sweden and after Sweden Germany that's
yes correct