[Music]
we feel some pretty huge questions on
the podcast like this one from a woman
named abijah who's going through a lot
dear pastor john hello so i've been
dealing with much
in my life which has been really hard
for the past three years
normally i could face life's challenges
with the assurance that god was in
control
and that i could trust him but beginning
in 2018 i started to get really
depressed about the whole
meaning of life and my own life purpose
it was in the midst
of my challenges that i lost someone i
really loved
and it broke me like nothing ever has my
entire view of god in life has been
shattered i can't seem to get myself out
of wondering why life is even a thing
life at least my life often feels like
it has
no meaning can you renew my vision for
life can you explain to me
what is the meaning of life
abijah i hear three
distinct and interrelated sorrows
that have brought you to this place of
doubt about the meaning of your life i
hear
depression i hear loss i hear
a kind of fixation in your mind you say
i can't seem to get myself out of
wondering why life is even a thing
in other words the tape keeps playing
over and over in your mind
is life really significant at all
or is it just a meaningless jumble
coming from nowhere going nowhere
nothing in between but randomness so i
take your question your plea
very seriously i have tasted a little
bit of what you're talking about
and i know others who have tasted all of
what you're talking about
i have seen myself come through i have
seen others come through and i believe
you can come through you can come out
into the light of confidence in god
confidence in christ confident
in the certain purpose that god has for
this world the wise
good just holy
purpose that god has for this world and
your place
in it even in the words that you use
abide you you put your finger on the
meaning
of life you say you are depressed about
the whole meaning of your life
and your own purpose
and i think that's right i think you're
absolutely right that
meaning consists in purpose
a good purpose a wise just satisfying
purpose or design for you for the world
so the whole question is does the world
with all of its
beauty and ugliness gladness
and groaning love and hate
pleasure and pain nobility and
vulgarity kindness and abuse
selfishness and sacrifice does
such a world as ours have a wise
good just satisfying
purpose under the providence of an
all-wise all-powerful
god or was the atheist bertrand russell
right at the end of his life when he
said
there is darkness without and when i die
there will be darkness within
there is no splendor no vastness
anywhere only
triviality for a moment and then
nothing are the words of macbeth
in shakespeare's play when he hears
about his wife's death are those words
true are they a reflection of reality
when he said out out brief candle
life's but a walking shadow a poor
player that struts and frets his
hour upon the stage and then is heard no
more
it's a tale told by an idiot
full of sound and fury signifying
nothing about you
i think one of the common strategies of
satan
whom you know is a thief and a murderer
he steals truth from the mind he kills
the soul
one of his common strategies is to
fixate our mind
on such possibilities life is a tale
told by an idiot isn't it full of sound
and
fury signifying nothing satan doesn't
even care if you believe that
he just wants you to be fixated on it to
think about it all the time and
wonder if it might be true he wants to
steal
from you and me every
vestige of confidence that god is wise
and
good and just and holy and
that god is working everything together
for a great
purpose so my purpose right now in this
past pastor john
is to pray for you
that you would have power to resist the
devil
and that i could put a sword
the sword of the spirit in your hand
so that you could do battle valiantly
and triumphantly against the darkness
the sword of the spirit you know this
the sword of the spirit
is the word of god god knew
when he wrote his book god knew that you
would go through this god knew about
your depression he knew about your loss
he knew about the fixation of doubt in
your mind
and he wrote about these things over and
over again in his word to help you
and all of us the meaning of life
according to that word god's word
is to know god as he really is
and to enjoy him and all that he is for
us in christ
and to reflect in this dark world
some of the light that he has shown to
us when christ
the very son of god died in our place
precisely that we might know god and
enjoy god in spite of our sin
and then one day see him and know him
perfectly
unendingly let me say it again
the meaning of life is to know god
and to enjoy god and reflect
some of the beauty of god as we know him
in christ
and one day see him perfectly
and unendingly enjoy him
the meaning of life now the purpose of
life
in this age is not
comfort in this world now
nor escape from suffering
now nor the avoidance of loss
now nor the maximizing of physical
pleasures
now nor the amassing of riches
now nor the achievement of any fame
now nor the right to any health
now nor that we would be treated with
respect and justice
now those are not the meaning
of life in this age for god's people
once sin entered the world and
everything was corrupted
and once god's saving purposes began to
rescue people from sin
the glorious and beautiful purposes of
this creation
were thrust forward into the time
when christ would come again and set
everything right
a time of perfect righteousness a time
of perfect peace a new creation
with no crying or pain anymore
so that over and over again in the
scriptures we are told
to rejoice in hope like romans 5
2 rejoice in hope of the glory
of god this present world
is primarily a season of testing
and a refiner's fire
if this world is all there is
then life is surely meaningless the
bible says let's eat drink and be merry
for tomorrow we'd die if there's no
resurrection from the dead
first corinthians 15 32
so the apostle paul said i consider
that the sufferings of this present time
are
not worth comparing with the glory that
is to be revealed to us
in romans 8 18. and again he said
this light momentary affliction
i'm thinking of your loss abidja for
example
this light momentary affliction
is preparing for us an eternal
weight of glory beyond all comparison
second corinthians 4 17 and the apostle
peter put it most fully and clearly
he said in chapter one verse five
by god's power you are being
guarded through faith for a salvation
ready to be revealed in the last time
in this this coming sure
remedy for all ills this salvation
in this you rejoice though now
for a little while if necessary you have
been grieved by
various trials oh abide ya
that's your life right that word various
trials means
all kinds of trials literally many
colors of trials and tests
so that the tested genuineness of your
faith
more precious than gold which though
perishable is tested by fire
may result in praise and glory and honor
at the revelation of jesus christ
what an amazing interpretation of this
world and our place in it the meaning of
suffering
in this life is the refinement of
faith by the fires of various
trials that we might know god
love god show god as more precious
than everything that the fires consume
jesus christ suffered precisely to bring
us
through these fiery trials
refined and purified into the very
presence of god for our eternal joy
first peter 3 18 so i close
abidja with an illustration
when covet 19 shut up my wife and me
someone gave us a puzzle with a
thousand pieces they thought we would
need something to do
i spread it out on two card tables
and in the interludes between my work i
would just pause there and try to find a
piece or two to put together i began
with the confidence these thousand
chaotic pieces
piled in the middle of the table would
one day be
that beautiful picture on the box
from bedlam to beauty from chaos to
order yes that's gonna come
i saw the picture on the box it was a
kind of promise
but one day i had the border almost
entirely completed that's the way i
started do the border
almost entirely completed everything
fitting together
but it wouldn't fit it was just one or
piece one or two pieces that wouldn't
fit
and i was sure a piece was missing i
looked all over the floor
or maybe they made the puzzle wrong it's
defective
i went through time after time
systematically looking at all the pieces
i put them in rows so i could see
i became fixated on the fact this
puzzle is not going to work this puzzle
is defective
then my wife came over and she sat down
and she looked at all the edge pieces
that i had put together
and she said i don't think these two
pieces go together
that you have fastened here they almost
go together i don't think they go
together
i look at it they're perfect they go
they said no i don't think so and she
took my puzzle apart
and she uncoupled the pieces that i had
spent hours finding
and she rearranged the pieces and she
put them back together and
it fit perfect there was no lost peace
there was no defect there was just
fallible me so
my prayer about you is that this
asked pastor john would perhaps come to
you
the way my wife came to me and showed me
johnny your fixation on the imperfection
of this puzzle
and that the makers blew it that's
out of place they really do fit
this is going to be a beautiful picture
just keep at it
trust the promise that's on the box
there it's true
the sufferings of this life are not
worth comparing
to the glory that will be revealed great
perspective thank you pastor john
sobering situation but god is sovereign
good and for his children he is doing
eternally good things in all of our
lives even in the hardest of life
situations
thank you pastor john for that reminder
we now break for the weekend and next
week we will begin with a very simple
question but a great one
from a listener named maxine maxine
wants to know
who wrote the bible
who wrote the bible man some great
questions of late coming into the inbox
pastor john will explain
his answer to us on monday i'm tony
rankine thanks for listening to the
podcast and we will see you then have a
great weekend