the Joe Rogan experience cause dealing
with a question of stupid topic but the
meaning of life right what's the thing
how could that be stupid though well
it's right it's trite you're not
supposed to think about it it's
something you ask your parents and
you're young they tell you don't worry
about it
or they still get a job yeah exactly
good job you frickin hippie or here's
God God is the meaning of life right and
so I was just trying to resolve for
myself like what could the answer be
right not what is the answer but what
could the answer be and so at a core
level I was forced to kind of hunting
down all these weird little things and
really understand for myself it's got to
be personal
right but I'd established for myself
what it could and could not be and that
gave me some level of peace so now I
don't have to keep asking that question
what is the meaning of life I mean
youyou I think the question is more
interesting than the answer everyone
should explore this on their own but let
me just explore a few parts with you
right
so first is if I gave you an answer if I
said the meaning of life is to please
God well which God okay judeo-christian
God well okay why that one why this
thing the problem is it's a why question
you can keep asking why forever right
any answer I give you you just ask why
again why again why good that's right
and you end up in a place called a grip
astre lemma
okay this is a philosophical exercise
but I kind of thought it through then
googled around and there's a thing
called a grip astre lemma and a grip was
trilemma says that any questioning like
this Y will always end in one of three
places okay
first is infinite regress right why
because of this why that what and just
keep playing from eminent the second is
circular reasoning
well a why a because it B or Y be
because of a get trapped in that or the
third is an axiom and the most popular
axiom is God but it could be anything
because of math because the science
because the Big Bang because the
simulation right these are all axioms
these are all just stopping points the
same simulation we're in a simulation or
saying it's the Big Bang it's just
another way of saying god it's just
God's a dirty word so we don't use it as
much anymore but same thing so you end
up in one of these three dead ends
essentially right so there is no answer
the real answer is because
[Laughter]
you get to make up your own answers the
beauty if there was a single answer we
would not be free we would be trapped
because then we would all have to live
to that answer then we'd be Borg like
robots each one competing with each
other to fulfill that single meaning
more than the others back to signaling
like I'm better at it than you are but
luckily there is no answer so you just
do whatever you want the meaning of life
it's funny that that would let that's
the basis of all existential angst that
you don't you don't know why you're here
and you have this feeling that it could
be meaning less it is I mean if you when
you start pondering the the multiverse
the universe the galaxies the solar
system the planet the organism the cells
inside the organism the bacteria the
parasites okay there's symbiotic
relationship we have to our environment
and you start going Jesus Christ what am
I just a little piece of this thing it's
like well the answer is still all the
great questions are paradoxes yeah so
for example you're asking like do i
matter that's like really the question
you asked right well how do i matter in
this infinite universe well you know on
the one hand you're separate no two
points are the same every point is every
two points are infinitely different
you're completely separated no one will
have your thoughts your emotions your
feelings your experience so your life is
a single-player game you're trapped
inside your head and you're just aware
of a bunch of things going on and that's
it on the other hand I cannot say the
words Joe Rogan without invoking the
entire universe Joe rogue alien comes
along says what's that Joe Rogan what's
Joe Rogan's a human what's a human
bipedal ape what's an ape on the earth
what's the earth planet what's a planet
solar system where was the carbon made
inside stars right instead I have to
create the entire universe to just say
the words Joe Rogan so in that sense
you're connected to everything it's
inseparable so the answer to that
question of do I matter is I am nothing
and I am everything and you'll find this
with all the great questions the answers
are all paradoxes which is why it's some
level it's sort of pointless to pursue
them to find a trite answer like I'm
giving but the act of pursuing them is
actually really useful because then it
gives you certain intrinsic
understanding in your life that brings a
level of peace