what if there is no
purpose and there is no purpose life is
a purpose unto itself it doesn't need
any
purpose this question comes up because
you have not tasted the Grandeur of life
this question comes up because you have
not realized the immensity of what it
means to be human it's too fabulous it's
too fantastic it's stupendous why would
you ask why
right now it's
meager here and there there are some
experiences to keep your life going rest
of it is too meager getting up in the
morning going to the toilet cooking
breakfast eating going to the office if
every moment of your life becomes
absolutely exuberant and bursting within
you why would be a ridiculous question
isn't it